<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- name="generator" content="blosxom/2.0" -->

<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>David A. Wheeler's Blog   </title>
    <meta name="viewport" content="width=device-width, initial-scale=1.0"></meta>
    <link>https://www.dwheeler.com/blog</link>
    <description>David A. Wheeler's weblog.</description>
    <language>en</language>

  <item>
    <title>FCC Votes against the People and Net Neutrality: Freedom is Slavery</title>
    <meta name="viewport" content="width=device-width, initial-scale=1.0"></meta>
    <link>https://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2017/11/23#net-neutrality-freedom</link>
    <pubDate>Thu, 23 Nov 2017 22:06 GMT</pubDate>
    <!-- date: 2017-11-23 -->
    <description>
&lt;p&gt;
To the surprise of no one, the US FCC led by Ajit Pai has finally
issued the order to kill net neutrality.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In short, the FCC is voting to directly
harm the US people and instead aid the monopolist
Intenet Service Providers (ISPs).
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.techdirt.com/articles/20171122/09473038669/fcc-releases-net-neutrality-killing-order-hopes-youre-too-busy-cooking-turkey-to-read-it.shtml&quot;&gt;More information is on Tech Dirt&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This is inexcusable.
Competition is often the best way to get good results,
but for various reasons customers often cannot practically choose ISPs;
in many cases they are essentially monopolies or duopolies.
Where competition does not effectively exist, there must be
regulation to prevent the monopolists from exploiting their customers,
and the FCC has decided to expressly reject their duty to the
people of the United States.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Orwell would be proud of the order&amp;#8217;s name,
&amp;#8220;Restoring Internet Freedom&amp;#8221;.
Remember, Freedom is Slavery!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#8217;m sure we have not heard the end of this.
This entire process was filled with fraud, with sock puppets proposing
to end net neutrality while real people were ignored.
All Americans need to make it clear to their representatives that
Internet access is important, and that ISPs must be required to neutral
carriers, instead of giving preferences to some sites or charging extra
for some sites.
I recommend
voting against any representatives who fail to protect Internet access,
as the FCC has failed to do.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
   </item>
  </channel>
</rss>