<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- name="generator" content="blosxom/2.0" -->

<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>David A. Wheeler's Blog   </title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog</link>
    <description>David A. Wheeler's weblog.</description>
    <language>en</language>

  <item>
    <title>New Hampshire: Open source, open standards, open data</title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2012/02/06#new-hampshire</link>
    <pubDate>Mon, 06 Feb 2012 01:05 GMT</pubDate>
    <!-- date: 2012-02-06 -->
    <description>
&lt;p&gt;
The U.S. state of New Hampshire just passed act &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nhliberty.org/bills/view/2012/HB418&quot;&gt;HB418 (2012)&lt;/a&gt;, which requires state agencies to consider open source software, promotes the use of open data formats, and requires the commissioner of information technology (IT) to develop an open government data policy.
&lt;a href=&quot;http://yro.slashdot.org/story/12/02/04/2259227/new-hampshire-passes-open-source-bill&quot;&gt;Slashdot has a posted discussion about it&lt;/a&gt;.
This looks really great, and it looks like a bill
that other states might want to emulate.
My congrats go to
&lt;a href=&quot;http://yro.slashdot.org/comments.pl?sid=2654797&amp;cid=38931519&quot;&gt;Seth Cohn&lt;/a&gt; (the primary author) and the many others who made this happen.
In this post I&amp;#8217;ll walk through some of its key points on
open source software, open standards for data formats,
and open government data.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
First, here&amp;#8217;s what it says about open source software (OSS):
&amp;#8220;For all software acquisitions, each state agency&amp;#8230; shall&amp;#8230; Consider whether proprietary or open source software offers the most cost effective software solution for the agency, based on consideration of all associated acquisition, support, maintenance, and training costs&amp;#8230;&amp;#8221;.
Notice that this law does not mandate that the state government
&lt;i&gt;must&lt;/i&gt; always use OSS.
Instead, it simply requires government agencies to &lt;i&gt;consider&lt;/i&gt; OSS.
You&amp;#8217;d think this would be useless, but you&amp;#8217;d be wrong.
Fairly considering OSS is still remarkably hard to do
in many government agencies,
so having a law or regulation clearly declare this is very valuable.
Yes, closed-minded people can claim they &amp;#8220;considered&amp;#8221; OSS and paper over
their biases, but laws like this make it easier for OSS to get a fair hearing.
The law defines &amp;#8220;open source software&amp;#8221; (OSS) in a way consistent
with its usual technical definition, indeed, this law&amp;#8217;s definition
looks a lot like the free software definition.
That&amp;#8217;s a good thing; the impact of laws and regulations is often
controlled by their definitions, so having good definitions (like this one
for OSS) is really important.
Here&amp;#8217;s the New Hampshire definition of OSS, which I think is a good one:
&lt;ol type=&quot;a&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;#8221;Unrestricted use of the software for any purpose;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unrestricted access to the respective source code;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Exhaustive inspection of the working mechanisms of the software;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Use of the internal mechanisms and arbitrary portions of the software, to adapt them to the needs of the user;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Freedom to make and distribute copies of the software; and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Modification of the software and freedom to distribute modifications of the new resulting software, under the same license as the original software.&amp;#8221;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The material on open standards for data says,
&amp;#8220;The commissioner shall assist state agencies in the purchase or creation of data processing devices or systems that comply with open standards for the accessing, storing, or transferring of data&amp;#8230;&amp;#8221;
The definition is interesting, too; it defines an &amp;#8220;open standard&amp;#8221; as
a specification &amp;#8220;for the encoding and transfer of computer data&amp;#8221; 
that meets a long list of requirements, including that it is
&amp;#8220;Is free for all to implement and use in perpetuity, with no royalty or fee&amp;#8221;
and that it
&amp;#8220;Has no restrictions on the use of data stored in the format&amp;#8221;.
The list is actually much longer; it&amp;#8217;s clear that the authors were trying to
counter common vendor tricks who try to create &amp;#8220;open&amp;#8221; standards that
really aren&amp;#8217;t.
I think it would have been great if they had adopted the more stringent
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.digistan.org/open-standard:definition&quot;&gt;Digistan
definition of open standard&lt;/a&gt;, but this is still a great step forward.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Finally, it talks about open government data, e.g., it requires that
&amp;#8220;The commissioner shall develop a statewide information policy based on the following principles of open government data&amp;#8221;.
This may be one of the most important parts of the bill,
because it establishes these as the open data principles:
&lt;ol type=&quot;a&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;#8221;Complete. All public data is made available, unless subject to valid privacy, security, or privilege limitations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Primary. Data is collected at the source, with the highest possible level of granularity, rather than in aggregate or modified forms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Timely. Data is made available as quickly as necessary to preserve the value of the data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Accessible. Data is available to the widest range of users for the widest range of purposes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Machine processable. Data is reasonably structured to allow automated processing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nondiscriminatory. Data is available to anyone, with no requirement of registration.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nonproprietary. Data is available in a format over which no entity has exclusive control, with the exception of national or international published standards.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;License-free. Data is not subject to any copyright, patent, trademark, or trade secret regulation. Reasonable privacy, security, and privilege restrictions may be allowed.&amp;#8221;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The official motto of the U.S. state of New Hampshire
is &amp;#8220;Live Free or Die&amp;#8221;.
Looks like they truly do mean to live free.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
   </item>
  </channel>
</rss>