<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- name="generator" content="blosxom/2.0" -->

<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>David A. Wheeler's Blog   </title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog</link>
    <description>David A. Wheeler's weblog.</description>
    <language>en</language>

  <item>
    <title>Z3 is OSS!</title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2015/03/27#z3-oss</link>
    <pubDate>Fri, 27 Mar 2015 08:45 GMT</pubDate>
    <!-- date: 2015-03-27 -->
    <description>
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Z3Prover/z3&quot;&gt;Z3&lt;/a&gt; has been released as
&lt;a href=&quot;http://opensource.org/&quot;&gt;open source software&lt;/a&gt; under the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://opensource.org/licenses/MIT&quot;&gt;MIT license&lt;/a&gt;!
This is great news.
Z3 is a good satisifiability modulo theories (SMT) solver /
theorem prover from Microsoft Research.
An SMT solver accepts a set of constraints
(such as &amp;#8220;a&amp;lt;5 and a&amp;gt;1&amp;#8221;) and tries to produce values that
satisfy all the constraints.
A satisfiability (SAT) solver does this too, but SAT solvers can only
work with boolean variables;
SMT solvers can handle other types, such as integers.
&lt;a href=&quot;http://rise4fun.com/z3/tutorial&quot;&gt;Here is a Z3 tutorial&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
SMT solvers are basically lower-level tools that have many uses
for building larger capabilities, because many problems
require solving logical formulas to find a solution.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I am particularly interested in the use of SMT solvers
to help prove that programs do something or do not do something.
&lt;a href=&quot;http://why3.lri.fr/&quot;&gt;Why3&lt;/a&gt; is a platform that lets you
write programs and their specifications, and then calls out to
various provers to try to determine if the claims are true.
By itself Why3 only supports its WhyML language, but Why3 can be combined
with other tools to prove statements in other languages.
Those include C (using Frama-C and a plug-in), Java, and Ada.
People have been able to prove tiny programs for decades, but scaling up
to bigger programs in practice requires a lot of automation.
I think this approach of combining many different tools, with
different strengths, is very promising.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The more tools that are available to Why3, the more likely it will
solve problems automatically.
That&amp;#8217;s because different tools use different heuristics and focus on
different issues, resulting in different ones being good at different things.
There are already several good SMT solvers available as OSS,
including
&lt;a href=&quot;http://cvc4.cs.nyu.edu/web/&quot;&gt;CVC4&lt;/a&gt;
and
&lt;a href=&quot;http://alt-ergo.lri.fr/&quot;&gt;alt-ergo&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now that Microsoft has released Z3 as OSS, there is yet another
strong OSS SMT solver that tools like Why3 can use directly.
In short, the collection of OSS SMT solvers has just become even stronger.
There&amp;#8217;s a standard for SMT solver inputs, the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.smt-lib.org/&quot;&gt;SMT-LIB format&lt;/a&gt;,
so it&amp;#8217;s not hard to take advantage of many SMT solvers.
My hope is that this will be another step in making it easier to
have strong confidence in software.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
   </item>
  <item>
    <title>Plans for HTTPS (SSL/TLS) on this site</title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2015/03/11#https</link>
    <pubDate>Wed, 11 Mar 2015 19:50 GMT</pubDate>
    <!-- date: 2015-03-11 -->
    <description>
&lt;p&gt;
Currently this website uses only HTTP, and does not support HTTPS.
That means that users cannot trivially authenticate what they receive, and
that in some cases users reveal to others what they are viewing on the site.
(Technical note:
HTTPS is implemented by a lower-level protocol; the current protocol
versions of this protocol are named TLS, and the older ones
are named SSL, but a lot of people use the term SSL to include TLS.)
I would &lt;i&gt;like&lt;/i&gt; to use HTTPS, but this website is entirely self-funded.
I do have a plan, though.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
My current plan is that I am waiting for
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2014/11/certificate-authority-encrypt-entire-web&quot;&gt;Let&amp;#8217;s encrypt&lt;/a&gt; to stand up and be ready.
Once that gets going, I intend to use it to add support for HTTPS.
I&amp;#8217;d like to eventually &lt;i&gt;only&lt;/i&gt; support HTTPS, since that prevents
downgrade attacks, but I need to make sure that the TLS certificates
and configuration works well.
Also, I pay others to maintain the server;
since I am not made of money, I necessarily use low-end cheap services.
That will limit what I can do in terms of HTTPS configuration hardening.
On the other hand, it should be better than the current situation.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The &lt;i&gt;software&lt;/i&gt; I develop is generally
available on SourceForge or GitHub, and they already provide HTTPS,
so you don&amp;#8217;t need to wait for that.
Currently
&lt;a href=&quot;https://sourceforge.net/p/forge/site-support/9807&quot;&gt;you
have to log into SourceForge to get HTTPS&lt;/a&gt;, but that is expected to change,
and for now just log in.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Anyway, I thought some of you might like to know that there &lt;i&gt;is&lt;/i&gt; a plan.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
   </item>
  </channel>
</rss>