<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- name="generator" content="blosxom/2.0" -->

<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>David A. Wheeler's Blog   </title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog</link>
    <description>David A. Wheeler's weblog.</description>
    <language>en</language>

  <item>
    <title>Democracy Requires Verified Voting</title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2004/06/14#verifiedvoting</link>
    <pubDate>Mon, 14 Jun 2004 10:37 GMT</pubDate>
    <!-- date: 2004-06-14 -->
    <description>
I&amp;#8217;m a strong advocate of democracy, but democracy
only works if a small group of people can&amp;#8217;t
rig the outcome.
Sadly, that&amp;#8217;s no longer true;
many counties have unwisely begun installing
computerized voting systems that cannot be verified,
and in fact are &lt;i&gt;untrustworthy&lt;/i&gt;.
&lt;p&gt;
That means a &lt;i&gt;single person&lt;/i&gt; could determine who wins or
loses a given election, by simply modifying the reports
from unverifiable computers.
By adding just a few lines of code to a voting program, or breaking
into one (experts have generally reported them to be easy to break into),
you could make an unverifiable voting system say whatever you wanted it to say.
That&amp;#8217;s nonsense.
&lt;p&gt;
The paperless electronic voting systems have already demonstrated
that they can never be trusted;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://edition.cnn.com/2004/TECH/06/11/league.electronicvoti.ap/&quot;&gt;
here are a few examples from CNN&lt;/a&gt;:
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&amp;#8220;In a January special election for a Florida state house seat, 134 people using
paperless voting terminals in Broward County failed to cast votes for any
candidate. The race was decided by a margin of 12 votes. It&amp;#8217;s unclear why some
voters didn&amp;#8217;t select candidates; and without a paper trail, poll workers
couldn&amp;#8217;t figure out voters&amp;#8217; intentions.
&lt;li&gt;
In North Carolina&amp;#8217;s 2002 general election, a software bug deleted 436
electronic ballots from six paperless machines in two counties. Election
Systems &amp; Software Inc., which built the terminals, determined that the
machines erroneously thought their memories were full and stopped counting
votes, even though voters kept casting ballots.
&lt;li&gt;
Earlier this year, California Secretary of State Kevin Shelley banned the use
of a paperless system made by Diebold Inc. after he found uncertified software
and other problems that &amp;#8220;jeopardized&amp;#8221; the outcome of elections in several
counties. At least 20 states have introduced legislation requiring a paper
record of every vote cast.&amp;#8221;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As noted in the article
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nytimes.com/2004/06/13/opinion/13SUN1.html&quot;&gt;
Gambling on Voting&lt;/a&gt; (NY Times, June 13, 2004),
gambling equipment is &lt;i&gt;far&lt;/i&gt; more trustworthy than voting machines.
For example, the state has access to all gambling software
(electronic voting machine makers say their software is a trade secret),
and the machines are spot-checked to make sure that the software running
is what&amp;#8217;s registered.


&lt;p&gt;
What&amp;#8217;s needed, as a bare minimum, is
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.verifiedvoting.org&quot;&gt;verified voting&lt;/a&gt;.
The VerifiedVoting.org folks wisely advocate
the use of voter-verified paper ballots (VVPBs)
for all elections in the United States, so voters
can inspect individual permanent records of their ballots before they
are cast and so meaningful recounts may be conducted.
They also insist that electronic voting equipment and software
be open to public scrutiny and that random, surprise recounts be
conducted on a regular basis to audit election equipment.
Without these simple safeguards, we&amp;#8217;ll all be forced to say that
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.truemajority.org/voting.cfm&quot;&gt;the computer ate my vote&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;p&gt;
I urge anyone in a democratic country to ensure that these
minimal requirements of verified voting (by paper ballot) are met.
</description>
   </item>
  </channel>
</rss>