<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- name="generator" content="blosxom/2.0" -->

<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>David A. Wheeler's Blog   </title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog</link>
    <description>David A. Wheeler's weblog.</description>
    <language>en</language>

  <item>
    <title>Flawfinder version 1.27 released!</title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2007/01/16#flawfinder-1.27</link>
    <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jan 2007 23:41 GMT</pubDate>
    <!-- date: 2007-01-16 -->
    <description>
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#8217;ve released yet another new version of
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/flawfinder&quot;&gt;flawfinder&lt;/a&gt; - now
it&amp;#8217;s version 1.27.
Flawfinder is a simple program that examines C/C++ source code and
reports on likely security flaws in the program, ranked by risk level.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The big functional addition is that flawfinder can now
examine &lt;i&gt;just the changes&lt;/i&gt; in a program.
If you&amp;#8217;re modifying a big program, it can be overwhelming to view all
of the warnings flawfinder can produce&amp;#8230; but if you can look at only the
ones relevant to the change &lt;i&gt;you&lt;/i&gt; are making, it can be easier to handle.
My thanks to Sebastien Tandel - he suggested the feature, I replied
in a brief email describing how I thought it could be done, and
&lt;i&gt;in the same day&lt;/i&gt; he replied with code to implement it.
Wow, that&amp;#8217;s truly amazing.  His original patch only worked with Subversion;
I modified it so that it also works with GNU diff.
For this to work, you use the new &amp;#8220;&amp;#8212;patch&amp;#8221; option and give flawfinder
a patch file (in unified diff format) that describes the changes&amp;#8230; and
flawfinder will only report on the potential vulnerabilities on the
changed lines (or the lines immediately above and below them).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
An administrative change is that
&lt;a href=&quot;https://sourceforge.net/projects/flawfinder/&quot;&gt;
flawfinder is now hosted on SourceForge.net&lt;/a&gt;, with a mailing list
and a Subversion repository for code changes.
This should make it easier for people to discuss the program,
submit changes, and generally keep track of things.
And it also deals nicely with the &amp;#8220;what happens if he&amp;#8217;s hit by a bus&amp;#8221;
problem.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You can view the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/flawfinder/ChangeLog&quot;&gt;Flawfinder
ChangeLog&lt;/a&gt; for the details on the other changes.
It deals more gracefully with unreadable files and when there are zero
lines of code.
Also, it now skips by default any directories beginning with &amp;#8220;.&amp;#8221;;
this makes it work nicely with many SCM systems
(use &amp;#8220;&amp;#8212;followdotdir&amp;#8221; if you WANT it to enter such directories).
My thanks to Steve Kemp, cmorgan, and others.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For more info, or a copy,
just go to my
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/flawfinder&quot;&gt;original flawfinder home page&lt;/a&gt;
or the new
&lt;a href=&quot;https://sourceforge.net/projects/flawfinder/&quot;&gt;
flawfinder page on SourceForge.net&lt;/a&gt;.
Enjoy!
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
   </item>
  <item>
    <title>DRM Nonsense, HD DVD, AACS, and BackupHDDVD - why &amp;#8220;content protection&amp;#8221; doesn&amp;#8217;t</title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2007/01/07#drm-nonsense-hddvd</link>
    <pubDate>Sun, 07 Jan 2007 23:58 GMT</pubDate>
    <!-- date: 2007-01-07 -->
    <description>
&lt;p&gt;
Hollywood wants to prevent piracy - and that is understandable.
But in their zeal it sometimes appears that some who create movies or music
don&amp;#8217;t care what privacy, security, legal rights,
or laws of physics they try to violate.
And that is a real problem.
DRM proponents want to release digital information to people,
yet make it impossible to copy them.
Yet the whole point of digital processing is to enable perfect copies.
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.defectivebydesign.org/&quot;&gt;DRM (Digital Rights Management or
Digital Restrictions Management) is truly &amp;#8220;&lt;i&gt;defective
by design&lt;/i&gt;&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt;.
As others have said, DRM is an attempt to change water so it&amp;#8217;s not wet.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The recent reports about HD DVD are showing the folly of DRM in general.
HD DVD encrypts a movie, and then encrypts that movie key
many different times on the DVD as well - once for each player.
The theory here is that the movie industry could then revoke a player
key by simply not including that key on future DVDs.
I think the first time they try to actually do this, they&amp;#8217;ll see the
folly of it &amp;#8212; it would mean that millions of customers would suddenly
no longer have access to future movies through a device they purchased
that they expected to work with them.
Can anyone say &amp;#8220;class action lawsuit&amp;#8221;?  I knew you could!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
But it turns out that this idea has a fatal flaw technically, as shown by
&lt;a href=&quot;http://forum.doom9.org/showthread.php?t=119871&quot;&gt;
BackupHDDVD&lt;/a&gt;
(you can
see the &lt;a href=&quot;http://zavlakas.googlepages.com/BackupHDDVD.zip&quot;&gt;code&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.playfuls.com/news_05648_HD_DVDs_AACS_Protection_Bypassed_In_Only_8_Days.html&quot;&gt;comments&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/01/technology/01hack.html?ei=5088&amp;amp;en=38ddb2918d77f8a4&amp;amp;ex=1325307600&amp;amp;partner=rssnyt&amp;amp;emc=rss&amp;amp;pagewanted=print&quot;&gt;NY Times article&lt;/a&gt;, and
&lt;a href=&quot;http://hardware.slashdot.org/article.pl?sid=06/12/28/0259244&quot;&gt;
Slashdot discussion&lt;/a&gt;).
The code itself is no big deal - it just implements the decryption protocol,
which is publicly known anyway.
But the interesting trick is that the released software
requires the master decryption key for that specific movie,
and the implementor is claiming that he has
found a way to get this key from a player.
To be fair, he hasn&amp;#8217;t proven he can get such keys by actually sharing
any real keys, but let&amp;#8217;s presume that he is telling the truth; his
described method for getting them is very plausible.
Yet the implementor is &lt;i&gt;not&lt;/i&gt; revealing the player that he got this from
or the exact details of how he got them.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That&amp;#8217;s more clever than it first appears.
The creators of the DRM scheme assumed that
anyone who broke a player would reveal the player&amp;#8217;s private key.
But because BackupHDDVD&amp;#8217;s creator
doesn&amp;#8217;t reveal that key, he never reveals the player
he&amp;#8217;s broken into.  Since the DRM scheme masters
don&amp;#8217;t know which player was broken into, their revocation scheme won&amp;#8217;t work.
Many other revocation schemes for media use the same basic approach,
and so they would fall the same way.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Some Blu-ray folks are claiming that this shows their scheme works better,
because they can include additional crypto stuff on the media.
But this shows that they don&amp;#8217;t understand the nature of the problem;
it&amp;#8217;s not hard to implement the crypto interpreter, and since you wouldn&amp;#8217;t
know which player to revoke, you would give all the crypto interpreter
information away too.  They&amp;#8217;d just need to send around the decrypted
decryptor&amp;#8230; which would be trivially acquired.
Once again, DRM is doing nothing to stop piracy, but it&amp;#8217;s certainly
interfering in legitimate use.
Sorry, but water stays wet.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I do not approve of piracy.
I don&amp;#8217;t approve of murder, either, yet I approve of
the sale of steak knives and cleaning supplies&amp;#8230; and would
oppose trying to halt their sales.
Certainly the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cs.auckland.ac.nz/~pgut001/pubs/vista_cost.txt&quot;&gt;costs to consumers of DRM measures&lt;/a&gt; are considerable,
yet they are actively against the interests of customers.. and they
even fail to do the one thing they are supposed to do.
DRM proponents are often laughingly referred to as the
MAFIAA (Music And Film Industry Association of America), in part because
their actions towards their own customers seem actively hostile.
DRM seems to be primarily about preventing people from using in legitimate
ways the products they&amp;#8217;ve already purchased, and has nothing to do
with actually preventing illegal activities.
Why can&amp;#8217;t I transfer that music or movie I bought to a new
device I just bought?  Or to an old CD so I can play it
on older equipment?  Why can&amp;#8217;t I watch what I bought using
GNU/Linux or BSD systems?
Why can&amp;#8217;t I use a $3000 display&amp;#8217;s full resolution at all times
for movies I have legitimately bought?
Measures this extreme that create monopolies and inhibit legal activities
are not a good thing, and are worse than the piracy that DRM measures
are trying to prevent.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What&amp;#8217;s worse, the anti-consumer impacts of DRM don&amp;#8217;t even inhibit piracy.
The big piracy operations will
just continue to make direct copies of the bits using specialized
equipment, and DRM cannot affect that at all.
Individuals can make recordings of the displays
or sounds&amp;#8230; again, DRM can&amp;#8217;t really counteract that (there are anti-sync
measures for video, but they are easily foiled).
So DRM will fail against individuals, and against large-scale piracy, period.
Since DRM tries to prevent many legitimate uses, it also encourages
law-abiding citizens to break them&amp;#8230; and so far they&amp;#8217;ve all fallen,
given that additional incentive.
The fact that DRM is not even successful at doing what it&amp;#8217;s supposed to
do is just icing on the cake. Even if DRM worked, it is still
worse than the problems it is trying to stop.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
DRM is the disease, not the cure.
It&amp;#8217;s time for content industries to take advantage of technology, instead of
trying to halt the use of technology.
Instead of DRM, they should sell non-DRMed content using standards that
&lt;i&gt;everyone&lt;/i&gt; can implement&amp;#8230; and then they can sell their
content to a very large unified market.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
   </item>
  </channel>
</rss>