<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- name="generator" content="blosxom/2.0" -->

<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>David A. Wheeler's Blog   </title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog</link>
    <description>David A. Wheeler's weblog.</description>
    <language>en</language>

  <item>
    <title>Navy: Open Source Software IS Commercial Software</title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2007/07/18#navy-direction-unchanged</link>
    <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jul 2007 17:52 GMT</pubDate>
    <!-- date: 2007-07-18 -->
    <description>
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://oss-institute.org/Navy/DONCIO_OSS_User_Guidance.pdf&quot;&gt;
On June 5, 2007, the U.S.
Navy released some guidance on Open Source Software&lt;/a&gt;.
In particular, they noted that if
Open Source Software (OSS) met the U.S. law definition of &amp;#8220;commercial item&amp;#8221;,
it was a commercial item.
(They actually say OSS that meets that definition is
commercial off-the-shelf (COTS), not just a &amp;#8220;commercial item&amp;#8221; -
presumably because they had in mind the off-the-shelf
open source software.)
I&amp;#8217;m delighted to see this guidance, because
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/essays/commercial-floss.html&quot;&gt;
I&amp;#8217;ve been saying the same thing&lt;/a&gt;.
This Navy memo was pretty clear, yet
some people seemed to have really odd interpretations of it.
In particular,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gcn.com/print/26_14/44462-1.html?topic=defense-technology&amp;amp;CMP=OTC-RSS&quot;&gt;
GCN reported&lt;/a&gt; that
&amp;#8220;After several years of evaluation, the Navy Department has
approved the use of open-source software in all Navy and Marine Corps
information technology systems.&amp;#8221;
This GCN article
makes it seem like there&amp;#8217;s been some big change in direction,
and I think that&amp;#8217;s a terrible misunderstanding of what&amp;#8217;s going on here.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I believe this 2007 Navy memo is &lt;i&gt;not&lt;/i&gt; a change in policy or direction.
This Navy memo merely tries to counter a widespread misunderstanding that is
sometimes resulting in a failure to obey U.S. law, the U.S. government&amp;#8217;s
Federal Acquisition Regulations (aka the FAR), and (by
implication) the U.S. Department of Defense&amp;#8217;s (DoD)
Defense Federal Acquisition Regulation Supplement (DFARS).
This memo also serves as a restatement that
Navy policy continues to obey &lt;i&gt;existing&lt;/i&gt;
DoD and U.S. government policies
regarding open source software (OSS), as were already formally established in
2003-2004.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Below are some supporting details to justify those statements. I hope
they will help put this memo in context.
As is usual in any blog, my conclusions are just my own opinion,
not the official position of any organization.
On the other hand, I think I have really good evidence!
So let&amp;#8217;s see&amp;#8230;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Years ago some people had the strange idea that OSS was prohibited in
the DoD or U.S. federal government, even though there was no such
prohibition. This was particularly bizarre in the DoD, since a MITRE
report (final publication early 2003) found that OSS use was already
widespread and very helpful to the DoD.  That MITRE report concluded
that &amp;#8220;Neither the survey nor the analysis supports the premise that
banning or seriously restricting [Free / Open Source Software (FOSS)]
would benefit DoD security or defensive capabilities. To the contrary,
the combination of an ambiguous status and largely ungrounded fears that
it cannot be used with other types of software are keeping FOSS from
reaching optimal levels of use.&amp;#8221;:
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.terrybollinger.com/dodfoss/dodfoss_pdf_hyperlinked.pdf&quot;&gt;http://www.terrybollinger.com/dodfoss/dodfoss_pdf_hyperlinked.pdf&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So in May 2003 an official DoD policy memo (&amp;#8220;OSS in DoD&amp;#8221;) was released.
It affirmed that OSS was fine as long as it met the applicable DoD
requirements, just as any other kind of software had to meet the
applicable DoD requirements:
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.egovos.org/rawmedia_repository/822a91d2_fc51_4e6e_8120_1c2d4d88fa06?/document.pdf&quot;&gt;http://www.egovos.org/rawmedia_repository/822a91d2_fc51_4e6e_8120_1c2d4d88fa06?/document.pdf&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This problem was government-wide, so in July 2004, OMB released a
similar policy memo (M-04-16), which explicitly stated that U.S. federal
government acquisition policy was neutral about using OSS vs.
proprietary software. In particular, it said that government &amp;#8220;policies
are intentionally technology and vendor neutral, and to the maximum
extent practicable, agency implementation should be similarly neutral.&amp;#8221;:
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.whitehouse.gov/omb/memoranda/fy04/m04-16.html&quot;&gt;http://www.whitehouse.gov/omb/memoranda/fy04/m04-16.html&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Yet there still seemed to be some strange misunderstandings, in spite of
these 2003 and 2004 policy memos explicitly stating that U.S. DoD and
federal acquisition policies were neutral on the question of using OSS
vs. proprietary software (they merely had to obey the usual
requirements). More recently, these misunderstandings seem to revolve
around a failure to read and understand the term &amp;#8220;commercial item&amp;#8221; as
defined by U.S. Code Title 41, Chapter 7, section 403, as well as its
corresponding FAR text. These define a &amp;#8220;commercial item&amp;#8221; as an item
&amp;#8220;customarily used by the general public or by non-governmental entities&amp;#8221;
(i.e., they have uses not unique to a government) and have been &amp;#8220;sold,
leased, or licensed to the general public&amp;#8221;). It would seem obvious that
if OSS meets the U.S. law/FAR definition for a commercial item, it is a
commercial item for government acquisition purposes.  And nearly all
extant OSS  does indeed meet this definition; nearly all extant OSS
has non-government uses and are licensed to the public.
In addition, almost all  already-existing OSS software also meets the definition
of commercial-off-the-shelf (COTS), since they are commercial items
that are ALREADY available to the public (&amp;#8220;off the shelf&amp;#8221;).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The problem was that some acquisition programs were redefining the term
&amp;#8220;commercial item&amp;#8221; (and COTS) to exclude OSS competitors. These
redefinitions were in contradiction to the existing DoD and federal
government-wide explicit policy for neutrality regarding OSS, and in
contradiction to the clear definition of &amp;#8220;commercial item&amp;#8221; given in U.S.
law, the FAR, and by implication the DFARS. The Navy memo simply tries
to correct this misunderstanding, as well as re-iterating that the
existing DoD and federal government policy on OSS continues.  This Navy
memo was signed by Department of the Navy CIO Robert J. Carey on June 5,
2007, and titled &amp;#8220;Department of the Navy Open Source Software Guidance&amp;#8221;.
You can find the Navy memo here:
&lt;a href=&quot;http://oss-institute.org/Navy/DONCIO_OSS_User_Guidance.pdf&quot;&gt;http://oss-institute.org/Navy/DONCIO_OSS_User_Guidance.pdf&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The main implication of this definition of &amp;#8220;commercial item&amp;#8221; is that (as
required by law and the FAR) contractors and their subcontractors at all
tiers must do market research of the commercial market and consider ALL
their commercial options&amp;#8230; including the OSS options.   This is
certainly NOT a special preference for OSS, and ALL evaluation
characteristics for software are still valid (e.g., functionality, total
cost of ownership, quality, security, support, and flexibility). But in
cases where the OSS option is the better option, by policy the U.S.
government intends to take advantage of it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This approach makes sense, given the major changes that are happening
in the software industry.  In many market segments OSS programs are
the #1 or #2 product by market share, and OSS in aggregate now
represents billions of dollars of development effort.   Many
companies are developing OSS and/or selling commercial support
for OSS, including Red Hat, Novell, Sun Microsystems, IBM, and
MySQL AB.  Microsoft competes with some OSS programs, business models,
and licenses, but in other areas Microsoft uses, develops,
and encourages OSS (Microsoft&amp;#8217;s Windows includes
BSD-developed networking applications; Microsoft OSS projects include WiX and
IronPython; Microsoft runs the &amp;#8220;Codeplex&amp;#8221; website to encourage
OSS development on Windows).  In areas where they are appropriate
some major OSS programs have received the relevant Common Criteria
or FIPS 140-2 IT security certificates.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
OSS potentially affects how acquisition programs acquire software, but
acquisition programs should &lt;i&gt;expect&lt;/i&gt; to be affected by changes in relevant
commercial industries.  This was anticipated; the DoD policy memo
&amp;#8220;Commercial Acquisitions&amp;#8221; (Jan. 5, 2001) explains that the benefits of
commercial item acquisition include &amp;#8220;increased competition; use of
market and catalog prices; and access to leading edge technology and
&amp;#8216;non-traditional&amp;#8217; business segments&amp;#8221;.  In other words, DoD policy
anticipates that there WILL be &amp;#8220;non-traditional business segments&amp;#8221; - and
its policy is to embrace and exploit such changes where appropriate.
(Given its growth and breadth, it&amp;#8217;s become increasingly difficult to
argue that OSS is &amp;#8220;non-traditional&amp;#8221; anyway.)  AT&amp;L&amp;#8217;s &amp;#8220;Commercial Item
Handbook&amp;#8221; (November 2001) explains that this broad definition of
&amp;#8220;commercial item&amp;#8221; is intentional, because it &amp;#8220;enables the Government to
take greater advantage of the commercial marketplace.&amp;#8221; See:
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.acq.osd.mil/dpap/Docs/cihandbook.pdf&quot;&gt;http://www.acq.osd.mil/dpap/Docs/cihandbook.pdf&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In other words, U.S. contractors must consider &lt;i&gt;all&lt;/i&gt; their options,
and then
select the best one.  They are &lt;i&gt;not&lt;/i&gt; allowed to arbitrarily ignore a
relevant commercial industry sector, and are specifically &lt;i&gt;not&lt;/i&gt; allowed to
ignore OSS options.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you&amp;#8217;re interested in this topic,
you might also be interested in some related articles of mine, such as
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/essays/oss-government-acquisitions.html&quot;&gt;
Open Source Software (OSS) in U.S. Government Acquisitions&lt;/a&gt;
and
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/essays/commercial-floss.html&quot;&gt;
“Commercial” is not the opposite of Free-Libre / Open Source Software (FLOSS):
Nearly all FLOSS is Commercial&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
   </item>
  </channel>
</rss>