<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- name="generator" content="blosxom/2.0" -->

<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>David A. Wheeler's Blog   </title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog</link>
    <description>David A. Wheeler's weblog.</description>
    <language>en</language>

  <item>
    <title>George Mason University (GMU) Thesis/Dissertation Sample Document in OpenDocument Format</title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2007/04/18#gmu-sample-document</link>
    <pubDate>Wed, 18 Apr 2007 10:31 GMT</pubDate>
    <!-- date: 2007-04-18 -->
    <description>
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#8217;ve released a &amp;#8220;sample document&amp;#8221; that implements all the requirements of
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gmu.edu/library/specialcollections/dtabout.htm&quot;&gt;
George Mason University (GMU)&amp;#8217;s Thesis/Dissertation format&lt;/a&gt;
in the OpenDocument format.
You can get it in
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/misc/gmu-sample-format.odt&quot;&gt;OpenDocument&lt;/a&gt;
or
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/misc/gmu-sample-format.pdf&quot;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt; formats.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you&amp;#8217;re a student at GMU who needs it, you really need this.. but even
if you&amp;#8217;re not, there&amp;#8217;s lots that can be shown from this template.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
First, if you&amp;#8217;re a student at GMU who needs it, let me explain why you
&lt;i&gt;really&lt;/i&gt; need it.
Most universities have their own formats that have many detailed requirements,
so by using a pre-created format, you immediately comply with lots of the
details that are meaningless, yet you can&amp;#8217;t graduate without meeting them.
GMU requires page numbers to be on the top right, except at chapter headings
(where they are centered on the bottom)&amp;#8230; except that appendix chapter
headings aren&amp;#8217;t considered chapter headings.
Got all that?
GMU requires that there be a horizontal line between any
footnotes and the main text, and it must be exactly 2&amp;#8221; long.
Oh, and there are lots of margin requirements, which you must get exactly right.
Every university has its own oddnesses; this format, for example, is
explicitly single-sided, uses U.S. customary measurement units everywhere,
and has its own odd placement rules (e.g., appendixes must be placed
&lt;i&gt;after&lt;/i&gt;, not before, the bibliography).
Headings are 2&amp;#8221; from the top.. except that level 1 appendix headings aren&amp;#8217;t
considered headings.
It took me a long time of back-and-forth discussions with the GMU
dissertation and thesis coordinator to get all the details right.
(The problem wasn&amp;#8217;t that OpenDocument couldn&amp;#8217;t do it; the problem was
understanding what the GMU requirements actually were.)
You can spend many, many hours to redo these details&amp;#8230;
or just grab this sample document and have the problems solved for you.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
But whether you&amp;#8217;re a GMU student or not, there&amp;#8217;s lots that can be shown
from this template.
It certainly shows that OpenDocument is fully capable of representing
fairly complicated (and odd!) formats, for large documents,
completely automatically.
That shouldn&amp;#8217;t be surprising; one of the OpenDocument
developers was Boeing, who develop so many large documents
to build an airplane that the documents (when printed) outweigh the plane.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In particular, this document shows that an OpenDocument document can automate
all sorts of things, easing development:
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Just create a &amp;#8220;Heading 1&amp;#8221; (control-1 in OpenOffice.org) and the page format
automatically switches to first chapter format (with page numbering in
a different place).
&lt;li&gt;The spacing and text flow all happen automatically, without weird
artifacts like undesired &amp;#8220;extra&amp;#8221; vertical space on the top of a page.
In fact, nearly everything is very automatic - you can concentrate
on writing a paper, instead of fixing formats.
The entire document is based on &amp;#8220;paragraph styles&amp;#8221; - just make sure each
paragraph has the right style (which is nearly always correct), and the
document will look right.
&lt;li&gt;Tables of Contents, of tables, and figures can all be automatically
regenerated.
&lt;li&gt;Even the bibliography can be regenerated automatically, so that only
documents actually cited in the paper are listed. You can even
determine what order is appropriate
(e.g., alphabetically or in citation order).
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What&amp;#8217;s particularly amusing is to compare the OpenDocument template to
the GMU Word templates, because their Word templates are &lt;i&gt;horrible&lt;/i&gt;
to use.
GMU&amp;#8217;s Word templates are a bunch of individual files, completely
inappropriate for actual use by a writer. Even the first page of a chapter
and the rest of a chapter are in separate documents, and the
table of contents has to be regenerated by hand.
But even merging these files together won&amp;#8217;t completely solve the problem;
Word sometimes fails to correctly generate tables of contents
(it&amp;#8217;s happened to me!),
which is one reason why so many people hand-create tables of contents.
And Word certainly doesn&amp;#8217;t match other OpenDocument capabilities,
such as automated bibliography management.
What&amp;#8217;s worse, even though Word &lt;i&gt;does&lt;/i&gt; have paragraph styles, Word
seems to work especially hard to subvert and make their use difficult.
Word seems to love redefining all your carefully-crafted styles,
making Word painful to use as the document gets long.
In contrast, OpenDocument is a breeze to use (at least in
OpenOffice.org, and probably other OpenDocument-based systems as well) -
setting paragraph styles is trivial (and for the most part completely
automatic), once set they stay set, and they can make all the other
formatting decisions automatic.
Creating useful sample documents in Word is also painful;
I started and completed one in OpenDocument quite easily,
while GMU is still struggling to create a Word template.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You don&amp;#8217;t have to use OpenOffice.org to use OpenDocument, which is great -
choice and competition are good things.
But OpenOffice.org is a reasonable choice.
Bruce Byfield&amp;#8217;s articles
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.newsforge.com/article.pl?sid=04/10/04/150207&quot;&gt;
Replacing FrameMaker with OOo Writer&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a
href=&quot;http://software.newsforge.com/article.pl?sid=05/06/14/2137222&quot;&gt;
OpenOffice.org Writer vs. Microsoft Word&lt;/a&gt;
showed that OpenOffice.org is remarkably capable, especially in its word
processor.
Byfield&amp;#8217;s comparison of OpenOffice.org with the widely-lionized
FrameMaker is especially enlightening:
&amp;#8220;I began comparing FrameMaker and Writer when a regular on the OpenOffice.org
User&amp;#8217;s list asked what it would take to give Writer the power of FrameMaker.
When I started, I mentally pictured a scale with Microsoft Word on one end and
FrameMaker on another, with Writer in the middle, but closer to Microsoft
Word.  As I proceeded, I found Writer was a much stronger contender than I had
expected. At the end of the comparison, I had to conclude that the two
products compare quite closely, depending on what features are more important
to a given user&amp;#8230;
[OpenOffice.org users]
can be in little doubt that they are using software that
competes with FrameMaker on its own terms, and wins as often it loses. Even
ignoring the cost and philosophical differences, OpenOffice.org is clearly an
acceptable alternative to FrameMaker.&amp;#8221;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In short, if you&amp;#8217;re creating a thesis at GMU, use OpenDocument.
I&amp;#8217;ve used Word, Word Perfect, OpenOffice.org, and FrameMaker to write
large documents.
FrameMaker is nice but hideously overpriced, and because it&amp;#8217;s overpriced,
non-standard, and poorly supported,
it&amp;#8217;s mostly disappearing from the marketplace.
Word works well for 1-2 page documents, but its weaknesses become apparant
as your documents get larger, and it&amp;#8217;s based on proprietary formats that
lock you into a single product.
It&amp;#8217;s painful to use for larger documents;
GMU has yet to create a Word template that is even slightly non-painful.
In contrast, in short order I created an OpenDocument format that
did everything they wanted, with lots of automation.
OpenDocument is an ISO standard, with nice products
to support it, and specifically designed for large documents.
If you need to make large documents, use the right tool for the job.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
   </item>
  <item>
    <title>April 2007 release of &amp;#8220;Why OSS/FS? Look at the Numbers!&amp;#8221;</title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2007/04/12#oss-why-20070412</link>
    <pubDate>Thu, 12 Apr 2007 19:27 GMT</pubDate>
    <!-- date: 2007-04-12 -->
    <description>
&lt;p&gt;
Finally, I&amp;#8217;ve released a new version of
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/oss_fs_why.html&quot;&gt;&amp;#8220;Why Open Source Software /
Free Software (OSS/FS, FLOSS, FOSS)? Look at the Numbers!&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt;
This paper continues to provide
&amp;#8220;quantitative data that, in many cases, using open source
software / free software (abbreviated as OSS/FS, FLOSS, or FOSS) is a
reasonable or even superior approach to using their proprietary competition
according to various measures. This paper’s goal is to show that you should
consider using OSS/FS when acquiring software.&amp;#8221;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#8217;s been a while; my last release was November 14, 2005.
The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/archive/ChangeLog&quot;&gt;ChangeLog&lt;/a&gt;
has all the details, but here are some of the highlights:
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
Updated webserver stats, and noted issues with the Go Daddy change
and lighttpd.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.esecurityplanet.com/views/article.php/3665801&quot;&gt;
Noted Kenneth van Wyk&amp;#8217;s article about Linux security&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
Added quotes from Microsoft&amp;#8217;s Bill Hilf, from
&amp;#8220;Cracking Open the Door to Open Source&amp;#8221; by Carolyn A. April,
&amp;#8220;Redmond&amp;#8221; magazine, March 2007, pp. 26-36.
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cs.vu.nl/~ast/brown/&quot;&gt;
Added link to Andy Tanenbaum&amp;#8217;s article about Ken Brown and ADTI&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
Added a link to an
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cyber-rights.org/interception/echelon/European_parliament_resolution.htm&quot;&gt;approved European Parliament resolution,
A5-0264/2001&lt;/a&gt;, which calls &amp;#8220;on the Commission and Member States to promote software projects
whose source text is made public (open-source software), as this is the only
way of guaranteeing that no backdoors are built into programmes [and calls] on
the Commission to lay down a standard for the level of security of e-mail
software packages, placing those packages whose source code has not been made
public in the &amp;#8216;least reliable&amp;#8217; category&amp;#8221; (5 September, 2001; 367 votes
for, 159 against and 39 abstentions).
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
Added a reference to the Forrester report &amp;#8220;Open Source Becoming
	   Mission-Critical In North America And Europe&amp;#8221; by Michael Goulde 
	   that says &amp;#8220;Firms Should Consider Open Source Options
	   For Mission-Critical Applications&amp;#8221;.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
Added references to a
&lt;a href=&quot;http://ec.europa.eu/enterprise/ict/policy/doc/2006-11-20-flossimpact.pdf&quot;&gt;major new European Commission-sponsored study,
&amp;#8220;Study on the Economic impact of open source software
on innovation and the competitiveness of the
Information and Communication Technologies (ICT) sector in the EU&amp;#8221;,
November 20, 2006&lt;/a&gt;.  This is a major new study;
&amp;#8220;Our findings show that, in almost all the cases,
a transition toward open source reports of savings
on the long term&amp;#8221;.  There is LOTS of quantitative information here.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
Added reference to Communications of the ACM (CACM) Jan. 2007,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://portal.acm.org/citation.cfm?id=1188921&quot;&gt;
&amp;#8220;Increased Security through Open Source&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt;
It doesn&amp;#8217;t say anything new, and it omits the many quantitative studies
cited here, but it&amp;#8217;s a prestigious journal that says it.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.oreillynet.com/pub/a/sysadmin/2007/01/05/fingerprinting-mail-servers.html&quot;&gt;Added reference to mail server market survey:
	  Sendmail and Postfix and #1 and #2 in the market&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
Added references to
&lt;a href=&quot;http://defectivebydesign.org&quot;&gt;defectivebydesign.org&lt;/a&gt;
and to Raymond/Landley&amp;#8217;s &amp;#8220;World Domination 201&amp;#8221; into desktop section.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.washingtonpost.com/securityfix/2007/01/internet_explorer_unsafe_for_2.html&quot;&gt;IE vs. Firefox unsafe days in 2006.&lt;/a&gt; Eek&amp;#8230; it&amp;#8217;s scary.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
Added
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.computerworld.com/action/article.do?command=viewArticleBasic&amp;articleId=9006990&amp;amp;intsrc=news_ts_head&quot;&gt;Survey - Linux use on mission-critical systems&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
Added
&lt;a href=&quot;http://lxer.com/module/newswire/view/77291/index.html&quot;&gt;Danish cities demand more openness&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
Added
&lt;a href=&quot;http://blogs.zdnet.com/open-source/?p=837&quot;&gt;
	  &amp;#8220;The war is over and Linux won&amp;#8221; (Server war)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
Added
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.linux.com/article.pl?sid=06/12/04/1538214&quot;&gt;
Evergreen, an open source, enterprise-class library management
developed by the Georgia Public Library Service&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
Added reference to TCO savings on OSS/FS databases, from
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.itnews.com.au/newsstory.aspx?CIaNID=42505&amp;amp;src=site-marq&quot;&gt;&amp;#8220;Open source databases &amp;#8216;60 percent cheaper&amp;#8217;&amp;#8221; article&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
Added info Firefox use which keeps growing. See
&lt;a href=&quot;http://marketshare.hitslink.com/report.aspx?qprid=3&quot;&gt;
http://marketshare.hitslink.com/report.aspx?qprid=3&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.techweb.com/wire/security/193104314&quot;&gt;
http://www.techweb.com/wire/security/193104314&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
Added
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.linux-watch.com/news/NS8445673704.html&quot;&gt;
reference to IDC survey&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/oss_fs_why.html#trusting-trust&quot;&gt;
Referenced &amp;#8220;Trusting Trust&amp;#8221; attack&lt;/a&gt;.
Here&amp;#8217;s the text:
	&amp;#8220;An Air Force evaluation by Karger and Schell first publicly described
	this very nasty computer attack, which Ken Thompson ably demonstrated
	and described in his classic 1984 paper &amp;#8220;Reflections on Trusting
	Trust&amp;#8221;. Thompson showed that because we use software to create other
	software, if an attacker subverts the software-creating programs, no
	amount of auditing any program can help you - the subverted programs
	can hide whatever they want to! This has been called the
	&amp;#8220;uncounterable attack&amp;#8221;, and some have said that it&amp;#8217;s impossible to
	secure computers simply because this attack is possible. Some have
	even said that all those security audits of OSS/FS are worthless,
	because subverted tools could insert attacks the auditors couldn&amp;#8217;t
	see. But it turns out that the trusting trust attack can be countered.
	My 2005 paper Countering Trusting Trust through Diverse
	Double-Compiling (DDC), published by ACSAC, shows how the
	&amp;#8220;uncounterable&amp;#8221; trusting trust attack can be countered. But there&amp;#8217;s a
	catch: the DDC defense only works if you can get the source code for
	your software creation tools, including the operating system,
	compiler, and so on. That kind of information is typically only
	available for OSS/FS programs! Thus, even in the case of the dangerous
	&amp;#8220;trusting trust&amp;#8221; attack, OSS/FS has a security advantage.&amp;#8221;

&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
Added a note about Symphony OS (innovative user interface).
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
Added quote from Bellovin to history section.  OSS was the
norm in many communities before the mid-1970s.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
Added
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.onestat.com/html/aboutus_pressbox44-mozilla-firefox-has-slightly-increased.html&quot;&gt;
stats from onestat.com re: Firefox usage&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
Added
&lt;a href=&quot;http://levanta.com/linuxstudy/index.shtml&quot;&gt;EMA study&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
Added &lt;a href=&quot;http://news.yahoo.com/s/cmp/20060210/tc_cmp/179102616&quot;&gt;
Spyware stats, IE vs. Firefox, from University of Washington&lt;/a&gt;.

&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
Added new reports on security flaw fixing time:
&lt;a href=&quot;http://blogs.washingtonpost.com/securityfix/2006/02/a_time_to_patch.html&quot;&gt;
http://blogs.washingtonpost.com/securityfix/2006/02/a_time_to_patch.html&lt;/a&gt;
and
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.heinz.cmu.edu/%7Ertelang/disclosure_jan_06.pdf&quot;&gt;
http://www.heinz.cmu.edu/%7Ertelang/disclosure_jan_06.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.

&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
Added
&lt;a href=&quot;http://flosspols.org/deliverables.php&quot;&gt;
	  &amp;#8220;Deliverable D3: Results and policy paper from survey of
	  government authorities&amp;#8221;.&lt;/a&gt;
There&amp;#8217;s lots of other good stuff there.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
Added reference to
&lt;a href=&quot;http://firstmonday.org/issues/issue10_10/nuvolari/&quot;&gt;
	  another paper on innovation&lt;/a&gt;.

&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
Added reference to
&lt;a href=&quot;http://insight.zdnet.co.uk/software/0,39020463,39238437,00.htm&quot;&gt;
&amp;#8220;Why open source projects are not publicised&amp;#8221; by Ingrid Marson,
ZDNet UK, November 25, 2005&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As I mentioned earlier,
I wish I&amp;#8217;d used the term &amp;#8220;FLOSS&amp;#8221;
(Free-Libre / Open Source Software) as my all-encompassing term in this paper.
FLOSS is much easier to say than some of the alternatives, and
the term &amp;#8220;Free Software&amp;#8221; is widely misunderstood as being &amp;#8220;no cost&amp;#8221;.
However, I&amp;#8217;ve used the term OSS/FS all over in the paper,
and it&amp;#8217;s awkward to change now
(and people might not find the document they were looking for), so
I haven&amp;#8217;t changed it here.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Enjoy!
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
   </item>
  </channel>
</rss>