<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- name="generator" content="blosxom/2.0" -->

<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>David A. Wheeler's Blog   </title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog</link>
    <description>David A. Wheeler's weblog.</description>
    <language>en</language>

  <item>
    <title>I hope we learn from the computer security problems of 2014</title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2014/12/31#learn-2014</link>
    <pubDate>Wed, 31 Dec 2014 15:06 GMT</pubDate>
    <!-- date: 2014-12-31 -->
    <description>
&lt;p&gt;
As 2014 draws to a close, I hope anyone involved with computers
will resolve to &lt;i&gt;learn&lt;/i&gt; from the legion of security
problems of 2014.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We had way too many serious vulnerabilities in widely-used software
revealed in 2014.
In each case, there are lessons that people &lt;i&gt;could&lt;/i&gt; learn from them.
Please take a look at the lessons that can be learned from
&lt;a href=&quot;/essays/heartbleed.html&quot;&gt;Heartbleed&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;/essays/shellshock.html&quot;&gt;Shellshock&lt;/a&gt;,
the
&lt;a href=&quot;/essays/poodle-sslv3.html&quot;&gt;POODLE attack on SSLv3&lt;/a&gt;, and the
&lt;a href=&quot;/essays/apple-goto-fail.html&quot;&gt;Apple goto fail vulnerability&lt;/a&gt;.
More generally,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/secure-programs/&quot;&gt;a lot of information
is available on how develop secure software&lt;/a&gt; -
even though most software developers still do not know how to develop
secure software.
Simiarly, there are a host of lessons that organizations could learn from
&lt;a href=&quot;/essays/sony-lax.html&quot;&gt;Sony Pictures&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;Will&lt;/i&gt; people actually learn anything?
Georg Wilhelm Friedrich Hegel reportedly said that,
&amp;#8220;We learn from history that we do not learn from history&amp;#8221;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Yet I think there are reasons to hope.
There are a lot of efforts to improve the security of
Free/Libre/Open Source Software (FLOSS) that are important yet
inadequately secure.
The
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.linuxfoundation.org/programs/core-infrastructure-initiative&quot;&gt;Linux Foundation (LF) Core Infrastructure Initiative (CII)&lt;/a&gt;
was established to &amp;#8220;fund open source projects that are in the critical
path for core computing functions&amp;#8221; to improve their security.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://fsfe.org/news/2014/news-20141219-01.en.html&quot;&gt;most recent European Union (EU) budget includes €1 million for auditing free-software programs&lt;/a&gt; to identify and fix vulnerabilities.
The &lt;a href=&quot;https://host-project.org/&quot;&gt;US DHS HOST project&lt;/a&gt; is also
working to improve security using open source software (OSS).
The
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/about/appsecurity/patch-rewards/&quot;&gt;Google Application Security Patch Reward Program&lt;/a&gt; is also working to improve security.
And to be fair, these problems were found by people who were examining
the software or protocols so that the problems could be fixed - exactly
what you &lt;i&gt;want&lt;/i&gt; to happen.
At an organizational level, I think Sony was unusually lax in its
security posture.
I am already seeing evidence that other organizations have suddenly
become much more serious about security, now that they see what has been
done to Sony Pictures.
In short, they are finally starting to see that
security problems are not theoretical; they are real.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Here&amp;#8217;s hoping that 2015 will be known as the year where people took
computer security more seriously, and as a result, software and our
computer systems became much harder to attack.
If that happens, that would make 2015 an awesome year.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
   </item>
  <item>
    <title>Sony Pictures, Lax Security, and Passwords</title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2014/12/20#sony-lax</link>
    <pubDate>Sat, 20 Dec 2014 19:10 GMT</pubDate>
    <!-- date: 2014-12-20 -->
    <description>
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;/essays/sony-lax.html&quot;&gt;Sony Pictures, Lax Security, and Passwords&lt;/a&gt;
is a new essay about the devastating attack on Sony Pictures.
We now have new information about how Sony Pictures was attacked;
from that, and public information about Sony Pictures,
we can see why the attack was so devastating.
Even more importantly, we can learn from it.
So please, take a look at
&lt;a href=&quot;/essays/sony-lax.html&quot;&gt;Sony Pictures, Lax Security, and Passwords&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
   </item>
  </channel>
</rss>