<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- name="generator" content="blosxom/2.0" -->

<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>David A. Wheeler's Blog   </title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog</link>
    <description>David A. Wheeler's weblog.</description>
    <language>en</language>

  <item>
    <title>Donald Macleay</title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2007/10/22#donald-macleay</link>
    <pubDate>Mon, 22 Oct 2007 23:06 GMT</pubDate>
    <!-- date: 2007-10-22 -->
    <description>
&lt;p&gt;
Don Macleay was my mentor and friend, and he just passed away
(Oct. 15, 2007).
So, this is a small blog entry in his honor.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/images/don-macleay.jpg&quot; width=&quot;163&quot; height=&quot;214&quot; alt=&quot;Donald (Don) Macleay&quot; align=&quot;left&quot;&gt;
&lt;/img&gt;
Here&amp;#8217;s what I said at his funeral:
&amp;#8220;In 1980, Don was the manager of a computer store.
I was only 15, but he took a chance on employing me, and I&amp;#8217;m grateful.
He taught me much, in particular, showing by example
that you could be in business (even as a salesman!) and be an honest person.
He later moved to other companies, and I moved twice with him,
because I found that good bosses were hard to find.
Don was honest, reliable, a good friend, and an inspiration to me.
I will miss him, and I look forward to seeing him again in heaven.&amp;#8221;
I should add that he spoke at my Eagle scout ceremony.
Later on,
when he moved out to the country, it was always a pleasure to visit him
and his family.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Here&amp;#8217;s a part of his biography, as printed in the funeral bulletin:
&amp;#8220;Born in Washington, D.C., on October 27, 1934, Donald Macleay was
raised in Falls Church.  He attained the rank of Eagle Scout and
graduated at the top of the first class of St. Stephen&amp;#8217;s School in 1952.
In 1956, he graduated with a Bachelor of Arts in English from
the Virginia Military Institute (VMI).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
After serving as a Marine Corps officer, Donald Macleay spent many years
in the business world before becoming a Parole Officer for the
Department of Juvenile Justice in Stafford County.
As well, in 1992, he was a candidate for the U.S. Congress as
an Independent.&amp;#8221;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The biography goes on to note that he &amp;#8220;valued being a Christian,
a husband, a father and grandfather, and a friend.&amp;#8221;
Much of his last years were spent helping troubled youth in his area
(Fredericksburg, VA), and from all accounts he was extraordinarily
successful at helping them and their families.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
   </item>
  </channel>
</rss>