<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- name="generator" content="blosxom/2.0" -->

<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>David A. Wheeler's Blog   </title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog</link>
    <description>David A. Wheeler's weblog.</description>
    <language>en</language>

  <item>
    <title>Innovations update</title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2011/04/10#innovations-update-2011</link>
    <pubDate>Sun, 10 Apr 2011 21:30 GMT</pubDate>
    <!-- date: 2011-04-10 -->
    <description>
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#8217;ve made various updates to my list of
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/innovation/innovation.html&quot;&gt;
The Most Important Software Innovations&lt;/a&gt;.
I&amp;#8217;ve added Distributed Version Control System (DVCS);
these are all over now in the form of git, Mercurial (hg),
Bazaar, Monotone, and so on, but
these were influenced by the earlier BitKeeper, which was
in turn influenced by the earlier Teamware (developed by Sun starting in 1991).
As is often the case, &amp;#8220;new&amp;#8221; innovations are actually much older
than people realize.
I also added &lt;i&gt;make&lt;/i&gt;, originally developed in 1977, and
quicksort, developed in 1960-1961 by C.A.R. (Tony) Hoare.
I&amp;#8217;ve also improved lots of material that was already there,
such as a better description of the history of
the remote procedure call (RPC).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So please enjoy
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/innovation/innovation.html&quot;&gt;
The Most Important Software Innovations&lt;/a&gt;!
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
   </item>
  <item>
    <title>Comparing Free/Libre/Open Source Software (FLOSS) with Charles River Bridge vs. Warren Bridge</title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2011/04/06#open-source-software-bridges</link>
    <pubDate>Wed, 06 Apr 2011 21:24 GMT</pubDate>
    <!-- date: 2011-04-06 -->
    <description>
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#8217;ve been reading over an old court case and thinking about how it
relates to the issue of government releasing free / libre /
open source software (FLOSS).
The case is
&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_River_Bridge_v._Warren_Bridge&quot;&gt;Charles River Bridge v. Warren Bridge, 36 U.S. 420&lt;/a&gt;, including the
final U.S. Supreme Court decision
(&lt;a href=&quot;http://books.google.com/books?id=ZHoYAAAAIAAJ&amp;pg=PA832&amp;lpg=PA832&amp;dq=court+case+government+built+toll+bridge+compete&amp;source=bl&amp;ots=yLgk4mANea&amp;sig=ifdpF4aQyJu1V0XAs5GpyJ4Ccxk&amp;hl=en&amp;ei=LL-cTfHhO8ucgQe3qZz_Bg&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=book_result&amp;ct=result&amp;resnum=2&amp;sqi=2&amp;ved=0CB4Q6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false&quot;&gt;United States Supreme Court reports, Vol. 9 (PDF page 773 on)&lt;/a&gt;).
This is &lt;i&gt;old&lt;/i&gt;; the decision was rendered in 1837.
But I think it has interesting ramifications for today.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Any lawyer will correctly tell you that you must not look at one
court decision to answer a specific question.
And any lawyer will tell you that the details matter; a case with
different facts may have a different ruling.
Fine.  I&amp;#8217;m not a lawyer anyway, and I am not trying to
create a formal legal opinion (this is a blog, not a legal opinion!).
But still, it&amp;#8217;s useful to look at these pivotal cases 
and try to think about their wider implications.
I think we should &lt;i&gt;all&lt;/i&gt; think about what&amp;#8217;s good (or not good)
for our communities, and how we should help our governments enable that;
that is &lt;i&gt;not&lt;/i&gt; a domain exclusive to lawyers.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, what was this case all about?
Wikipedia has a nice summary.
Basically, in 1785 the Charles River Bridge Company was granted a
charter to construct a bridge over the Charles River between Boston and
Charleston.
The bridge owners got quite wealthy from the bridge tolls, but the
public was not so happy with having to keep paying and paying
for such a key service.
So Massachusetts allowed another company to build another bridge,
the Warren bridge, next to the original Charles River bridge.
What&amp;#8217;s more, this second agreement stipulated that
the Warren bridge would, after a certain time,
be turned over to the state and be free for the public to use.
The Charles River bridge owners were enraged &amp;mdash; they
knew that a free-to-use bridge would eliminate their profits.
So they sued.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As noted in Wikipedia,
the majority decision (read by Taney) was that
any charter contract should be interpreted as narrowly as possible.
Since the Charles River Bridge contract did not explicitly guarantee
exclusive rights, the Supreme Court held that they didn&amp;#8217;t get exclusive rights.
The Supreme Court
also determined that, in general, public grants should be interpreted
closely and if there is ever any uncertainty in a contract, the decision
made should be one to better the public.
Taney said, &amp;#8220;While the rights
of private property are sacredly guarded, we must not forget that the
community also have rights, and that the happiness and well-being of
every citizen depends on their faithful preservation.&amp;#8221;
In his remarks,
Taney also explored what the negative effects on the country would be if
the Court had sided with the Charles River Bridge Company.
He stated that
had that been the decision of the Court, transportation would be affected
around the whole country.
Taney made the point that with the rise of
technology, canals and railroads had started to take away business from
highways, and if charters granted monopolies to corporations, then these
sorts of transportation improvements would not be able to flourish.
If this were the case then, Taney said, the country would &amp;#8220;be thrown back
to the improvements of the last century, and obliged to stand still.&amp;#8221;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So how does this relate to FLOSS and government?
Well first, let me set the stage, by pulling in a different strand of thought.
The U.S. government pays to develop a lot of software.
I think that in general, when &amp;#8220;we the people&amp;#8221; pay for software,
then &amp;#8220;we the people&amp;#8221; should get it.
The idea of paying for some software to be developed, and then giving
long monopoly rights to a single company, seems to fly in the face of this.
It doesn&amp;#8217;t make sense from a cost viewpoint; when there&amp;#8217;s a single
monopoly supplier, the costs go up because there&amp;#8217;s no effective competition!
Some software shouldn&amp;#8217;t be released to the public at all, but that is
what classification and export controls are supposed to deal with.
I&amp;#8217;m sure there are exceptions, but currently we assume that when
&amp;#8220;we the people&amp;#8221; pay to develop software, then &amp;#8220;we the people&amp;#8221; do
&lt;i&gt;not&lt;/i&gt; get the software, and that is absurd.
If someone wants to have exclusive rights to some software, then he should
spend all his time and money to develop it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A fair retort to my argument is,
&amp;#8220;But does the government have the right to take an action that might
put reduce the profits of a business, or put it out of business?&amp;#8221;
In particular,
if the government paid to develop software, can the government
release that software as FLOSS
if a private company sells equivalent proprietary software?
After all, that private company would suddenly find itself
competing with a less-expensive or free product!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Examining all relevant legal cases about this topic
(releasing FLOSS when there is an existing proprietary product)
would be daunting; I don&amp;#8217;t pretend to have done that analysis.
(If someone &lt;i&gt;has&lt;/i&gt; done it, please tell me!)
However, I think
&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_River_Bridge_v._Warren_Bridge&quot;&gt;Charles River Bridge v. Warren Bridge&lt;/a&gt;
can at least shed some light and is interesting to think about.
After all, this is a major Supreme Court decision,
so the ruling should be able to help us think about the issue
of the government
enabling a free service that competes with an existing business.
In this case, the government
knowingly created a competing free service,
and as a result an existing business would no longer be able to make money
from something it did have rights to.
There were a lot of people who had bought stock in the first company,
for a lot of money, and those stock holders
expected to reap massive returns from their
monopoly on an important local service.
There were also a lot of ordinary citizens who were unhappy about this
local monopoly, and wanted to get rid of the monopoly.
There is another interesting similarity between the bridge case
and the release of FLOSS: the government did
&lt;i&gt;not&lt;/i&gt; try to take away the existing bridge, instead, they enabled the
re-development of a competing bridge.
While it&amp;#8217;s not the last word, this case about bridges
can (I think) help us think about whether governments can release FLOSS
if there&amp;#8217;s already a proprietary program that does the same thing.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I would certainly agree that governments shouldn&amp;#8217;t perform an
action with the sole or primary purpose of putting a company out of business.
But when governments release FLOSS they usually are &lt;i&gt;not&lt;/i&gt; trying
to put a proprietary company out of business as their primary purpose.
In the case of Charles River Bridge vs. Warren Bridge,
the government took action not because it wanted to put a company out of
business, but because it wanted to help the public
(in this case, by reducing use costs for key infrastructure).
At least in this case, the Supreme Court
clearly decided that a government can do something even
if it hurts the profitability of some business.
If they had ruled otherwise, government would be completely hamstrung;
almost all government actions help someone and harm someone else.
The point &lt;i&gt;should&lt;/i&gt; be that the government should be trying to aid the
community as a whole.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I think a reasonable take-away message from this case is that government
should focus on the rights, happiness, and well-being of the community
as a whole, even if some specific group would make less money &amp;mdash;
and that helping the community may involve making some goods or
services (like FLOSS!) available at no cost.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
   </item>
  <item>
    <title>FLOSS Weekly: FLOSS in the DoD</title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2011/04/06#floss-weekly-dod</link>
    <pubDate>Wed, 06 Apr 2011 20:48 GMT</pubDate>
    <!-- date: 2011-04-06 -->
    <description>
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://twit.tv/floss160&quot;&gt;FLOSS Weekly #160&lt;/a&gt;
is out, and it features me!
It&amp;#8217;s an interview of me by Randal Schwartz and Simon Phipps
about free/libre/open source software (FLOSS) and the
U.S. Department of Defense (DoD).
The DoD uses and releases FLOSS, and it has a recent
policy about FLOSS that I think is pretty good.
If you&amp;#8217;re interested in this topic, take a look!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you&amp;#8217;re interested in this topic, you might also be interested in:
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://cio-nii.defense.gov/sites/oss/&quot;&gt;DoD information on open source software&lt;/a&gt;.  In particular, look at the
DoD OSS policy (&amp;#8220;Clarifying Guidance Regarding Open Source Software (OSS)&amp;#8221;, Memorandum by David M. Wennergren, 16 October 2009), the
DoD OSS FAQ, and
the paper &amp;#8220;Use of Free and Open-Source Software (FOSS) in the U.S. DoD&amp;#8221; (MITRE 2003).
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://softwaretechnews.thedacs.com/stn_view.php?stn_id=56&quot;&gt;
DACS Software Tech News issue on &amp;#8220;DoD and Open Source Software&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt;.
See especially my essay,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://softwaretechnews.thedacs.com/stn_view.php?stn_id=56&amp;article_id=180&quot;&gt;
&amp;#8220;Publicly Releasing Open Source Software Developed for the U.S. Government&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/&quot;&gt;David A. Wheeler&amp;#8217;s personal website&lt;/a&gt;
(yes, that&amp;#8217;s my website).
You might be especially interested in
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/oss_fs_why.html&quot;&gt;
&amp;#8220;Why Open Source Software / Free Software (OSS/FS)? Look at the Numbers!&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt;
(a huge collection of FLOSS statistics),
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/essays/commercial-floss.html&quot;&gt; &amp;#8220;FLOSS is commercial software&amp;#8221; &lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/essays/gpl-compatible.html&quot;&gt; &amp;#8220;Make Your Open Source Software GPL-Compatible. Or Else&amp;#8221; &lt;/a&gt;
(Why you should pick a GPL-compatible license),
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/sloc/&quot;&gt;
&amp;#8220;More than a Gigabuck: Estimating GNU/Linux&amp;#8217;s size&amp;#8221; &lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/oss_fs_eval.html&quot;&gt;
&amp;#8220;How to Evaluate OSS/FS Programs&amp;#8221;
&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/secure-programs/&quot;&gt;
&amp;#8220;Secure Programming for Linux and Unix HOWTO&amp;#8221;
&lt;/a&gt;
(information on creating secure software),
and
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/trusting-trust&quot;&gt;
&amp;#8220;Fully Countering Trusting Trust through Diverse Double-Compiling (DDC)&amp;#8221;
&lt;/a&gt;
(on countering the &amp;#8220;Trusting Trust&amp;#8221; attack).
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So take a look at
&lt;a href=&quot;http://twit.tv/floss160&quot;&gt;FLOSS Weekly #160&lt;/a&gt;, and enjoy.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
   </item>
  </channel>
</rss>