<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- name="generator" content="blosxom/2.0" -->

<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>David A. Wheeler's Blog   </title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog</link>
    <description>David A. Wheeler's weblog.</description>
    <language>en</language>

  <item>
    <title>Challenges for securing closed source software</title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2008/08/21#closed-source-security</link>
    <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2008 15:48 GMT</pubDate>
    <!-- date: 2008-08-21 -->
    <description>
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#8217;ve just learned of a really interesting article by
&lt;a href=&quot;http://blogs.techrepublic.com.com/security/?p=549&quot;&gt;
Chad Perrin, &amp;#8220;10 security challenges facing closed source software&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt;.
He starts with my
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/secure-programs/Secure-Programs-HOWTO/&quot;&gt;
Secure Programming for Linux and Unix HOWTO&lt;/a&gt; book&amp;#8217;s list of
&amp;#8220;core requirements for developing secure software&amp;#8221;, which was
part of the section on developing secure open source software.
My list was really simple:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;First, people have to actually review the code.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Second, at least some of the people developing and reviewing the code must know how to write secure programs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Third, once found, problems need to be fixed quickly and their fixes distributed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
Lots of people have cited that list (and the book!), including
&lt;a href=&quot;http://googleonlinesecurity.blogspot.com/2008/05/contributing-to-open-source-software.html&quot;&gt;
Google&amp;#8217;s &amp;#8220;Contributing To Open Source Software Security&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At the time I made that list, I was primarily
thinking about that list as requirements for
open source software.
Chad Perrin had the interesting insight that the list applies to
closed source software too&amp;#8230; and then examined what the challenges are.
It&amp;#8217;s a really interesting list, I suggest taking a look at it!
He closes with a very interesting claim:
&amp;#8220;None of these disadvantages for closed source software are inflexible
or absolute. There’s no reason closed source software developed by a
corporate vendor can’t be as secure as an open source equivalent. It
should be pretty obvious that, all else being equal, the trend is for
circumstances to favor the security of open source software — at least
as far as these principles of software security are concerned.&amp;#8221;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
   </item>
  <item>
    <title>FLOSS License Proliferation: Still a problem</title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2008/08/20#license-proliferation</link>
    <pubDate>Wed, 20 Aug 2008 16:19 GMT</pubDate>
    <!-- date: 2008-08-20 -->
    <description>
&lt;p&gt;
License proliferation in
free-libre / open source software (FLOSS) licenses is less than it
used to be, but it&amp;#8217;s still a serious problem.
There are, thankfully, some interesting rumblings to try to make things better.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.crynwr.com/cgi-bin/ezmlm-cgi?3:mss:15914:200808:nbobhajnkkgafccgdpco&quot;&gt;Russ Nelson at the Open Source Initiative (OSI)&lt;/a&gt;
wants to restart a FLOSS license anti-proliferation committee
to address the problem that there are too many FLOSS licenses.
He wants to set up a process to establish
two tiers, &amp;#8220;recommended&amp;#8221; and &amp;#8220;compliant&amp;#8221;.
There&amp;#8217;s no telling if the work will be successful, but the basic
concept sounds very reasonable to me.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://news.cnet.com/8301-13505_3-10007321-16.html?hhTest=1&quot;&gt;
Matt Asay counters&lt;/a&gt; that
&amp;#8220;Someone needs to tell the Open Source Initiative,
Google, and others who fret about license proliferation
that the market has already cut down the number of actively
used licenses to just a small handful:
L/GPL, BSD/Apache, MPL, and a few others (EPL, CPL)&amp;#8230;
It&amp;#8217;s a worthy cause, but one that has already been effectively fought
and settled by the free market. I would hazard a guess that upwards of
95 percent of all open-source projects are licensed under less than 5
percent of open-source licenses. (The last time I checked, 88 percent
of Sourceforge projects were L/GPL or BSD. It&amp;#8217;s been a non-issue for
many years.)
There is no open-source proliferation problem. Do we have a lot of
open-source licenses? Yes, just as we have a lot of proprietary licenses
(in fact, we have many more of those). But we don&amp;#8217;t have a license
proliferation problem, because very few open-source licenses actually
get used on a regular basis.
This is a phantom. It seems scary, but it&amp;#8217;s not real.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Asay is right that &amp;#8220;the market&amp;#8221; has mostly settled the issue, but I think
Asay is quite wrong that there is no problem.
I quite agree with Asay that
there is a very short list of standard FLOSS licenses&amp;#8230; but there&amp;#8217;s
still a lot of people who, even in 2008, keep creating new incompatible
FLOSS (or intended to be FLOSS) licenses for their newly-released programs.
And although it&amp;#8217;s true that &amp;#8220;very few actually get used on a regular basis&amp;#8221;,
it&amp;#8217;s also true that a large number of people are still creating new,
one-off FLOSS licenses that are incompatible with many widely-used licenses.
Why?
I think the problem is that there are still a &lt;i&gt;lot&lt;/i&gt; of lawyers and
developers who &amp;#8220;didn&amp;#8217;t get the memo&amp;#8221; from users and potential co-developers
that new FLOSS licenses are decidedly unwelcome.
As a result,
new programs are still being released under new non-standard licenses.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I can even speculate why there are so many people still creating
incompatible licenses, even though users and distributors don&amp;#8217;t want them.
A lot of new programs are developed by people who know a lot
about their technical specialty, but very little about copyright law,
and also very little about FLOSS norms (both in licensing and
community development processes).
So they go to lawyers of their organizations. As far as I can tell, many
lawyers think it&amp;#8217;s fun to create new licenses and have absolutely no clue that
using a nonstandard FLOSS-like license will relegate the program to oblivion.
(The primary thing that matters to a lawyer is if they or
their organization can be sued; if the license causes the program to be
useless, well, too bad, the lawyer still gets paid.)
Indeed, many lawyers still don&amp;#8217;t even know what the requirements for FLOSS
licenses are - never mind that there are license vetting procedures, or that
using non-standard FLOSS licenses is widely considered harmful.
So we have developers, who know they want to collaborate but don&amp;#8217;t realize
that they need to follow community standards to make that work,
and we have lawyers, who often don&amp;#8217;t realize that there &lt;i&gt;are&lt;/i&gt; community
standards for the licenses (and their non-selection will affect their clients).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Let me give some specific examples from recent work I&amp;#8217;m doing, to
show that this is still a problem.
Right now I&amp;#8217;m trying to get some software packaged to more rigorously prove
that software does (or doesn&amp;#8217;t) do something important.
I tried to get CVC3 packaged; it has &amp;#8220;almost a BSD license&amp;#8221;, and I believe
the developer intended for it to be FLOSS.
Problem is, somebody thought it&amp;#8217;d be fun to add some new nonstandard clauses.
The worst clause - and I&amp;#8217;m highly paraphrasing here - could be interpreted as,
&amp;#8220;If we developers did lots of illegal activities in creating the software,
you&amp;#8217;re required to pay for our legal expenses to defend our illegal activities,
even if the only thing that you did is provide copies of this software
to other people, or used it incidentally.&amp;#8221;
Certainly that&amp;#8217;s how I interpret it, though I&amp;#8217;m no lawyer.
When I brought this license text to Fedora legal, let&amp;#8217;s just say that
they were less than enthused about endorsing this license or including
the program in the distribution.
Indeed, CVC3&amp;#8217;s license may make it too dangerous for anyone to use.
After all, how could I possibly determine the risk that you (the developer)
did something illegal?
CVC3 also has another annoying incompatible license addition (compared to
the BSD-new license), a &amp;#8220;must change name if you change the code&amp;#8221; type clause.
Of course, it won&amp;#8217;t compile as-is;
the only way to compile it is to change the code :-).
Here&amp;#8217;s hoping that they fix this by switching to a standard license.
CVC3 is not the only offender, either, there are legions of them.
I examined Alt-Ergo, a somewhat similar program.
It uses a FLOSS license, but it uses the
remarkably weird and non-standard CeCILL-C license (this is even
less well known than its cousin the CeCILL; according to Fedora it&amp;#8217;s
FLOSS but GPL-incompatible, and a GPL-incompatible FLOSS license is a
remarkably bad choice).
Third example - over this weekend
I had a private email conversation with a developer who&amp;#8217;s about to
release their software with a license; the developer intended to
create (as a &lt;i&gt;non-lawyer!&lt;/i&gt;) yet another license with incompatible
non-FLOSS terms.
Which would have been a big mistake.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Frankly, I think Asay is being excessively generous in his list of
acceptable licenses.
The standard FLOSS licenses are, I believe,
simply MIT, revised BSD (BSD-new),
LGPL (versions 2.1 and 3), and GPL (versions 2 and 3),
and possibly the Apache 2.0 license.
All of these licenses have a very large set of projects that use them,
are widely understood, have been deeply analyzed by legal experts, and yet
are comprehensible to both developers and users.
An especially important property of this set, as you can see from
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/essays/floss-license-slide.html&quot;&gt;
my FLOSS license slide&lt;/a&gt;, is that they are generally compatible
(with the problem that Apache 2.0 and GPLv2 aren&amp;#8217;t compatible).
Compatibility is critical; if you want to use FLOSS to build serious
applications, you often need to combine them in novel ways, and license
incompatibilities often prevent that.
As I note in
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/essays/gpl-compatible.html&quot;&gt;
Make Your Open Source Software GPL-Compatible. Or Else&lt;/a&gt;,
the GPL is by far the most popular FLOSS license; &lt;i&gt;most&lt;/i&gt; FLOSS
software is under the GPL.
So choosing a GPL-incompatible license is, in most cases, foolish.
Which is a key reason I don&amp;#8217;t include the MPL in that set;
not only do these licenses have vanishingly small market share
compared to the set above, but their incompatibilities make their use foolish.
Even Mozilla, the original creator of the MPL, essentially no longer uses the
MPL (they tri-license with the GPL/LGPL/MPL, because GPL-incompatibility
was a bad idea).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Having a short &amp;#8220;OSI recommended&amp;#8221; or &amp;#8220;FSF recommended&amp;#8221; list of licenses
is unlikely to completely solve the problem of license proliferation.
But having a semi-formal, more obviously endorsed, and easy-to-reference
site that identified the short list of recommended licenses, and
explained why license proliferation is bad, would help.
While those well-versed in FLOSS understand things, the problem is those
others who are just starting out to develop a FLOSS project.
After all, the license is chosen at the very beginning of a project,
when the lead developer may have the &lt;i&gt;least&lt;/i&gt; experience with FLOSS.
Anyone beginning a new project is likely to make mistakes, but there&amp;#8217;s
a difference; just about any other mistake in starting
a FLOSS project can be fixed fairly easily.
Don&amp;#8217;t like the CM system? Switch!
Don&amp;#8217;t like your hosting environment? Move!
But a bad license is often extremely difficult to change; it may require
agreement by a vast army of people, or those (e.g., organizational lawyers)
who have no incentive to cooperate later.
Yes, projects like vim and Python have done it,
but only with tremendous effort.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The license mistakes of one project can even hurt other projects.
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.squeak.org/&quot;&gt;Squeak&lt;/a&gt; is
still trying to transition from early licensing mistakes, and it&amp;#8217;s still
not done even though it&amp;#8217;s been working on it for years.
These has impeded the packaging and wider use of nice programs like
&lt;a href=&quot;http://scratch.mit.edu/&quot;&gt;Scratch&lt;/a&gt;, which depend on Squeak.
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gnu.org/philosophy/java-trap.html&quot;&gt;The Java Trap&lt;/a&gt;
discusses some of the challenges when FLOSS &lt;i&gt;requires&lt;/i&gt; proprietary
software to run; when the FLOSS licenses are incompatible, many of the
same problems apply.
In short, when FLOSS licenses are incompatible,
they cause problems for everyone.
And when there are more than a few FLOSS licenses,
it also becomes very hard to understand, keep track of, and comply with them.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Asay and Nelson have no trouble understanding the license proliferation
issues; they&amp;#8217;ve been analyzing FLOSS for years.
But they are not the ones who need this information, anyway.
It&amp;#8217;s the newcomers - the innovators coming up with the new software ideas,
but who don&amp;#8217;t fully understand collaborative development and how
FLOSS licensing enables it - who need this information.
I don&amp;#8217;t really mean to pick on Asay in this article; it&amp;#8217;s just in this case,
I think Asay knows too much, and has forgotten how many people &lt;i&gt;don&amp;#8217;t&lt;/i&gt;
yet understand FLOSS.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Documenting a short list of the &amp;#8220;recommended licenses&amp;#8221; would be a great boon,
because it would help those innovative newcomers to FLOSS approaches
avoid one of the costliest mistakes of all: Using a nonstandard license.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
   </item>
  <item>
    <title>Free-Libre/Open Source Software (FLOSS) licenses legally enforceable - and more</title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2008/08/14#licenses-enforceable</link>
    <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2008 17:33 GMT</pubDate>
    <!-- date: 2008-08-14 -->
    <description>
&lt;p&gt;
The
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cafc.uscourts.gov/opinions/08-1001.pdf&quot;&gt;
U.S. Court of Appeals for the Federal Circuit
has ruled in Jacobsen v. Katzer&lt;/a&gt; (August 13, 2008)
that Free-Libre/Open Source Software (FLOSS)
licenses are legally enforceable.
Specifically, it determined that in the U.S.
disobeying a FLOSS license is copyright infringement
(unless there are other arrangements),
and not just a contract violation.
This makes it &lt;i&gt;much&lt;/i&gt; easier to enforce FLOSS licenses in the
United States.
It has some other very interesting things to say, too,
as I show below.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Frankly, I thought this was a very obvious ruling;
I find it bizarre that some people thought
there was another possibility (and that this had to be appealed).
After all, U.S. copyright law clearly
says that the copyright holder can determine the conditions for
(most) copying, and doing anything else (unless specially permitted
by law) is copyright infringement.  This ruling simply states
that the law is what it says it is, and that FLOSS licenses are a
perfectly valid set of conditions.  This eliminates, in one stroke,
the argument &amp;#8220;is a license a contract or a license?&amp;#8221; silliness.
A license is, well, a license!
I&amp;#8217;ve thought it was quite obvious that a license is not a contract;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gnu.org/philosophy/enforcing-gpl.html&quot;&gt;Eben Moglen&lt;/a&gt;
and
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.groklaw.net/article.php?story=20031214210634851&quot;&gt;Groklaw&lt;/a&gt;
have both written articles on this that I find extremely persuasive.
In some countries, this distinction
may make no difference, but in the U.S. there is a big difference.
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pcworld.com/businesscenter/article/149796/open_source_advocates_hail_appeals_court_ruling.html&quot;&gt;As Andy Updegrove noted&lt;/a&gt;,
&amp;#8220;Under contract law, the remedy is monetary
damages, which aren&amp;#8217;t likely to amount to anything involving open-source
software that is given away&amp;#8230;&amp;#8221;, but statutory damages (money awarded for
a violation of law) &amp;#8220;can be awarded for copyright infringement without
requiring proof of monetary damages&amp;#8230; people can recover attorney fees
for copyright infringement cases&amp;#8230; [and] most importantly for licenses
such as the [GNU General Public License], it means that your rights to
use the copyrighted work at all disappear&amp;#8221;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You can find more about the legal implications in
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.groklaw.net/article.php?story=2008081313212422&quot;&gt;
Groklaw&amp;#8217;s article on Jacobsen v. Katzer&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://sourceforge.net/mailarchive/forum.php?thread_name=p06240807c4c943180289%40[10.0.1.191]&amp;amp;forum_name=jmri-legal-announce&quot;&gt;the announcement on Jmri-legal-announce&lt;/a&gt;, and
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.linuxinsider.com/story/Open-Source-Wins-Landmark-Legal-Validation-64164.html&quot;&gt;LinuxInsider&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;a href=&quot;http://jmri.sourceforge.net/k/news.html#CAFCruling1&quot;&gt;JMRI has
a set of links to related articles&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The court also had many very interesting things to say about FLOSS.
I suspect many will quote it because it&amp;#8217;s an official U.S. court ruling
that cuts to the essense of FLOSS licensing and why it is the way it is.
Let me pull out a few interesting quotes;
I have bolded some particularly interesting points:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;#8220;We consider here the ability of a copyright holder to dedicate certain
work to free public use and yet enforce an &amp;#8216;open source&amp;#8217; copyright license
to control the future distribution and modification of that work&amp;#8230;
Public licenses, often referred to as &amp;#8216;open source&amp;#8217; licenses, are used
by artists, authors, educators, software developers, and scientists who
wish to create collaborative projects and to dedicate certain works
to the public. Several types of public licenses have been designed
to provide creators of copyrighted materials a means to protect and
control their copyrights. Creative Commons, one of the amici curiae,
provides free copyright licenses to allow parties to dedicate their
works to the public or to license certain uses of their works while
keeping some rights reserved.&amp;#8221;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;#8220;&lt;b&gt;Open source licensing has become a widely used method of creative
collaboration that serves to advance the arts and sciences in a manner
and at a pace that few could have imagined just a few decades ago&lt;/b&gt;. For
example, the Massachusetts Institute of Technology (&amp;#8216;MIT&amp;#8217;) uses a Creative
Commons public license for an OpenCourseWare project that licenses all
1800 MIT courses. Other public licenses support the GNU/Linux operating
system, the Perl programming language, the Apache web server programs,
the Firefox web browser, and a collaborative web-based encyclopedia
called Wikipedia.  Creative Commons notes that, by some estimates, there
are close to 100,000,000 works licensed under various Creative Commons
licenses. The Wikimedia Foundation, another of the amici curiae, estimates
that the Wikipedia website has more than 75,000 active contributors
working on some 9,000,000 articles in more than 250 languages.&amp;#8221;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;#8220;Open Source software projects invite computer programmers from around
the world to view software code and make changes and improvements to it.
&lt;b&gt;Through such collaboration, software programs can often be written
and debugged faster and at lower cost than if the copyright holder
were required to do all of the work independently.  In exchange and
in consideration for this collaborative work, the copyright holder
permits users to copy, modify and distribute the software code subject
to conditions that serve to protect downstream users and to keep the code
accessible&lt;/b&gt;.  By requiring that users copy and restate the license and
attribution information, a copyright holder can ensure that recipients of
the redistributed computer code know the identity of the owner as well
as the scope of the license granted by the original owner. The Artistic
License in this case also requires that changes to the computer code be
tracked so that downstream users know what part of the computer code is
the original code created by the copyright holder and what part has been
newly added or altered by another collaborator.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;#8220;Traditionally, copyright owners sold their copyrighted material in
exchange for money. &lt;b&gt;The lack of money changing hands in open source
licensing should not be presumed to mean that there is no economic
consideration, however.&lt;/b&gt; There are substantial benefits, including
economic benefits, to the creation and distribution of copyrighted works
under public licenses that range far beyond traditional license royalties.
For example, program creators may generate market share for their
programs by providing certain components free of charge. Similarly,
a programmer or company may increase its national or international
reputation by incubating open source projects. Improvement to a product
can come rapidly and free of charge from an expert not even known to the
copyright holder. The Eleventh Circuit has recognized the economic motives
inherent in public licenses, even where profit is not immediate&amp;#8230;.
(Program creator &amp;#8216;derived value from the distribution [under a public
license] because he was able to improve his Software based on suggestions
sent by end-users&amp;#8230; . It is logical that as the Software improved,
more end-users used his Software, thereby increasing [the programmer&amp;#8217;s]
recognition in his profession and the likelihood that the Software would
be improved even further.&amp;#8217;).&amp;#8221;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;#8220;&amp;#8230; The conditions set forth in the Artistic License are vital to enable
the copyright holder to retain the ability to benefit from the work of
downstream users. By requiring that users who modify or distribute the
copyrighted material retain the reference to the original source files,
downstream users are directed to Jacobsen=s website. Thus, downstream
users know about the collaborative effort to improve and expand the
SourceForge project once they learn of the &amp;#8216;upstream&amp;#8217; project from a
&amp;#8216;downstream&amp;#8217; distribution, and they may join in that effort.&amp;#8221;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;#8220;&amp;#8230; &lt;b&gt;Copyright holders who engage in open source licensing have the right
to control the modification and distribution of copyrighted material&lt;/b&gt;.
As the Second Circuit explained in Gilliam v. ABC, 538 F.2d 14, 21 (2d
Cir. 1976), the &amp;#8216;unauthorized editing of the underlying work, if proven,
would constitute an infringement of the copyright in that work similar
to any other use of a work that exceeded the license granted by the
proprietor of the copyright.&amp;#8217;  Copyright licenses are designed to support
the right to exclude; money damages alone do not support or enforce that
right. &lt;b&gt;The choice to exact consideration in the form of compliance with
the open source requirements of disclosure and explanation of changes,
rather than as a dollar-denominated fee, is entitled to no less legal
recognition. Indeed, because a calculation of damages is inherently
speculative, these types of license restrictions might well be rendered
meaningless absent the ability to enforce through injunctive relief.&lt;/b&gt;&amp;#8221;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&amp;#8220;&amp;#8230; The clear language of the Artistic License creates conditions
to protect the economic rights at issue in the granting of a public
license. These conditions govern the rights to modify and distribute
the computer programs and files included in the downloadable software
package. The attribution and modification transparency requirements
directly serve to drive traffic to the open source incubation page and to
inform downstream users of the project, which is a significant economic
goal of the copyright holder that the law will enforce. Through this
controlled spread of information, the copyright holder gains creative
collaborators to the open source project; by requiring that changes made
by downstream users be visible to the copyright holder and others, the
copyright holder learns about the uses for his software and gains others&amp;#8217;
knowledge that can be used to advance future software releases.&amp;#8221;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In short, this court ruling makes it clear that FLOSS
licenses really are legally enforceable&amp;#8230;
so it&amp;#8217;s safe for businesses to rely on them.
It also makes a number of clear statements that FLOSS really
does have economic value, even when money doesn&amp;#8217;t change hands -
a point I make in my article
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/essays/commercial-floss.html&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Free-Libre / Open Source Software (FLOSS) is Commercial Software&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
   </item>
  </channel>
</rss>