<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- name="generator" content="blosxom/2.0" -->

<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>David A. Wheeler's Blog   </title>
    <meta name="viewport" content="width=device-width, initial-scale=1.0"></meta>
    <link>https://www.dwheeler.com/blog</link>
    <description>David A. Wheeler's weblog.</description>
    <language>en</language>

  <item>
    <title>Initial Analysis of Underhanded Source Code</title>
    <meta name="viewport" content="width=device-width, initial-scale=1.0"></meta>
    <link>https://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2020/05/15#underhanded-code</link>
    <pubDate>Fri, 15 May 2020 19:11 GMT</pubDate>
    <!-- date: 2020-05-15 -->
    <description>
&lt;p&gt;
Announcing - a newly-available security paper I wrote! It&amp;#8217;s titled
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ida.org/-/media/feature/publications/i/in/initial-analysis-of-underhanded-source-code/d-13166.ashx&quot;
&gt;&amp;#8220;Initial Analysis of Underhanded Source Code&amp;#8221;
(by David A. Wheeler, IDA Document D-13166, April 2020)&lt;/a&gt;.
Here&amp;#8217;s what it&amp;#8217;s about, from its executive summary:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&amp;#8220;It is possible to develop software source code that appears benign
to human review but is actually malicious. In various competitions,
such as the Obfuscated V Contest and Underhanded C Contest,
software developers have demonstrated that it is possible to solve
a data processing problem “with covert malicious behavior [in the]
source code [that] easily passes visual inspection.”
This is not merely an academic concern; in 2003, an attacker attempted to
subvert the widely used Linux kernel by inserting underhanded software
(this attack inserted code that used = instead of ==, an easily missed,
one-character difference).
This paper provides a brief initial look at
underhanded source code, with the intent to eventually help develop
countermeasures against it. &amp;#8230;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;
This initial work suggests that countering underhanded code is not
an impossible task; it appears that a relatively small set of simple
countermeasures can significantly reduce the risk from underhanded
code. I recommend examining more samples, identifying a recommended
set of underhanded code countermeasures, and applying countermeasures
in situations where countering underhanded code is important and the
benefits exceed their costs.&amp;#8221;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In my experience there are usually ways to reduce security risks,
once you know about them.
This is another case in point; once you know that this is a potential
attack, there are a variety of ways to reduce their effectiveness.
I don&amp;#8217;t think this is the last word at all on this topic, but
I hope it can be immediately applied and that others can build on it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This was the last paper I wrote when I worked at IDA
(I now work at the Linux Foundation).
My thanks to IDA for releasing it!
My special thanks go to Margaret Myers, Torrance Gloss, and
Reginald N. Meeson, Jr., who all worked to make this paper possible.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So if you&amp;#8217;re interested in the topic, you can view the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ida.org/research-and-publications/publications/all/i/in/initial-analysis-of-underhanded-source-code&quot;&gt;Landing page for
IDA Document D-13166&lt;/a&gt; or go directly to the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ida.org/-/media/feature/publications/i/in/initial-analysis-of-underhanded-source-code/d-13166.ashx&quot;
&gt;PDF for IDA DOcument D-13166,
&amp;#8220;Initial Analysis of Underhanded Source Code&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt;.
(If that doesn&amp;#8217;t work, use this
&lt;a href=&quot;https://perma.cc/FVQ8-EKWA&quot;&gt;Perma.cc link to paper D-13166&lt;/a&gt;.)
Enjoy!
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
   </item>
  </channel>
</rss>