<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- name="generator" content="blosxom/2.0" -->

<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>David A. Wheeler's Blog   </title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog</link>
    <description>David A. Wheeler's weblog.</description>
    <language>en</language>

  <item>
    <title>ISPs Inserting Ads Into Your Pages: Unlawful Modifications (Copyright Violation)</title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2007/06/23#unlawful-modifications</link>
    <pubDate>Sat, 23 Jun 2007 11:20 GMT</pubDate>
    <!-- date: 2007-06-23 -->
    <description>
&lt;p&gt;
Here&amp;#8217;s a nasty trick.
Apparantly some
&lt;a href=&quot;http://yro.slashdot.org/yro/07/06/23/1233212.shtml&quot;&gt;
shady Internet Service Providers (ISPs) are
inserting advertizements into other people&amp;#8217;s web pages without their
permission&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I believe these are usually &lt;i&gt;illegal modifications&lt;/i&gt;.
Whoever creates a work automatically has a copyright on that work.
(If you&amp;#8217;re doing work for someone else, or if you
sell the copyright, &lt;i&gt;they&lt;/i&gt; have the copyright.)
Anyone who releases a public web page obviously grants others the right
to copy that work to &lt;i&gt;view&lt;/i&gt; it, but unless otherwise stated, you
don&amp;#8217;t have the right to &lt;i&gt;modify&lt;/i&gt; the work.
U.S. law also has &amp;#8220;fair use&amp;#8221; provisions that let you quote another work
without being sued, and so on, but those can&amp;#8217;t possibly be stretched into
letting someone insert ads.
The copyright owner can release works permitting such actions
(that&amp;#8217;s how Free-libre / open source software works), but they have to
give that permission&amp;#8230; you can&amp;#8217;t just unilaterally &lt;i&gt;modify&lt;/i&gt; it.
What really angers me is that they might insert stuff I am
morally opposed to, and sullying &lt;i&gt;my&lt;/i&gt; reputation.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If you run a website, here&amp;#8217;s a sample letter that you can send to inform
these ISPs that what they&amp;#8217;re doing is wrong.
&lt;pre&gt;
Dear (name here),

I am concerned that you appear to be violating copyright laws,
by unlawfully modifying and then redistributing copyrighted works
of mine and many others.

In particular, your &quot;terms of service&quot; say... (quote them, if you can).

My website, (www.dwheeler.com), distributes many copyrighted works
at no charge, but I do _NOT_ give the right to modify many of
those works.  Many other websites do the same.  (Some can add:
In addition, I have ads on my site; by adding your own ads, you are
diluting the value of MY ads and in essence stealing from me.)

Please stop modifying my web pages immediately.  It is my hope that
this was just a misunderstanding, and that we can settle this amicably.

Thank you very much.
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
   </item>
  </channel>
</rss>