<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- name="generator" content="blosxom/2.0" -->

<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>David A. Wheeler's Blog   </title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog</link>
    <description>David A. Wheeler's weblog.</description>
    <language>en</language>

  <item>
    <title>Challenges for securing closed source software</title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2008/08/21#closed-source-security</link>
    <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2008 15:48 GMT</pubDate>
    <!-- date: 2008-08-21 -->
    <description>
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#8217;ve just learned of a really interesting article by
&lt;a href=&quot;http://blogs.techrepublic.com.com/security/?p=549&quot;&gt;
Chad Perrin, &amp;#8220;10 security challenges facing closed source software&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt;.
He starts with my
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/secure-programs/Secure-Programs-HOWTO/&quot;&gt;
Secure Programming for Linux and Unix HOWTO&lt;/a&gt; book&amp;#8217;s list of
&amp;#8220;core requirements for developing secure software&amp;#8221;, which was
part of the section on developing secure open source software.
My list was really simple:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;First, people have to actually review the code.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Second, at least some of the people developing and reviewing the code must know how to write secure programs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Third, once found, problems need to be fixed quickly and their fixes distributed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
Lots of people have cited that list (and the book!), including
&lt;a href=&quot;http://googleonlinesecurity.blogspot.com/2008/05/contributing-to-open-source-software.html&quot;&gt;
Google&amp;#8217;s &amp;#8220;Contributing To Open Source Software Security&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At the time I made that list, I was primarily
thinking about that list as requirements for
open source software.
Chad Perrin had the interesting insight that the list applies to
closed source software too&amp;#8230; and then examined what the challenges are.
It&amp;#8217;s a really interesting list, I suggest taking a look at it!
He closes with a very interesting claim:
&amp;#8220;None of these disadvantages for closed source software are inflexible
or absolute. There’s no reason closed source software developed by a
corporate vendor can’t be as secure as an open source equivalent. It
should be pretty obvious that, all else being equal, the trend is for
circumstances to favor the security of open source software — at least
as far as these principles of software security are concerned.&amp;#8221;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
   </item>
  </channel>
</rss>