<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- name="generator" content="blosxom/2.0" -->

<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>David A. Wheeler's Blog   </title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog</link>
    <description>David A. Wheeler's weblog.</description>
    <language>en</language>

  <item>
    <title>Please point me to High-Assurance Free-Libre / Open Source Software (FLOSS) Components</title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2007/11/05#high-assurance-floss-components</link>
    <pubDate>Mon, 05 Nov 2007 14:19 GMT</pubDate>
    <!-- date: 2007-11-05 -->
    <description>
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#8217;m looking for
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/essays/high-assurance-floss.html#highassurancecomponents&quot;&gt;High Assurance and Free-Libre / Open Source Software (FLOSS) components&lt;/a&gt;.
Can anyone &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/contactme.html&quot;&gt;point me to ones I don&amp;#8217;t know about&lt;/a&gt;?
A little context might help, I suppose&amp;#8230;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A while back I posted a paper,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/essays/high-assurance-floss.html&quot;&gt;High Assurance (for Security or Safety) and Free-Libre / Open Source Software (FLOSS)&lt;/a&gt;.
For purposes of the paper,
I define &amp;#8220;high assurance software&amp;#8221;
as software where there&amp;#8217;s an &lt;i&gt;argument
that could convince skeptical parties&lt;/i&gt;
that the software &lt;i&gt;will always perform or never perform&lt;/i&gt;
certain key functions &lt;i&gt;without fail&lt;/i&gt;.
That means you have to show convincing evidence that there are
&lt;i&gt;absolutely no software defects&lt;/i&gt;
that would interfere with the software&amp;#8217;s key functions.
Almost all software built today is &lt;i&gt;not&lt;/i&gt; high assurance;
developing high assurance software is currently a specialist&amp;#8217;s field.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
High assurance and FLOSS are potentially a great match.
We achieve high assurance in scientific analysis and
mathematical proofs by subjecting them to peer review, and then
worldwide review.
FLOSS programs, unlike proprietary programs, can receive similar kinds of
review, and many FLOSS programs achieve
really good reliability figures for medium assurance.
So it can be easily argued that
stepping up to high assurance should be &lt;i&gt;easier&lt;/i&gt; for
FLOSS than for proprietary software.
In addition, there are a vast number of FLOSS tools that support developing
high assurance components,
including PVS, ACL2, Isabelle/HOL, prover9, and Alloy
(there&amp;#8217;s lots more, see the paper for more details).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Yet it&amp;#8217;s hard to find
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/essays/high-assurance-floss.html#highassurancecomponents&quot;&gt;High Assurance Free-Libre / Open Source Software (FLOSS) components&lt;/a&gt;.
To be fair, high assurance software components
are exceedingly rare in the non-FLOSS world as well.
But I suspect there are more than I&amp;#8217;ve found, and I hope that people
will help me by pointing them out to me.
I&amp;#8217;d like to know about such components for direct use, and also simply for
use as demonstrations of how to actually develop high assurance software.
Today, it&amp;#8217;s nearly impossible to explain how to develop high assurance
software, because there are almost no fully-published examples.
Existing &amp;#8220;formal methods successes&amp;#8221; papers generally
don&amp;#8217;t publish everything including their specs, proofs, and code&amp;#8230;
which makes it impossible to really learn how to do it.
And no, I don&amp;#8217;t &lt;i&gt;require&lt;/i&gt; that proofs prove every line of machine code;
but showing how correspondance demonstrations are made would be valuable,
and that&amp;#8217;s currently not well demonstrated by working examples.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you&amp;#8217;re curious about the general topic, take a peek at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/essays/high-assurance-floss.html&quot;&gt;High Assurance (for Security or Safety) and Free-Libre / Open Source Software (FLOSS)&lt;/a&gt;.
I&amp;#8217;ve collected lots of interesting information;
hopefully it will be useful to some of you.
And &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/contactme.html&quot;&gt;let me know&lt;/a&gt; of
high-assurance FLOSS components that I don&amp;#8217;t already know about.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
   </item>
  </channel>
</rss>