<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- name="generator" content="blosxom/2.0" -->

<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>David A. Wheeler's Blog   </title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog</link>
    <description>David A. Wheeler's weblog.</description>
    <language>en</language>

  <item>
    <title>Flawfinder version 1.25 released!</title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2004/05/31#flawfinder-1.25</link>
    <pubDate>Mon, 31 May 2004 15:26 GMT</pubDate>
    <!-- date: 2004-05-31 -->
    <description>
I&amp;#8217;ve released a new version of
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/flawfinder&quot;&gt;flawfinder&lt;/a&gt; - version 1.25.
Flawfinder is a simple program that examines C/C++ source code and
reports on likely security flaws in the program, ranked by risk level.
You can view the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/flawfinder/ChangeLog&quot;&gt;Flawfinder
ChangeLog&lt;/a&gt; for the details.
Here are some of the highlights:
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
Added more rules for finding problems by examining the
Red Hat Linux 9 documentation (the man3 man pages),
looking for phrases like &amp;#8220;do not use&amp;#8221;, &amp;#8220;security&amp;#8221;, and &amp;#8220;obsolete&amp;#8221;.
Thus, added rules for
cuserid, getlogin, getpass, mkstemp, getpw, memalign, as
well as the obsolete functions gsignal, ssignal, ulimit, usleep.
Flawfinder now has 137 rules that it checks automatically.
&lt;li&gt;
Added lengthy text to the manual to explain exactly how to use
flawfinder with vim and emacs.  This should also help
integrate flawfinder into other text editors/IDEs.
&lt;li&gt;
Fixed an error in &amp;#8212;columns format, so that the output is simply
&amp;#8220;filename:linenumber:columnnumber&amp;#8221; when &amp;#8212;columns (-C) is used.
&lt;li&gt;
Added shortcut single-letter commands (-D for &amp;#8212;dataonly,
-Q for &amp;#8212;quiet, -C for &amp;#8212;columns), so that invoking from
editors is easier.
&lt;li&gt;
Tries to autoremove some false positives, and
added a &amp;#8220;&amp;#8212;falsepositive&amp;#8221; (-F) option which tries to remove
many more.
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Just go to the 
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/flawfinder&quot;&gt;flawfinder home page&lt;/a&gt;
to get the latest version.
</description>
   </item>
  <item>
    <title>Added permanent location for patent protest</title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2004/05/18#patent-20040518</link>
    <pubDate>Tue, 18 May 2004 18:34 GMT</pubDate>
    <!-- date: 2004-05-18 -->
    <description>
&lt;p&gt;
I can&amp;#8217;t keep the protest page on patents up forever,
but I certainly want people to be able to access it.
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/blackout.html&quot;&gt;
So here&amp;#8217;s the permanent location of the patent blackout
page&lt;/a&gt;, so you can get its information even when it&amp;#8217;s
not the front page of my site.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; 
I&amp;#8217;ll occasionally place it back as the front page
until this issue gets resolved more reasonably.
In the meantime, I&amp;#8217;ve added a
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ffii.org.uk/ftc/ftc.html&quot;&gt;link
to relevant excerpts from the U.S. Federal
Trade Commission Report&lt;/a&gt;.
For example:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Many panelists and participants expressed the view that software
and Internet patents are impeding innovation.
They stated that such patents are impairing follow-on incentives,
increasing entry barriers, creating uncertainty that harms
incentives to invest in innovation, and producing patent thickets.
Panelists discussed how defensive patenting increases the complexity
of patent thickets and forces companies to divert resources from
R&amp;amp;D into obtaining patents.
Commentators noted that patent thickets make it more
difficult to commercialize new products and raise uncertainty
and investment risks. Some panelists also noted that hold-up
has become a problem that can result in higher prices being passed
along to consumers. 
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
Note that after discussing the various ways that patents
are intended to spur innovation,
&amp;#8220;Commentators were generally skeptical about the benefits of the
patent system in these [software and Internet] industries.&amp;#8221;
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
   </item>
  <item>
    <title>SLOCCount 2.24 Released!</title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2004/05/10#sloccount-2.24</link>
    <pubDate>Mon, 10 May 2004 00:37 GMT</pubDate>
    <!-- date: 2004-05-10 -->
    <description>
I&amp;#8217;ve just released
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/sloccount&quot;&gt;
SLOCCount version 2.24&lt;/a&gt;.
SLOCCount is a set of tools for automatically
counting physical Source Lines of Code (SLOC) in a large number of languages
of a potentially large set of programs.
This suite of tools was used in my papers
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/sloc&quot;&gt;
&lt;i&gt;More than a Gigabuck: Estimating GNU/Linux&amp;#8217;s Size&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
and
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/sloc&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Estimating Linux&amp;#8217;s Size&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
to measure the SLOC of entire GNU/Linux distributions.
&lt;a href=&quot;http://people.debian.org/~jgb/debian-counting&quot;&gt;Others have
measured Debian GNU/Linux&lt;/a&gt; using this tool suite.
SLOCCount runs on GNU/Linux, FreeBSD, Windows,
Apple Mac OS X (as of this version),
and hopefully on other systems too.
&lt;p&gt;
Version 2.24 introduces a few minor bugfixes and improvements.
Now SLOCCount automatically tries to use several different MD5 programs, until
it finds one that works - this is more flexible, and as a result,
it now works out-of-the-box on Apple Mac OS X.
SLOCCount now accepts &amp;#8220;.&amp;#8221; as the directory to analyze,
it correctly identifies wrapper scripts left by libtool as
automatically generated code, and it correctly identifies debian/rules
files as makefiles. Also, installation documentation has improved.
My thanks to Jesus M. Gonzalez-Barahona for telling me about the
Debian bug reports and testing of candidate versions.
My thanks to Koryn Grant, who told me what needed to be done
to get SLOCCount running on Mac OS X (and for testing my change).
This version resolves Debian Bug reports #173699,
#159609, and #200348.
</description>
   </item>
  <item>
    <title>Counter EU Council of Ministers&amp;#8217; foolish patent decision</title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2004/05/07#patent-may2004</link>
    <pubDate>Fri, 07 May 2004 13:50 GMT</pubDate>
    <!-- date: 2004-05-07 -->
    <description>
The FFII has learned that the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://swpat.ffii.org/news/04/cons0507/index.en.html&quot;&gt;
EU Council of Ministers has decided to ignore the EU Parliment,
and instead plan to
establish a reckless &amp;#8220;patent everything&amp;#8221; approach to software and
business models&lt;/a&gt;.
This is an incredibly bad idea; US experience has shown uncontrolled
patenting is an unmitigated disaster for commerce,
and there&amp;#8217;s no reason for Europe to import &lt;i&gt;bad&lt;/i&gt; ideas.
It&amp;#8217;s also exposing some serious problems with EU governance;
members of the European Parliament across the political spectrum
are condemning this blatant disrespect for democracy in Europe.
&lt;p&gt;
See the &lt;a href=&quot;http://ffii.org&quot;&gt;FFII for more information&lt;/a&gt;,
including a simple example of why patents are bad &amp;#8212; they have
&lt;a href=&quot;http://webshop.ffii.org/&quot;&gt;
a demo web page that would be illegal if these laws were passed&lt;/a&gt;,
because Europe has already granted patents on the idea of a web store, etc.
In the process of gathering information on
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/innovation&quot;&gt;software innovation&lt;/a&gt;
it became quite clear to me that, while patents may be useful in the
hardware fields they were intended for, patents actually
impede innovation in software and business methods.
Which is why US law originally forbid them (until these laws were
stealthily overturned by patent lawyers), and why most countries
still forbid them.
&lt;p&gt;
I urge Europeans to
&lt;a href=&quot;http://kwiki.ffii.org/SwpDemo0405En&quot;&gt;
get involved - see this FFII page for more information&lt;/a&gt;.
</description>
   </item>
  </channel>
</rss>