<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- name="generator" content="blosxom/2.0" -->

<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>David A. Wheeler's Blog   </title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog</link>
    <description>David A. Wheeler's weblog.</description>
    <language>en</language>

  <item>
    <title>California: Open Source Software is Okay!</title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2010/01/09#california-oss-ok</link>
    <pubDate>Sat, 09 Jan 2010 13:07 GMT</pubDate>
    <!-- date: 2010-01-09 -->
    <description>&lt;p&gt;
The California state government has officially declared that
it&amp;#8217;s okay to use open source software inside the
California state government.
On January 7, 2010, the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cio.ca.gov/Government/IT_Policy/ITPL.html&quot;&gt;
California Office of the State Chief Information Officer (OCIO)
released
Information Technology Policy Letter (ITPL) 10-01, titled
&amp;#8220;Open Source Software Policy&amp;#8221; &lt;/a&gt;.
A key purpose of ITPL 10-01 is to
&amp;#8220;formally establish the use of Open Source Software (OSS)
in California state government as an acceptable practice&amp;#8221;,
and the first sentence of its policy statement is that
&amp;#8220;The OCIO permits the use of OSS&amp;#8221;.
It even includes the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.opensource.org/docs/osd&quot;&gt;
ten-point open source definition (OSD)
as promulgated by the Open Source Intiative&lt;/a&gt;, to make sure that
there&amp;#8217;s no misunderstanding.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I think this is a big deal.
Officially saying &amp;#8220;it&amp;#8217;s okay to use free/libre/open source software
(FLOSS)&amp;#8221; is really important
before FLOSS can get widespread use in governments.
Most technologists already understand the potential advantages of FLOSS,
but they encounter a lot of resistance when they try to use or develop
FLOSS in large organizations like governments.
Far too many middle managers are instinctively afraid of change
from &amp;#8220;the way we&amp;#8217;ve always done it&amp;#8221;.
For example, they may be afraid of unseen problems, or
afraid their bosses will rake them over the coals later.
Far too often the middle managers have misunderstandings about FLOSS, too.
For example, many managers still believe the myth that
&amp;#8220;you can&amp;#8217;t get support&amp;#8221; and are unaware
of the many companies that &lt;i&gt;do&lt;/i&gt; provide such support.
Companies that make competing proprietary products are
delighted (of course) when governments don&amp;#8217;t consider their
competition&amp;#8230; but
in an era of tight budgets, it doesn&amp;#8217;t make sense for governments
to ignore competing (and often less expensive) products.
When top officials give official &amp;#8220;top cover&amp;#8221; permission to consider
FLOSS, then the technologists and middle managers are far more
likely to fairly and honestly consider them.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Also, the fact that it&amp;#8217;s California matters.
The &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Economy_of_California&quot;&gt;
economy of the California&lt;/a&gt;
is larger than most countries (if it were a country, it would be
third through tenth in the world depending on how you measure it).
Anything the state of California does can influence other states
and countries; acts like this further legitimize the user of
Free/Libre/Open Source Software (FLOSS).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Of course, the state of California isn&amp;#8217;t the
only government organization to release a memo officially declaring
that it&amp;#8217;s okay to use free/libre/open source software (FLOSS).
Just looking inside the U.S., the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://cio-nii.defense.gov/docs/OpenSourceInDoD.pdf&quot;&gt;
U.S. DoD did this in 2003&lt;/a&gt;, the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.whitehouse.gov/omb/memoranda/fy04/m04-16.html&quot;&gt;
Office of Management and Budget (OMB) released a somewhat similar
memo in 2004 that applied to the entire U.S. federal government&lt;/a&gt;, the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.doncio.navy.mil/PolicyView.aspx?ID=312&quot;&gt;U.S. Navy
did this in 2007&lt;/a&gt;, and the
the &lt;a href=&quot;http://cio-nii.defense.gov/sites/oss/&quot;&gt;U.S. DoD released
clarifying guidance in 2009 re-emphasizing this point&lt;/a&gt;.
And that&amp;#8217;s only a few examples from U.S. government organizations;
the examples from around the world are legion.
It&amp;#8217;s really difficult to get people to change what they do&amp;#8230;
as you can tell from the number of times that various U.S. federal government
organizations have had to state and re-state it.
Still, they really do have an effect.
Official policy statements that FLOSS is used, such as the one
California just released, are a necessary first step to changing things
from &amp;#8220;the way we&amp;#8217;ve always done things&amp;#8221;.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
   </item>
  </channel>
</rss>