<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- name="generator" content="blosxom/2.0" -->

<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>David A. Wheeler's Blog   </title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog</link>
    <description>David A. Wheeler's weblog.</description>
    <language>en</language>

  <item>
    <title>Updated my essay on Software Configuration Management Security</title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2004/04/16#scm-security1</link>
    <pubDate>Fri, 16 Apr 2004 23:34 GMT</pubDate>
    <!-- date: 2004-04-16 -->
    <description>
I&amp;#8217;ve updated my essay on
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/essays/scm-security.html&quot;&gt;Software Configuration Management (SCM) Security&lt;/a&gt;.
That essay is relatively new, and I&amp;#8217;ve added more now.
Today we use SCM tools to manage our complicated software,
yet we&amp;#8217;re not paying enough attention to those tools&amp;#8217; security
requirements.
&lt;p&gt;
For example, few SCM tools think about the problem of handling
malicious developers (who are &lt;i&gt;trying&lt;/i&gt; to insert Trojan horses) or
about countering people who gain root access on a centralized system
being used as the SCM data repository&amp;#8230; even though that&amp;#8217;s already
happening.
There &lt;i&gt;are&lt;/i&gt; ways to deal with those kinds of attacks&amp;#8230; but you
have to think about them to counter them.
&lt;p&gt;
One of the recent additions to the essay
is based on an interesting email I received from
Dr. Carsten Bormann of the University of Bremen.
He mentioned a specialized attack that he terms the
&amp;#8220;encumbrance pollution attack&amp;#8221;.
In an encumberance pollution attack, the attacker inserts material
that cannot be legally included.
&lt;p&gt;
To understand it, first
imagine an SCM with perfectly indestructible history.
The attacker steals developer credentials, or is himself a malicious
developer, and checks in a change that contains some encumbered material.
&amp;#8220;Encumbered&amp;#8221; material is simply material which cannot be legally included.
Examples include child pornography, slanderous/libelous statements, or
code which has copyright or patent encumberances.
This could be very advantageous, for example, a company
might hire a malicious developer to insert that company&amp;#8217;s code into a
competing product, and then sue the competitor for copyright infringement,
knowing that their SCM system &amp;#8220;can&amp;#8217;t&amp;#8221; undo the problem.
Or a lazy programmer might copy code that they have no right to copy
(this is rare in open source software projects, because every line of code
and who provided it is a matter of public record, but it proprietary
projects do have this risk).
&lt;p&gt;
Any SCM can record a change that essentially undoes a previous change,
but if the history is indestructable and viewable by all, then
you can&amp;#8217;t get rid of the history.
This makes your SCM archive irrevocably encumbered.
This can especially be a problem if the SCM is indestructably recording
proposals by outsiders!
&lt;p&gt;
Anyway, take a look at
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/essays/scm-security.html&quot;&gt;Software Configuration Management (SCM) Security&lt;/a&gt;.
</description>
   </item>
  <item>
    <title>Treat Washington, DC as Part of Maryland for Congressional Elections</title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2004/04/16#dc-in-maryland</link>
    <pubDate>Fri, 16 Apr 2004 22:29 GMT</pubDate>
    <!-- date: 2004-04-16 -->
    <description>
The U.S. has encouraged democracy abroad through the years.
Yet due to strange quirks of history, residents of the U.S. capital &amp;#8212;
Washington, DC &amp;#8212; cannot vote in U.S. Congressional elections.
That is, simply put, absurd.
I&amp;#8217;m a big believer in democracy, and this is a quirk that needs fixing.
Several solutions have been proposed, but I think one solution
in particular stands above the rest and hasn&amp;#8217;t gotten the
attention it deserves.
What&amp;#8217;s that solution?
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/essays/dc-in-maryland.html&quot;&gt;Treat Washington, DC as Part of Maryland for Congressional Elections&lt;/a&gt;.
See my essay for more details.
</description>
   </item>
  <item>
    <title>Stop European Software Patents</title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2004/04/09#european-patent2004</link>
    <pubDate>Fri, 09 Apr 2004 14:11 GMT</pubDate>
    <!-- date: 2004-04-09 -->
    <description>
As you can tell, I&amp;#8217;ve placed a protest on my front page
about the push in Europe to permit software patents.
Patent lawyers are trying to get laws passed to
permit unlimited patenting of software, a foolish idea
that the European Parliment has already rejected.
The &lt;a href=&quot;http://ffii.org&quot;&gt;ffii.org&lt;/a&gt; and other
groups have more information on the topic.
Please get others to stop this thing.
</description>
   </item>
  <item>
    <title>NewsForge interviews me on Proprietary vs. OSS/FS TCO</title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2004/04/07#microsoft-tco</link>
    <pubDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2004 18:57 GMT</pubDate>
    <!-- date: 2004-04-07 -->
    <description>
&lt;a href=&quot;http://software.newsforge.com/software/04/04/02/179211.shtml?tid=132&amp;amp;tid=150&amp;amp;tid=82&quot;&gt;
NewsForge has just posted an interview of me, where I discuss
the Microsoft-funded studies claiming that Microsoft&amp;#8217;s proprietary products
have a lower total cost of ownership (TCO) than
Open Source Software/Free Software (OSS/FS)&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;p&gt;
My answers shouldn&amp;#8217;t be surprising to those who&amp;#8217;ve read
my other writings.  For example, I say that:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&amp;#8220;TCO is extremely sensitive to a specific circumstance, so
a TCO for one situation doesn&amp;#8217;t usually apply to other cases.
I&amp;#8217;m sure that there are cases where Microsoft&amp;#8217;s approach has
a lower TCO than alternatives, so in those specific cases it&amp;#8217;s true.
However, there are also cases where open source software or
Linux-based solutions have a lower TCO.
You really have to consider all the costs for your specific situation,
and your results may differ.&amp;#8221;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I don&amp;#8217;t have a lot of faith in Microsoft&amp;#8217;s studies,
because Microsoft funded almost all of them&amp;#8230; a concern I
discuss in the interview.
As I say,
&amp;#8220;There may be useful information in the self-funded studies,
but I don&amp;#8217;t have any way to be confident with them.&amp;#8221;
There are just too many ways for a vendor to tweak studies they fund.
Oh, and I&amp;#8217;d say the same thing about a study funded by Red Hat or IBM or
Apple or anyone else.
You should give much more weight to &lt;i&gt;independent&lt;/i&gt; studies.
&lt;p&gt;
Want more details?
&lt;a href=&quot;http://software.newsforge.com/software/04/04/02/179211.shtml?tid=132&amp;amp;tid=150&amp;amp;tid=82&quot;&gt;Take a peek at the interview.&lt;/a&gt;
</description>
   </item>
  </channel>
</rss>