<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- name="generator" content="blosxom/2.0" -->

<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>David A. Wheeler's Blog   </title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog</link>
    <description>David A. Wheeler's weblog.</description>
    <language>en</language>

  <item>
    <title>Added &amp;#8220;MapReduce&amp;#8221; to the &amp;#8220;Software Innovations&amp;#8221; list</title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2007/11/04#mapreduce</link>
    <pubDate>Sun, 04 Nov 2007 00:08 GMT</pubDate>
    <!-- date: 2007-11-04 -->
    <description>
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.krugle.com/?p=272&quot;&gt;Ken Krugler&amp;#8217;s recent blog&lt;/a&gt;
said that my article of
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/innovation/innovation.html&quot;&gt;
The Most Important Software Innovations&lt;/a&gt; was &amp;#8220;very good&amp;#8221;, but he
was surprised that I hadn&amp;#8217;t included
&lt;a href=&quot;http://labs.google.com/papers/mapreduce.html&quot;&gt;MapReduce&lt;/a&gt;
as an important software innovation.
Basically, MapReduce makes writing certain kinds of
programs that process &lt;i&gt;huge&lt;/i&gt; amounts of data, on vast distributed
clusters, remarkably easy and efficient.
(&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MapReduce&quot;&gt;Wikipedia explains
MapReduce&lt;/a&gt;, including links to alternative implementations like
the open source &lt;a href=&quot;http://lucene.apache.org/hadoop/&quot;&gt;Hadoop&lt;/a&gt;.)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It&amp;#8217;s not because I didn&amp;#8217;t know about MapReduce;
I read about it almost immediately after it got published.
I thought it was &lt;i&gt;very&lt;/i&gt; promising, and even forwarded the original
paper to some co-workers.
I think MapReduce is especially promising because, now that we have
cheap commodity computers, having a way to &lt;i&gt;easily&lt;/i&gt; exploit their
capabilities is really valuable.
But even with something this promising, I didn&amp;#8217;t want to add it to
my list of innovations right away - after all,
maybe after a little while it turns out to be not so helpful.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Currently, there&amp;#8217;s aren&amp;#8217;t many who have Google-sized clusters of computers
available.
But it&amp;#8217;s clear that this approach is useful in many other circumstances
as well.
It&amp;#8217;s new, but I think it&amp;#8217;s stood the test of time enough that it&amp;#8217;s
a worthy addition&amp;#8230; so I&amp;#8217;ve just added it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One interesting issue is that the
MapReduce framework is itself built primarily on
the &amp;#8220;map&amp;#8221; and &amp;#8220;reduce&amp;#8221; functions, which are far, far older.
So, is MapReduce really a &lt;i&gt;new&lt;/i&gt; idea,
or is it just a high-quality implementation of an old idea?
I&amp;#8217;ll accept that it&amp;#8217;s a new idea, but that can be difficult to judge.
This judgment doesn&amp;#8217;t &lt;i&gt;really&lt;/i&gt; matter unless you think
software patents are a good idea
(since every software patents in theory prevents progress for 20 years).
But I think it&amp;#8217;s quite clear that software patents are a foolish idea,
and it&amp;#8217;s clear that others have come to the same conclusion.
&lt;a href=&quot;http://press.ffii.org/Press_releases/Economist_Critic_of_Software_Patents_gets_Nobel_Prize&quot;&gt;
Eric S. Maskin, an economist who has long criticised the patenting
of software, recently received the 2007 Nobel Prize for Economics&lt;/a&gt;.
Here&amp;#8217;s a nice quote:
&amp;#8220;&amp;#8230; when patent protection was extended to software in the 1980s,
[&amp;#8230;] standard arguments would predict that R&amp;amp;D
intensity and productivity should have increased among patenting firms.
Consistent with our model, however, these increases did not occur.&amp;#8221;
Someone who correctly predicted that software patents were harmful
to innovation just received a Nobel prize.
I hope to someday see people receive other prizes because they
ended software patenting in the United States.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
   </item>
  </channel>
</rss>