<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- name="generator" content="blosxom/2.0" -->

<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>David A. Wheeler's Blog   </title>
    <meta name="viewport" content="width=device-width, initial-scale=1.0"></meta>
    <link>https://www.dwheeler.com/blog</link>
    <description>David A. Wheeler's weblog.</description>
    <language>en</language>

  <item>
    <title>FOSS Contributor Survey</title>
    <meta name="viewport" content="width=device-width, initial-scale=1.0"></meta>
    <link>https://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2020/07/30#cii-survey</link>
    <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jul 2020 12:45 GMT</pubDate>
    <!-- date: 2020-07-30 -->
    <description>
&lt;p&gt;
If you contribute to Free/Open Source Software,
please take the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://hbs.qualtrics.com/jfe/form/SV_enfu6tjRM0QzwQB&quot;
&gt;FOSS Contributor Survey&lt;/a&gt;!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This survey is a collaboration between the Linux Foundation&amp;#8217;s Core
Infrastructure Initiative and the Laboratory for Innovation Science
at Harvard. Some of the questions are specific to those who write
software; if you contribute, but don&amp;#8217;t write software, just skip
those questions.
The goal is to get a better understanding about its development so that
we can best work out how to improve its security and sustainability.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Also: please tell others who develop this software about the survey!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One interesting complication about this survey is that it&amp;#8217;s difficult to
get the word out about such a general survey.
People talk about the &amp;#8220;open source software community&amp;#8221;, but in practice
there isn&amp;#8217;t &lt;i&gt;one&lt;/i&gt; such community, there are many communities
with some overlap.
I don&amp;#8217;t want to spam people who have never expressed any interest
in information like this.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#8217;m currently talking with some folks in the Linux Foundatinon leadership
about sending a one-time email &lt;i&gt;only&lt;/i&gt; to developers who are
&lt;i&gt;already&lt;/i&gt; signed up for Linux Foundation mailing lists
that are focused on developing open source software.
We don&amp;#8217;t want to spam people, but I think it&amp;#8217;s reasonable to believe
that people on those mailing lists &lt;i&gt;are&lt;/i&gt; interestd in information
related to the development of open source software.
One problem with sending to multiple mailing lists is that we don&amp;#8217;t want
to annoy people by having them receive multiple copies, so we want
to work out a way so an individual only gets one copy.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#8217;ve never done this before, and I hate spam myself.
So I&amp;#8217;m &lt;i&gt;first&lt;/i&gt; checking with Linux Foundation leaders and program
managers to see if they think this is reasonable.
I think it is, but it&amp;#8217;s easy to justify anything to yourself, so
I&amp;#8217;m waiting to hear from others about what they think.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So getting back to the point -
if you contribute to Free/Open Source Software,
please take the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://hbs.qualtrics.com/jfe/form/SV_enfu6tjRM0QzwQB&quot;
&gt;FOSS Contributor Survey&lt;/a&gt;!
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
   </item>
  </channel>
</rss>