<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- name="generator" content="blosxom/2.0" -->

<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>David A. Wheeler's Blog   </title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog</link>
    <description>David A. Wheeler's weblog.</description>
    <language>en</language>

  <item>
    <title>Why copyright damage limits don&amp;#8217;t hurt FLOSS</title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2009/04/22#damage-limits-dont-harm-floss</link>
    <pubDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2009 23:50 GMT</pubDate>
    <!-- date: 2009-04-22 -->
    <description>
&lt;p&gt;
There&amp;#8217;s a move afoot to argue that copyright infringement penalties should
bear a rational relationship to the value of what was infringed.
You &lt;i&gt;might&lt;/i&gt; think that this could harm Free/Libre/Open Source Software
(FLOSS), but I don&amp;#8217;t think so.  
Here&amp;#8217;s why.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
First: This is all being brought to a head by the
current file-sharing lawsuit against Boston University graduate student
Joel Tenenbaum, which raises a number of interesting questions.
One issue that I find particularly interesting is the issue of
statutory damages:
Are fines from $750 to $150,000 per song (worth at most $1),
non-commercially shared without permission, even legal under the
US Constitution?
Or, are these fines so excessive that they are unconstitutional?
&lt;a href=&quot;http://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/news/2009/03/obama-admin-nothing-wrong-with-statutory-damages.ars&quot;&gt;
Ars Technical gives a brief summary of the case&lt;/a&gt;, if you haven&amp;#8217;t
been following it.
The
&lt;a href=&quot;http://beckermanlegal.com/pdf/?file=/Lawyer_Copyright_Internet_Law/sony_tenenbaum_090320FSFAmicusBrief.pdf&quot;&gt;
Free Software Foundation (FSF)&amp;#8217;s
Amicus Brief in Connection with defendant&amp;#8217;s motion to dismiss on grounds of unconstitutionality
of copyright act statutory damages as applied
to infringement of single MP3 files&lt;/a&gt;
argues that these penalties grossly exceed the crime;
the FSF argues that the
&amp;#8220;State Farm/Gore due process test applicable to punitive damage awards
is likewise applicable to statutory damages, and in particular bars
the suggestion that each infringement of an MP3 file having a retail value
of 99 cents or less may be punishable by statutory damages of
from $750 to $150,000 &amp;#8212; or from 2,100 to 425,000 times the actual damages&amp;#8221;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Frankly, I think the FSF and Tenenbaum have a reasonable argument on this point.
People who shoplift a CD from a store would definitely pay penalties when
caught, but those penalties would bear some relationship to the value of the
property stolen, and would be &lt;i&gt;far&lt;/i&gt; smaller than a file-sharer.
This notion that the &amp;#8220;punishment should fit the crime&amp;#8221; is certainly not new;
Proverbs 6:30-31 talks about thieves paying sevenfold if they are caught.
That doesn&amp;#8217;t make such actions &lt;i&gt;right&lt;/i&gt; - but unjust 
penalties aren&amp;#8217;t right either.
I think a lot of the problem is that copyright laws were originally
written when only rich people with printing presses could really
make and distribute many copies of material.
Today,
8-year-olds can distribute as much information as the New York Times, and
the law hasn&amp;#8217;t caught up.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
But does the FSF risk subverting Free/Libre/Open Source Software (FLOSS)
by making this argument?
After all, FLOSS developers also depend on copyright law to enforce
certain conditions, and often charge $0 for copies of their software.
If the penalties would be limited to &amp;#8220;7 times the original cost&amp;#8221;,
would that make FLOSS development impossible?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I don&amp;#8217;t think there&amp;#8217;s any problem, but for some people that may not be obvious.
The difference is that in a typical music copyright infringement case,
the filesharer &lt;i&gt;could&lt;/i&gt; purchase the right to do what they&amp;#8217;re doing for
a relatively low price, something typically &lt;i&gt;not&lt;/i&gt; true for FLOSS.
For example, under normal circumstances
it&amp;#8217;s perfectly legal to buy a song for $1, and then transfer that
song to someone else (as long as you destroy your own copies),
so sharing that song with 10 people is legal after paying $10.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In contrast, violations of FLOSS licenses often can&amp;#8217;t be made
legal by simply buying the rights.
If you violate the revised BSD license by removing all credits to the
original author, there&amp;#8217;s typically no &amp;#8220;alternative&amp;#8221; legal
version available for sale without the author credits.
(Indeed, under legal systems with strict &amp;#8220;moral rights&amp;#8221; it may not even be
possible.)
Similarly, if you violate the GPL by releasing binary software yet
refusing to release its source code,
there&amp;#8217;s often no way to pay additional money
to the original authors for that privilege.
In &lt;i&gt;some&lt;/i&gt; cases, GPL&amp;#8217;ed software is released via a dual-use license
(e.g., &amp;#8220;GPL or proprietary&amp;#8221;), with the proprietary version costing additional
money; in &lt;i&gt;those&lt;/i&gt; cases you &lt;i&gt;do&lt;/i&gt; have a
value that you can compare against.
In cases where there &lt;i&gt;is&lt;/i&gt; a value you can compare against, then
you should use that value to help determine the penalty.
Otherwise, a much stiffer penalty is justified, because there is no
method for the infringer to &amp;#8220;buy&amp;#8221; his or her way out, and their
actions risk making functional products (not just entertainment) unsupportable.
As noted in the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cafc.uscourts.gov/opinions/08-1001.pdf&quot;&gt;
United States Court of Appeals for the Federal Circuit case 2008-1001,
JACOBSEN v. KATZER&lt;/a&gt;,
the court essentially
found that failing to obey the conditions of an open source software
license led to copyright infringement.
(For more on this particular case,
see &lt;a href=&quot;http://lawandlifesiliconvalley.blogspot.com/2007/08/new-open-source-legal-decision-jacobsen.html&quot;&gt;New Open Source Legal Decision: Jacobsen &amp;amp; Katzer and How Model Train Software Will Have an Important Effect on Open Source Licensing&lt;/a&gt;.)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So I think that it &lt;i&gt;does&lt;/i&gt; make sense to limit copyright
penalties based on the value of the original infringed item&amp;#8230; but
that doing so does not (necessarily) put FLOSS development processes
at risk.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
   </item>
  </channel>
</rss>