<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- name="generator" content="blosxom/2.0" -->

<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>David A. Wheeler's Blog   </title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog</link>
    <description>David A. Wheeler's weblog.</description>
    <language>en</language>

  <item>
    <title>Autonumbering supported in Firefox 1.5!</title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2006/06/02#firefox-autonumbering</link>
    <pubDate>Fri, 02 Jun 2006 21:31 GMT</pubDate>
    <!-- date: 2006-06-02 -->
    <description>
&lt;p&gt;
Here&amp;#8217;s another reason to use Firefox as your web browser, besides the fact that
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2005/08/06/#ie-horrific&quot;&gt;Firefox has
a better security record&lt;/a&gt; and that Firefox has
&lt;a href=&quot;http://news.com.com/Microsoft+yielding+to+IE+standards+pressure/2100-1032_3-5620988.html&quot;&gt;better
support for web standards in general.&lt;/a&gt;
Firefox 1.5 has added autonumbering support, and sites like mine are
starting to use it.
If you&amp;#8217;re using a non-compliant web browser,
like the current version of Internet Explorer,
you&amp;#8217;re missing out.
But let&amp;#8217;s back up a bit to the basics: HTML.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.w3.org/MarkUp/&quot;&gt;HTML&lt;/a&gt; has been a
spectacularly successful standard for sharing
information - web pages around the world use it.
I write a lot of my papers directly in HTML, because it&amp;#8217;s easy,
using HTML makes them easily accessible to everyone, and it&amp;#8217;s a
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/essays/opendocument-open.html&quot;&gt;
completely open standard&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
But HTML has several weaknesses if you&amp;#8217;re writing long or
technical reports.
One especially important one is automatic numbering of headers:
the original HTML specification can&amp;#8217;t do it.
When you&amp;#8217;re reading a long report, it can be hard to keep track of
where you are, so having every heading numbered (such as
&amp;#8220;section 2.4.3&amp;#8221;) is &lt;i&gt;really&lt;/i&gt; helpful.
This can be solved by having programs directly insert the heading numbers
numbers into the HTML text, but that&amp;#8217;s a messy and kludgy solution.
It&amp;#8217;d be much
better if browsers automatically added numbered headings where appropriate,
so that the HTML file itself is simple and clean.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The W3C (the standards group in charge of HTML and related
standards) agreed that automatic numbering was important,
and included support for automatic numbering in the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.w3.org/Style/CSS/&quot;&gt;
Cascading Style Sheets (CSS) standard&lt;/a&gt; way back in 1998.
CSS is an important support standard for HTML, so that should have been it&amp;#8230;
but it wasn&amp;#8217;t.
Both Netscape and Microsoft decided to not fully implement the standard,
nor try to fix the standard so that they &lt;i&gt;would&lt;/i&gt; implement it.
Soon afterwards Microsoft gained dominant market share, and then
let their browser stagnate (why bother improving it, since there was
no competition?).
It looked like we, the users, would never get basic
capabilities in HTML like auto-numbering.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#8217;m happy to report that
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.spreadfirefox.com/?q=affiliates&amp;amp;id=31988&amp;amp;t=60&quot;&gt;
Firefox 1.5 has added support for auto-numbering&lt;/a&gt; headings and
other constructs too.
So I&amp;#8217;ve modified my
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/essays/paper.css&quot;&gt;CSS file for
papers and essays&lt;/a&gt; so it auto-number headings;
I&amp;#8217;ve released my CSS file under the MIT/X license, so anyone else can use it.
If you develop web content you may want to look
at examples like mine for a reason, because&amp;#8230;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It turns out that the story is more complicated.
In the process of implementing auto-numbering,
the Firefox developers found a serious problem with the CSS specification.
Oops!
The &lt;a href=&quot;https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=3247&quot;&gt;
Mozilla Firefox bug #3247&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.davidflanagan.com/blog/2005_08.html#000075&quot;&gt;
David Flanagan&amp;#8217;s blog&lt;/a&gt; discuss this further.
The Firefox developers talked with the W3C, and the W3C ended up creating
&amp;#8220;CSS 2.1&amp;#8221;, an updated/patched version of the CSS2 standard
that is in the process of being formally released.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What this means is that the examples for autonumbering
in the &amp;#8220;official&amp;#8221; original CSS2 standard won&amp;#8217;t actually work!
Instead, you need to follow a slightly different approach as defined
in the patched CSS2.1 specification.
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Technical stuff:&lt;/b&gt;
The basic problem involves scoping issues.
To solve it, the counter-reset property &lt;i&gt;must&lt;/i&gt; be in the
main heading names (like h1, h2, etc.), and &lt;i&gt;not&lt;/i&gt; in the
&amp;#8220;before&amp;#8221; sections (like h1:before, h2:before, etc.) - in spite of
all the examples in the original CSS2 spec.
You can put counter-increment in either place, though the spec
puts them in the :before sections so I have too.
&lt;!-- Here's the W3C example.  I don't think it matters; I think
     what matters is the location of the counter-reset.
H1:before {
    content: &quot;Chapter &quot; counter(chapter) &quot;. &quot;;
    counter-increment: chapter;  /* Add 1 to chapter */
}
H1 {
    counter-reset: section;      /* Set section to 0 */
}
The latest examples in CSS2.1 working draft of 11 April 2006
move the counter-reset property to main heading names, but keep the
counter-increment property in the &quot;:before&quot; sections.
--&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now people have yet another reason to upgrade to Firefox.
Firefox has had better standards support for some time;
there are now many sites that won&amp;#8217;t display properly
(or as well) if your browser doesn&amp;#8217;t support the standards well.
But here is a clear and functionally important difference.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#8217;m a big believer in standards, but they can only help users if
they are implemented, and they will only be implemented if
users demand standards compliance.
I think that the more people switch to standards-compliant browsers,
and the more that sites use standards (to encourage people to switch),
the more pressure it will bring on the other browser makers to catch up.
And that would be great for all computer users.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
More broadly, this is also a good example of why it&amp;#8217;s important to have
implementations try out standards before they are frozen;
they help avoid mistakes like this.
Today,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/essays/open-standards-open-source.html&quot;&gt;
essentially every successful open standard is implemented by
free-libre/open source software (FLOSS)&lt;/a&gt; - this makes sure that the
standard is implementable, helps all understand what the standard
means, and also helps other developers understand at least one way
to implement it.
This doesn&amp;#8217;t mean standards aren&amp;#8217;t important; standards are vital!
And this also shows that when a mistake is made by a standards body,
life is not over;
standards bodies can work with implementors to fix problems.
In fact, this
shows that the best standards are those created from an
interplay between standards developers and implementors, where
standards are then made official after actual implementation experience.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
   </item>
  </channel>
</rss>