<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- name="generator" content="blosxom/2.0" -->

<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>David A. Wheeler's Blog   </title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog</link>
    <description>David A. Wheeler's weblog.</description>
    <language>en</language>

  <item>
    <title>Insecure open source software libraries?</title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2012/04/03#insecure-libraries</link>
    <pubDate>Tue, 03 Apr 2012 14:00 GMT</pubDate>
    <!-- date: 2012-04-03 -->
    <description>
&lt;p&gt;
The news is abuzz about a new report,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aspectsecurity.com/blog/the-unfortunate-reality-of-insecure-libraries/&quot;&gt;&amp;#8220;The Unfortunate Reality of Insecure Libraries&amp;#8221; (by Aspect Security, in partnership with Sonatype)&lt;/a&gt;.
Some news articles about it, like
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.networkworld.com/news/2012/032612-open-source-vulnerabilities-257645.html&quot;&gt;Open source code libraries seen as rife with vulnerabilities (Network World)&lt;/a&gt;
make it sound like open source software (OSS) is especially bad.
(To be fair, they do not literally say that, but many readers might
infer it.)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
However, if you look at the report, you see something quite different.
The report directly states that,
&amp;#8220;This paper is not a critique of open source libraries,
and we caution against interpreting this analysis as such.&amp;#8221;
They only examined open source Java libraries,
but their &amp;#8220;experience in evaluating
the security of hundreds of custom applications indicates that the
findings are likely to apply to closed-source and commercial libraries
as well.&amp;#8221;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is a valuable report, because it points out a general problem
&lt;i&gt;not&lt;/i&gt; specific to OSS.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The problem is that
&lt;b&gt;software libraries (OSS or not)
are not being adequately managed, leading to a vast
number of vulnerabilities&lt;/b&gt;.
For example, the report states that
&amp;#8220;The data show that most organizations do not appear to have a strong process in place for ensuring
that the libraries they rely upon are up-to-date and free from known vulnerabilities.&amp;#8221;
They point out that
&amp;#8220;development teams readily acknowledge, often with some level of embarrassment,
that they make no efforts to keep their libraries up-to-date.&amp;#8221;
They also note that
&amp;#8220;Organizations download many old versions of libraries&amp;#8230;
If people were updating their libraries, we would have expected the popularity of older libraries to drop to zero within the first two years. However, the data clearly show popularity extending back over six years&amp;#8230;.
The continuing popularity of libraries for extended months suggests
that incremental releases of legacy applications are not being updated
to use the latest versions of libraries but are continuing to
use older versions.&amp;#8221;
They recommend that software development organizations inventory,
analyze, control, and monitor their libraries, and give details on each point.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I should note that I&amp;#8217;ve been saying some of these things for years.
For years I have said that you should
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/oss_fs_eval.html&quot;&gt;evaluate OSS before
you use it&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8230; some software is better than others.
Back in 2008 I also urged
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2008/09/19/&quot;&gt;developers to
use system libraries&lt;/a&gt;, at least as an option;
embedding libraries often leads over time to the use of old (and vulnerable)
libraries.
An advantage of OSS is that many people can review the software,
find problems (including vulnerabilities), and fix them&amp;#8230;
but this advantage is lost if the fixed versions are not used!
And of course, if you develop software, you need to learn
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/secure-programs/index.html&quot;&gt;how to
develop secure software&lt;/a&gt;.
As the report notes, tools can be useful
(I give away &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/flawfinder/&quot;&gt;flawfinder&lt;/a&gt;),
but tools cannot replace human knowledge and human review.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For more information, you should see their actual report,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aspectsecurity.com/blog/the-unfortunate-reality-of-insecure-libraries/&quot;&gt;&amp;#8220;The Unfortunate Reality of Insecure Libraries&amp;#8221; (by Aspect Security)&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
   </item>
  </channel>
</rss>