<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- name="generator" content="blosxom/2.0" -->

<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>David A. Wheeler's Blog   </title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog</link>
    <description>David A. Wheeler's weblog.</description>
    <language>en</language>

  <item>
    <title>FLOSS numbers database!</title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2014/05/08#numbers-database</link>
    <pubDate>Thu, 08 May 2014 22:22 GMT</pubDate>
    <!-- date: 2014-05-08 -->
    <description>
&lt;p&gt;
If you are doing research related to Free / Libre / Open Source Software
(FLOSS), then I have something that may be useful to you: the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/numbers-database/&quot;&gt;FLOSS numbers database&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
My paper
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/oss_fs_why.html&quot;&gt;Why Open Source Software / Free Software (OSS/FS, FLOSS, or FOSS)? Look at the Numbers!&lt;/a&gt;
is a big collection of quantitative studies about FLOSS.
Too big, in fact.
There have been a &lt;i&gt;lot&lt;/i&gt; of quantitative studies
about FLOSS over the years!
A lot of people want to query this information for specific purposes, 
and it is hard to pull out just the parts you want from a flat document.
I had thought that as FLOSS became more and more common, fewer
people would want this information&amp;#8230; but I still get requests for it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So I am announcing the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/numbers-database/&quot;&gt;FLOSS numbers database&lt;/a&gt;;
it provides the basic information in spreadsheet format,
making it easy to query for just the parts you want.
My special thanks go to Paul Rotilie, who worked to get the
data converted from my document format into the spreadsheet.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you want to discuss this database, I have set up a discussion group:
&lt;a href=&quot;https://groups.google.com/forum/#!forum/numbers-about-free-libre-open-source-software&quot;&gt;Numbers about Free Libre Open Source Software&lt;/a&gt;.
If you are doing research and need or use this kind of information,
please feel free to join.
If you just need a presenatation based on this, you might like my
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/numbers/&quot;&gt;Presentation: Why Free-Libre / Open Source Software (FLOSS or OSS/FS)? Look at the Numbers!&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This database is the sort of thing that if you need it, you really need it.
I am sure it is incomplete&amp;#8230; but I am also sure that with your
help, we can make it better.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
   </item>
  </channel>
</rss>