<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- name="generator" content="blosxom/2.0" -->

<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>David A. Wheeler's Blog   </title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog</link>
    <description>David A. Wheeler's weblog.</description>
    <language>en</language>

  <item>
    <title>U.S. government must balance its budget</title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2011/07/03#us-government-balance-budget</link>
    <pubDate>Sun, 03 Jul 2011 22:39 GMT</pubDate>
    <!-- date: 2011-07-03 -->
    <description>meta-markup: markdown

(This is a blog entry for U.S. citizens -- everyone else can ignore it.)

We Americans must *demand* that the U.S. government
work to balance its budget over time.

The U.S. government has a massive annual deficit, resulting
in a massive national debt that is growing beyond all reasonable bounds.
For example, in just
&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_federal_budget&quot;&gt;Fiscal Year (FY) 2010&lt;/a&gt;,
about $3.4 trillion was spent, but only
$2.1 trillion was received; that means that the U.S. government spent
more than a trillion dollars more than it received.
Every year that the government spends more than it receives it adds to the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pgpf.org/Special-Topics/The-Federal-Budget-Primer.aspx&quot;&gt;gross federal debt, which is now more than $13.6 trillion&lt;/a&gt;.

This is unsustainable.
The fact that this is unsustainable is certainly not news. The
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gao.gov/cghome/d08446cg.pdf&quot;&gt;U.S. Financial Condition and Fiscal Future Briefing (GAO, 2008)&lt;/a&gt;
says, bluntly, that the &quot;Current Fiscal Policy Is Unsustainable&quot;.
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fiscalcommission.gov/sites/fiscalcommission.gov/files/documents/TheMomentofTruth12_1_2010.pdf&quot;&gt;
&quot;The Moment of Truth:
Report of the National Commission on Fiscal Responsibility and Reform&quot;&lt;/a&gt;
similarly says
&quot;Our nation is on an unsustainable fiscal path&quot;.
Many others have said the same.
But even though it's not news, it needs to be yelled from the rooftops.

The fundamental problem is that too many Americans -- aka &quot;we the people&quot; --
have not (so far) been willing to face this unpleasant fact.
&lt;a href=&quot;http://transcripts.cnn.com/TRANSCRIPTS/1002/21/fzgps.01.html&quot;&gt;Fareed Zakaria nicely put this in February 21, 2010&lt;/a&gt;:
&quot; ... in one sense, Washington is delivering to the American people exactly what they seem to want. In poll after poll, we find that the public is generally opposed to any new taxes, but we also discover that the public will immediately punish anyone who proposes spending cuts in any middle class program which are the ones where the money is in the federal budget.
Now, there is only one way to square this circle short of magic, and that is to borrow money, and that is what we have done for decades now at the local, state and federal level ...
The lesson of the polls in the recent elections is that politicians will succeed if they pander to this public schizophrenia. So, the next time you accuse Washington of being irresponsible, save some of that blame for yourself and your friends&quot;.

But Americans must face the fact that we must balance the budget.
And we must face it now.
We must balance the budget the same way families balance
their budgets -- the government must raise income (taxes), lower
expenditures (government spending), or both.
Growth over time will not fix the problem.

If we do not do this very soon, it will spell economic disaster for the
U.S., and frankly, for much of the world.

*How* we rellocate income and outgo so that they match
needs to be a political process.
Working out compromises is what the political
process is supposed to be all about;
nobody gets everything they want, but eventually some sort of rough
priorities needs to be worked out for the resources available.
Compromise is not a dirty word to describe the job of politics;
it *is* the job.
In reality, I think we will need to both raise revenue and decrease spending.
I think we must raise taxes to some degree,
but we can't raise taxes on the lower or middle
class much; they don't have the money.
So yes, we will need to raise the taxes on the rich, but
we will not be able to solve this by taxing the rich out of the country.
Which means that we *must* cut spending somehow as well.
Just cutting defense spending won't work;
defense is only 20% of the entire budget.
In contrast, the so-called entitlements -- mainly
medicare, medicaid, and social security -- are 43% of the
government costs and rapidly growing in cost.
So I think we are going to have to lower entitlement spending;
that is undesirable, but we can't keep providing services
we can't pay for.
Raising the age before Social Security benefits can
normally be received is to me an obvious baby step, but again,
that alone will not solve the problem.
It's clearly possible to hammer out approaches to
make this work.
There must be a compromise worked out between various camps.

To get there, we need to specify and plan out the maximum debt that the
U.S. will incur in each year, decreasing that each year
(say, over a 10-year period).
We don't need to figure out ahead of time how that will be done;
we need to first agree that it must be done.
Then Congress (and the President) will need to work out, each year,
how to meet that requirement.
It doesn't need to be any of the plans that have been put
forward so far; there are lots of ways to do this.
But unless we agree that we must live within our means, we will not
be able to make the decisions necessary to do so.
The U.S. is not a Greece, at least not now, but we must make decisions
soon to prevent bad results.

In the next year, I suspect we will need to focus on short-term
recovery rather than balancing the budget.
And we must *not* default.
But we must set the plans in motion to stop the runaway deficit,
and get that budget balanced.
The only way to get there is for the citizenry to demand it stop,
before far worse things happen.
</description>
   </item>
  </channel>
</rss>