<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- name="generator" content="blosxom/2.0" -->

<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>David A. Wheeler's Blog   </title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog</link>
    <description>David A. Wheeler's weblog.</description>
    <language>en</language>

  <item>
    <title>Introduction to the autotools (autoconf, automake, libtool)</title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2012/03/19#introduction-autotools</link>
    <pubDate>Mon, 19 Mar 2012 00:01 GMT</pubDate>
    <!-- date: 2012-03-19 -->
    <description>
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#8217;ve recently posted a
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/autotools&quot;&gt;video titled
&amp;#8220;Introduction to the autotools (autoconf, automake, and libtool)&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt;.
If you develop software, you might find this video useful.
So, here&amp;#8217;s a little background on it, for those who are interested.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The &amp;#8220;autotools&amp;#8221; are a set of programs
for software developers that include at least autoconf, automake, and libtool.
The autotools make it easier to create or
distribute source code that (1) portably and automatically builds, (2)
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/essays/releasing-floss-software.html&quot;&gt;follows
common build conventions (such as DESTDIR)&lt;/a&gt;, and (3)
provides automated dependency generation if you&amp;#8217;re using C or C++.
They&amp;#8217;re primarily intended for Unix-like systems, but
they can be used to build programs for Microsoft Windows too.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The autotools are &lt;i&gt;not&lt;/i&gt; the only way to create source code releases
that are easily built and packaged.
Common and reasonable alternatives,
depending on your circumstances, include Cmake, Apache Ant, and Apache Maven.
But the autotools are one of the most widely-used such tools, especially
for programs that use C or C++ (though they&amp;#8217;re not limited to that).
Even if you choose to not use them for projects you control, if you are a
software developer, you are likely to encounter
the autotools in programs you use or might want to modify.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Years ago, the autotools were hard for developers to use and they
had lousy documentation.
The autotools &lt;i&gt;have&lt;/i&gt; significantly improved over the years.
Unfortunately, there&amp;#8217;s a lot of really obsolete documentation,
along with a lot of obsolete complaints about autotools, and it&amp;#8217;s
a little hard to get started with them (in part due to all this
obsolete documentation).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, I have created a little video introduction at
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/autotools&quot;&gt;http://www.dwheeler.com/autotools&lt;/a&gt; that I hope will give people a hand.
You can also view the video via YouTube (I had to split it into parts) as
&lt;a href=&quot;http://youtu.be/4q_inV9M_us&quot;&gt;Introduction to the autotools, part 1&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://youtu.be/tku2h_fPxhc&quot;&gt;Introduction to the autotools, part 2&lt;/a&gt;, and
&lt;a href=&quot;http://youtu.be/e-uYBb554LU&quot;&gt;Introduction to the autotools, part 3&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The entire video was created using free/libre / open source software
(FLOSS) tools. I am releasing it in the royalty-free webm video format,
under the Creative Commons CC-BY-SA license.
I am posting it to my personal site using the HTML5 video tag, which should
make it easy to use.
Firefox and Chrome users can see it immediately; IE9 users can see it once
they install a free webm driver.
I tried to make sure that the audio was more than loud enough to hear,
the terminal text was large enough to read, and that the quality of both
is high; a video that cannot be seen or heard is rediculous.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This video tutorial emphasizes how to use the various autotools pieces
together, instead of treating them as independent components,
since that&amp;#8217;s how most people will want to use them.
I used a combination of slides (with some animations) and the command line
to help make it clear.
I even walk through some examples, showing how to do some things step by step
(including using git with the autotools).
This tutorial gives simple quoting rules that will prevent lots of mistakes,
explains how to correctly create the &amp;#8220;m4&amp;#8221; subdirectory
(which is recommended but not fully explained in many places), and
discusses why and how to use a non-recursive make.
It is merely an introduction, but hopefully it will be enough to help
people get started if they want to use the autotools.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
   </item>
  </channel>
</rss>