<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- name="generator" content="blosxom/2.0" -->

<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>David A. Wheeler's Blog   </title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog</link>
    <description>David A. Wheeler's weblog.</description>
    <language>en</language>

  <item>
    <title>Software patents &amp;#8212; keep protesting</title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2004/11/23#patent-20041123</link>
    <pubDate>Tue, 23 Nov 2004 12:35 GMT</pubDate>
    <!-- date: 2004-11-23 -->
    <description>
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://nosoftwarepatents.com/en/m/intro/app0411.html&quot;&gt;
Linus Torvalds (lead developer of the Linux kernel),
Michael Widenius (lead for MySQL) and Rasmus Lerdorf (lead for PHP)
have written an appeal to the EU Council against
software patents in Europe.&lt;/a&gt;
This letter is useful as yet another ray of sunlight into
a sea of deceptive practices.  Here&amp;#8217;s what the letter reveals:
&amp;#8220;The draft directive in question is deceptive because it leads laymen, and even
those legal professionals who are not familiar with the intricacies of patent
law, to falsely believe that it would exclude software from patentability.
However, it is actually a compilation of the entirety of the excuses with
which the patent system has, for many years, been circumventing article 52 of
the European Patent Convention in order to grant patents on software ideas.&amp;#8221;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I think that the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://webshop.ffii.org/&quot;&gt;patented webshop&lt;/a&gt; in particular
shows why patents have always been excluded from patenting
in Europe (and were originally excluded everywhere, until big money
bought the laws of some countries).
You should also see this
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ffii.org.uk/ftc/ftc.html&quot;&gt;link
to relevant excerpts from the U.S. Federal
Trade Commission Report&lt;/a&gt;.
For example:
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Many panelists and participants expressed the view that software
and Internet patents are impeding innovation.
They stated that such patents are impairing follow-on incentives,
increasing entry barriers, creating uncertainty that harms
incentives to invest in innovation, and producing patent thickets.
Panelists discussed how defensive patenting increases the complexity
of patent thickets and forces companies to divert resources from
R&amp;amp;D into obtaining patents.
Commentators noted that patent thickets make it more
difficult to commercialize new products and raise uncertainty
and investment risks. Some panelists also noted that hold-up
has become a problem that can result in higher prices being passed
along to consumers. 
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
Note that after discussing the various ways that patents
are intended to spur innovation,
&amp;#8220;Commentators were generally skeptical about the benefits of the
patent system in these [software and Internet] industries.&amp;#8221;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You can see
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/blackout.html&quot;&gt;
my patent blackout page&lt;/a&gt;, so you can get its information even when it&amp;#8217;s
not the front page of my site.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; 
For more information on the problem, and how you can help
stop this absurd notion, see
&lt;a href=&quot;http://nosoftwarepatents.com/&quot;&gt;NoSoftwarePatents.com&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ffii.org&quot;&gt;the FFII&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
   </item>
  </channel>
</rss>