<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- name="generator" content="blosxom/2.0" -->

<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>David A. Wheeler's Blog   </title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog</link>
    <description>David A. Wheeler's weblog.</description>
    <language>en</language>

  <item>
    <title>New presentation on Government and OSS/FS (LinuxWorld 2004, eGov)</title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2004/02/02#new-government-oss</link>
    <pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2004 14:43 GMT</pubDate>
    <!-- date: 2004-02-02 -->
    <description>
I&amp;#8217;ve just posted a new presentation,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/government_oss.pdf&quot;&gt;What Should
Governments Examine in Acquiring COTS Open Source Software (OSS)?&lt;/a&gt;
This is the presentation I gave at
LinuxWorld on January 22, 2004 (with a few tweaks).
LinuxWorld was in New York City&amp;#8217;s Javits center, and many U.S. government
folks weren&amp;#8217;t there.
So, I&amp;#8217;m also going to be giving the same presentation
on February 3, 2004, at the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.e-gov.com/events/2004/we_gov/conference&quot;&gt;Web-enabled
Government conference&lt;/a&gt; in Washington, DC (at the Ronald Reagan building).
In both cases this presentation is part of a set of short presentations
by panel members, followed by a panel question and answer period.
If you&amp;#8217;re curious, the other panelists include
Tony Stanco (George Washington University), Terry Bollinger (MITRE),
and Peter Gallagher (devIS).
If you&amp;#8217;re not curious, I can&amp;#8217;t help you.
&lt;p&gt;
This presentation is pretty short; it has to be, since each of
us has only has 10 minutes to give our initial presentation.
So much information had to be kept out to fit in 10 minutes&amp;#8217; time!!
Still, I think this presentation would be
useful for those who are thinking about
the relationship betwen governments and
open source software / Free Software (OSS/FS).
I talk about in what way OSS/FS is the same as proprietary software,
how OSS/FS is different in terms of its implications,
challenges in employing OSS/FS, and closing remarks.
I think the challenges in particular need more thinking about.
For example, acquisition processes were designed before OSS/FS was common;
it&amp;#8217;s easy to unintentionally exclude perfectly good OSS/FS options from
consideration.
&lt;p&gt;
This presentation is yet another example of a minor terminology problem.
I normally use &amp;#8220;OSS/FS&amp;#8221; in my writing, as a broad term covering the
definitions of both open source software (as defined by OSI)
and Free Software (as defined by the FSF).
However, &amp;#8220;OSS/FS&amp;#8221; is a complicated thing to say.
In this briefing, I just use the term &amp;#8220;OSS&amp;#8221;; for this audience,
that works reasonably well.
However, some seem to think that this term
excludes &amp;#8220;Free Software&amp;#8221; (I don&amp;#8217;t mean to), and
for some government types this term is slightly confusing
(since &amp;#8220;open source&amp;#8221; in governmentese means &amp;#8220;available to the public&amp;#8221;).
I&amp;#8217;m thinking about starting to use the term
&amp;#8220;FLOSS&amp;#8221; (Free-Libre / Open Source Software), since FLOSS is easier to
say and deals with the problem that to many, &amp;#8220;free software&amp;#8221; means
&amp;#8220;free of cost&amp;#8221; and not the intended &amp;#8220;freedoms provided&amp;#8221;.
F/OSS (Free / Open Source Software)
is also easy to say, but that phrase leaves the second problem untouched.
It&amp;#8217;d be far too much of a hassle to change my current documents, though.
Since FLOSS has &amp;#8220;open source software&amp;#8221; embedded in it, people searching
for &amp;#8220;open source software&amp;#8221; could at least still find it.
&lt;p&gt;
One last-minute addition to the presentation is a set of web sites
that might be of special interest to someone examining the issue of
government and open source software.
I&amp;#8217;ve listed as interesting papers my own
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/oss_fs_why.html&quot;&gt;Why OSS/FS?
Look at the Numbers!&lt;/a&gt; paper,
the MITRE &amp;#8220;Use of Free and Open Source Software in the US Dept. of Defense&amp;#8221;,
the President&amp;#8217;s Information Technology Advisory Committee (PITAC) - Panel
on Open Source Software for High End Computing, and the
DoD policy memo &amp;#8220;Open Source Software (OSS) in the DoD&amp;#8221; signed by
John P. Stenbit (DoD Chief Information Officer) on May 28, 2003.
Interesting sites include the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.egovos.org&quot;&gt;Center of Open Source and Government
(eGovOS)&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://opensector.org&quot;&gt;OpenSector.org&lt;/a&gt;,
and
the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.osaia.org&quot;&gt;Open Source and Industry Alliance&lt;/a&gt;.
And of course, the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.opensource.org&quot;&gt;Open Source Initiative (OSI)&lt;/a&gt;
and
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fsf.org&quot;&gt;Free Software Foundation (FSF)&lt;/a&gt;.
Obviously there are many other potentially interesting sites and papers;
a longer list is in my list of
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/oss_fs_refs.html&quot;&gt;OSS/FS references&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;p&gt;
Note that, as with all things on my personal site, this
presentation is not formally endorsed by my employer, government,
or guinea pig.  I&amp;#8217;ll work on the guinea pig.
</description>
   </item>
  </channel>
</rss>