<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- name="generator" content="blosxom/2.0" -->

<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>David A. Wheeler's Blog   </title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog</link>
    <description>David A. Wheeler's weblog.</description>
    <language>en</language>

  <item>
    <title>Microsoft Office XML (OOXML) massively defective</title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2008/03/21#ooxml-200803</link>
    <pubDate>Fri, 21 Mar 2008 18:48 GMT</pubDate>
    <!-- date: 2008-03-21 -->
    <description>
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.robweir.com/blog/2008/03/how-many-defects-remain-in-ooxml.html&quot;&gt;Robert Weir has been analyzing Microsoft&amp;#8217;s Office XML spec
(aka OOXML) to determine how defective it is&lt;/a&gt;, with disturbing results.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Most standards today are relatively small, build on other standards, and
are developed publicly over time with lots of opportunity for correction.
Not OOXML; Emca submitted Office Open XML
for &amp;#8220;Fast Track&amp;#8221; as a
&lt;a href=&quot;http://fussnotes.typepad.com/plexnex/2007/05/ooxml_more_than_1.html&quot;&gt;
massive 6,045 page specification&lt;/a&gt;, developed in an
absurdly rushed way, behind closed doors, using a process controlled
by a single vendor.
It&amp;#8217;s huge primarily because does everything in a non-standard way,
instead of referring to other standards where practical as standards are
&lt;i&gt;supposed&lt;/i&gt; to do (e.g., for mathematical equations they created their
own incompatible format instead of using the MathML standard).
All by itself, its failure to build on other standards should have
disqualified OOXML, but it was accepted for review anyway, and what
happened next was predictable.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
No one can seriously review such a massive document in a short time, though
ISO tried; ISO&amp;#8217;s process did find 3,522 defects.
It&amp;#8217;s not at all clear that the defects were fixed -
there&amp;#8217;s been no time to really check, because the process for reviewing
the standard simply wasn&amp;#8217;t designed to handle that many defects.
But even if they were fixed - a doubtful claim -
Robert Weir has asked another question, &amp;#8220;did they find nearly all of the
defects?&amp;#8221;.
The answer is: Almost all of the original defects &lt;i&gt;remain&lt;/i&gt;.
By sampling pages, he&amp;#8217;s found error after error, none of which were found by
the ISO process.
The statistics from the sample are very clear: practically all serious
errors have &lt;i&gt;not&lt;/i&gt; been found.
It&amp;#8217;s true that good standards sometimes have a few errors left in them,
after review, but this isn&amp;#8217;t &amp;#8220;just a few errors&amp;#8221;; these clearly show that
the specification is intensely defect-ridden.
Less than 2% of the defects have been found, by the data we have so far,
which suggests that there are over 172,000 important defects (49x3522)
left to find.
That&amp;#8217;s rediculous.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Want more evidence that it&amp;#8217;s defect-ridden?
Look at
&lt;a
href=&quot;http://surguy.net/articles/ooxml-validation-and-technical-review.xml&quot;&gt;
Inigo Surguy&amp;#8217;s
&amp;#8220;Technical review of OOXML&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt;, where he examines
just the WordProcessingML section&amp;#8217;s 2300 XML examples.
He wrote code to check for well-formedness and validation errors,
and found that more than 10% (about 300) were in error even given this
trivial test.
Conclusion?
&amp;#8220;While a
certain number of errors is understandable in any large specification, the
sheer volume of errors indicates that the specification has not been through a
rigorous technical review before becoming an Ecma standard, and therefore may
not be suitable for the fast-track process to becoming an ISO standard.&amp;#8221;
This did not include the other document sections, and
this is a lower bound on accuracy (XML could validate and still be
in error).
(He also confirmed that Word 2007 does not implement
the extensibility requirements of the Ecma specification, so as a result it
would be hard to
&amp;#8220;write an interoperable word processor with Word&amp;#8221; using OOXML.)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I think that all by itself, these vast number of errors in OOXML prove that the
&amp;#8220;Fast Track&amp;#8221; process is completely inappropriate for OOXML.
The &amp;#8220;Fast Track&amp;#8221; process was intended to be used when there was already
a widely-implemented, industry-accepted standard that had already had its
major problems addressed.
That&amp;#8217;s just not the case here.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
These huge error rates were predictable, too.
The committee for creating OOXML wasn&amp;#8217;t even &lt;i&gt;created&lt;/i&gt; until OpenDocument
was complete, so they
&lt;i&gt;had&lt;/i&gt; to do a massive rush job to produce &lt;i&gt;anything&lt;/i&gt;.
(&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.noooxml.org/forum/t-19484/microsoft-has-to-rush-to-keep-its-office-revenue-stream&quot;&gt;
Doug Mahugh admitted that
&amp;#8220;Microsoft&amp;#8230; had to rush this standard through.&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt;)
They didn&amp;#8217;t reuse existing mature standards, so they ended up creating
much more work for themselves.
Most developers (who could have helped find and fix the defects)
stayed away from the Ecma process in the first
place; its rules gave one vendor complete control over what was allowed,
and there was already a vendor-independent standard in place, which gave
most experts no reason to participate.
The Ecma process was also almost entirely closed-door
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.robweir.com/blog/2006_07_01_robweir_archive.html&quot;&gt;
(OpenDocument&amp;#8217;s mailing lists are public, in contrast)&lt;/a&gt;,
which predictably increased the error rate too.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The GNOME Foundation has been involved in OOXML&amp;#8217;s development, and here&amp;#8217;s what they say in the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://foundation.gnome.org/about/gnome_annual_report_2007.pdf&quot;&gt;
GNOME Foundation Annual Report 2007&lt;/a&gt;:
&amp;#8220;The GNOME Foundation’s involvement in ECMA TC45-M (OOXML) was the main discussion point during the last meeting&amp;#8230;. [the] Foundation does not support this file format as the main format or as a standard&amp;#8230;&amp;#8221;
I don&amp;#8217;t think this is as widely touted as it should be.
Here&amp;#8217;s an organization
&lt;i&gt;directly involved&lt;/i&gt; in OOXML development,
and it thinks OOXML should not be a standard at all.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.groklaw.net/article.php?story=20080320121533442&quot;&gt;
India has already voted &amp;#8220;no&amp;#8221; to OOXML&lt;/a&gt;.
I hope others do the same.
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.groklaw.net/article.php?story=20080319130708601&quot;&gt;
Countries with the appropriate rights have until March 29 to decide.&lt;/a&gt;
It&amp;#8217;s quite plausiable that the final vote will be &amp;#8220;no&amp;#8221;, and indeed,
based on what&amp;#8217;s published, it &lt;i&gt;should&lt;/i&gt; be &amp;#8220;no&amp;#8221;.
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.openmalaysiablog.com/2008/03/geneva-day-five.html&quot;&gt;
Open Malaysia&lt;/a&gt; reported on the March 2008 BRM meeting, for example.
It reports that everybody &amp;#8220;did their darnest to improve the spec&amp;#8230;
The final day was absolute mayhem. We had to submit decisions on over 500
items which we hadn&amp;#8217;t [had] the time to review. All the important issues which
have been worked on repeatedly happened to appear on this final day. So it was
non-stop important matters&amp;#8230;
It was a failure of the Fast Track process, and Ecma for choosing it. It
should have been obvious to the administrators that submitting a 6000+ page
document which failed the contradiction period, the 5 month ballot vote and
poor resolution dispositions, should be pulled from the process. It should
have been blatantly obvious that if you force National Bodies to contribute in
the BRM and end up not deliberating on over 80% of their concerns, you will
make a lot of people very unhappy&amp;#8230;
judging from the reactions from the National Bodies who
truly tried to contribute on a positive manner,
without having their concerns heard let alone resolved, they leave the
BRM with only one decision in their mind come March 29th.
The Fast Tracking process is NOT suitable for ISO/IEC DIS 29500. It will fail
yet again.  And this time it will be final.&amp;#8221;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In my opinion, the OOXML specification should not become an international
standard, period.
I think it clearly doesn&amp;#8217;t meet the criteria for &amp;#8220;fast track&amp;#8221; - but
more importantly, it doesn&amp;#8217;t meet the needs for being a standard at all.
It completely contradicts the goal of
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.iso.org/iso/pressrelease.htm?refid=Ref832&quot;&gt;
&amp;#8220;One standard, one test - Accepted everywhere&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt;, and it
simply is not an open standard.
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2007/06/05/&quot;&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve blogged before
that having multiple standards for office documents is a terrible idea&lt;/a&gt;.
There&amp;#8217;s nothing wrong with a vendor publishing their internal format;
in fact,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.noooxml.org/open:rejectooxmlnow&quot;&gt;
ISO&amp;#8217;s &amp;#8220;type 2 technical report&amp;#8221; or &amp;#8220;ISO agreement&amp;#8221;
are pre-existing mechanisms for documenting the format of a
single vendor and product line specification&lt;/a&gt;.
But when important data is going to be exchanged between parties,
it should be exchanged using an open standard.
We already have an open standard for office documents that was developed
by consensus and implemented by multiple vendors: OpenDocument (ISO/IEC 26300).
For more clarification about what an open standard is, or
why OpenDocument is an open standard, see my essay
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/essays/opendocument-open.html&quot;&gt;
&amp;#8220;Is OpenDocument an Open Standard? Yes!&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt;
OpenDocument works very well; I use it often.
In contrast, it seems clear that OOXML will never be
a specification that everyone can fully implement.
Its technical problems alone are serious, but even more importantly, the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.softwarefreedom.org/resources/2008/osp-gpl.html&quot;&gt;
Software Freedom Law Center&amp;#8217;s
&amp;#8220;Microsoft&amp;#8217;s Open Specification Promise: No Assurance for GPL&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt;
makes it clear that OOXML cannot be legally implemented by anyone
using any license.
And this matters greatly.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://consortiuminfo.org/standardsblog/article.php?story=20080224143425160&quot;&gt;
Andy Updegrove calls for recognition of &amp;#8220;Civil ICT Standards&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt;, which
I think helps puts this technical stuff into a broader and
more meaningful context.
He notes that in our new &amp;#8220;interconnected world,
virtually every civic, commercial, and expressive human activity
will be fully or partially exercisable only via the Internet,
the Web and the applications that are resident on, or interface
with, them.  And in the third world, the ability to accelerate one’s progress
to true equality of opportunity will be mightily dependent on whether one has
the financial and other means to lay hold of this great equalizer&amp;#8230;
[and thus] public policy relating to
information and communications technology (ICT) 
will become as important, if not more,
than existing policies that relate to freedom of travel (often now being
replaced by virtual experiences), freedom of speech (increasingly expressed on
line), freedom of access (affordable broadband or otherwise), and freedom to
create (open versus closed systems, the ability to create mashups under
Creative Commons licenses, and so on)&amp;#8230;
This is where standards enter the picture, because standards are where policy
and technology touch at the most intimate level.
Much as a constitution establishes and balances the basic rights of an
individual in civil society, standards codify the points where proprietary
technologies touch each other, and where the passage of information is
negotiated&amp;#8230;
what will life be like in the future if Civil ICT Rights are not recognized and
protected, as paper and other fixed media disappear, as information becomes
available exclusively on line, and as history itself becomes hostage to
technology?
I would submit that a vote to adopt OOXML would be a step away from, rather
than a way to advance towards, a future in which Civil ICT Rights are
guaranteed&amp;#8221;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.raffee.co.za/post/29079077&quot;&gt;
Ms. Geraldine Fraser-Moleketi,
Minister of Public Service and Administration, South Africa, gave an
interesting presentation at the
Idlelo African Conference on FOSS and the Digital Commons&lt;/a&gt;.
She said,
&amp;#8220;The adoption of open standards by governments is a critical factor in
building interoperable information systems which are open, accessible,
fair and which reinforce democratic culture and good governance practices.
In South Africa we
have a guiding document produced by my department called the Minimum
Interoperability Standards for Information Systems in Government (MIOS). The
MIOS prescribes the use of open standards for all areas of information
interoperability, including, notably, the use of the Open Document Format
(ODF) for exchange of office documents&amp;#8230;
It is unfortunate that the leading vendor of office software, which enjoys
considerable dominance in the market, chose not to participate and support ODF
in its products, but rather to develop its own competing document standard
which is now also awaiting judgement in the ISO process. If it is successful,
it is difficult to see how consumers will benefit from these two overlapping
ISO standards&amp;#8230;  The proliferation of multiple standards in
this space is confusing and costly.&amp;#8221;
She also said,
&amp;#8220;One cannot be in Dakar without being painfully aware of the tragic history of
the slave trade&amp;#8230;
As we find ourselves today in this new era of the globalised Knowledge Economy
there are lessons we can and must draw from that earlier era. That a crime
against humanity of such monstrous proportions was justified by the need to
uphold the property rights of slave owners and traders should certainly make
us more than a little cautious about what should and should not be considered
suitable for protection as property.&amp;#8221;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You can get more detail from the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.groklaw.net/staticpages/index.php?page=20051216153153504&quot;&gt;
Groklaw ODF-MSOOXML main page&lt;/a&gt;, but I think the point is clear.
The world doesn&amp;#8217;t need the confusion of a specification 
controlled by a single vendor being labelled as an international standard.
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.noooxml.org/open:rejectooxmlnow&quot;&gt;NoOOXML has a list
of reasons to reject OOXML&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
   </item>
  <item>
    <title>Twisted Mind of the Security Pro</title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2008/03/21#twisted-mind</link>
    <pubDate>Fri, 21 Mar 2008 10:08 GMT</pubDate>
    <!-- date: 2008-03-21 -->
    <description>
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wired.com/politics/security/commentary/securitymatters/2008/03/securitymatters_0320&quot;&gt;Bruce Schneier&amp;#8217;s
&amp;#8220;Inside the Twisted Mind of the Security Professional&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt;
is highly-recommended reading - he explains the different kind of thinking
required to be good at making things secure.
Security pros are able to see the bigger picture, and in particular, they are
able to see things from from an attacker&amp;#8217;s perspective.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For example,
&amp;#8220;SmartWater is a liquid with a unique identifier linked to a particular
owner. &amp;#8216;The idea is for me to paint this stuff on my valuables as proof
of ownership,&amp;#8217; I wrote when I first learned about the idea. &amp;#8216;I think
a better idea would be for me to paint it on your valuables, and then
call the police.&amp;#8217;&amp;#8221;
Similarly, on opening up an ant farm, his friend was surprised that the
manufacturer would send you ants by mail; Bruce thought it was interesting that
&amp;#8220;these people will send a tube of live ants to anyone you tell them to.&amp;#8221;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Being able to think like an attacker is so important that in my
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/secure-programs/&quot;&gt;
book on writing secure programs&lt;/a&gt;,
I gave it its own heading:
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/secure-programs/Secure-Programs-HOWTO/paranoia.html&quot;&gt;paranoia is a virtue&lt;/a&gt;.
It&amp;#8217;s still true.
My thanks to Bruce Schneier for expressing this need so eloquently.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We would live in a better world if &lt;i&gt;all&lt;/i&gt; of us could see the world
as attackers do - or at least make the effort to try.
In particular, we&amp;#8217;d stop doing many foolish things in the name of
&amp;#8220;security&amp;#8221;, and instead do things that actually secured our world.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
   </item>
  <item>
    <title>OSS and the U.S. DoD - Questions and Answers</title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2008/03/11#oss-dod-qa2008</link>
    <pubDate>Tue, 11 Mar 2008 20:19 GMT</pubDate>
    <!-- date: 2008-03-11 -->
    <description>
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#8217;ve just posted
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/essays/dod-oss-qa.html&quot;&gt;
Questions and Answers for 2008 &amp;#8220;Open Source Software and DoD&amp;#8221; Webinar&lt;/a&gt;.
These are my attempts to answer the questions people sent me at my February
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/oss-dod-webinar2008.html&quot;&gt;
&amp;#8220;Open Source Software (OSS) and the U.S. Department of Defense (DoD)&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt;
Some of the questions were easy to answer, but some were surprisingly
difficult.
In some cases, I asked lawyers and got conflicting answers.
But this is the best information that I could find on the topic.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For example, I explain in detail why
In particular, it appears fairly clear that
both the government and government contractors can
release their results as open source software under the default
DoD contract terms for software development
(&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.acq.osd.mil/dpap/dars/dfars/html/current/252227.htm#252.227-7014&quot;&gt;DFARS contracting clause 252.227-7014&lt;/a&gt;):
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The government can release software as OSS once it receives
&amp;#8220;unlimited rights&amp;#8221; to it.
Unless other arrangements are made,
the government has unlimited rights to software components when (1) it
pays entirely for their development, or (2) five years after
contract signature if it partly paid for their development.
Before award, a contractor may identify the components that will have more
restrictive rights (e.g., so the government can prefer proposals
that give the government more rights).
Where possible, software developed partly by government funds
should broken into a set of smaller components at the
&amp;#8220;lowest practicable level&amp;#8221;
so the rules can be applied separately to each one.
Of course, the software can only be released to the public as OSS
if other laws are also met
(such as classification, export control, patent law, and trademark law).
&lt;li&gt;
Normally a DoD contractor can release the software as OSS at any time,
since it holds the copyright.
This default can be overridden by the contract, e.g.,
&lt;a
href=&quot;http://www.acq.osd.mil/dpap/dars/dfars/html/current/252227.htm#252.227-7020&quot;&gt;DFARS
252.227-7020&lt;/a&gt;
assigns copyright to the government, and is included in some contracts.
Again, this release can only occur if other laws are also met
(such as classification, export control, patent law, and trademark law).
&lt;/ol&gt;
These are the usual defaults; negotiations can change things, so read
the contract to see if the contract changes these defaults.
For example, sometimes the government has copyright assigned to it,
in which case it can release the software simply because it has the copyright.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I also point out that even when the government isn&amp;#8217;t the copyright holder,
if it releases software under an OSS license it can still enforce its license.
That&amp;#8217;s because, even when it&amp;#8217;s not the copyright holder, it can still enforce
the license&amp;#8230; and because the doctrine of unclean hands will impact
those who refuse to obey the license.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Several people had questions about software developed by a government
employee (which can&amp;#8217;t be copyrighted in the U.S.) and how that impacts OSS.
The short impact is that there&amp;#8217;s no problem; government employees can
still contribute to OSS projects, for example.
I also discuss some of the export control issues (especially ITAR), and
how to address them.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If there are mistakes, please let me know. Thanks!
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
   </item>
  </channel>
</rss>