<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- name="generator" content="blosxom/2.0" -->

<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>David A. Wheeler's Blog   </title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog</link>
    <description>David A. Wheeler's weblog.</description>
    <language>en</language>

  <item>
    <title>E-Password comment deadline (April 4) looms - COMMENT NOW</title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2005/03/23#epassword</link>
    <pubDate>Wed, 23 Mar 2005 17:02 GMT</pubDate>
    <!-- date: 2005-03-23 -->
    <description>
&lt;p&gt;
As noted in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wired.com/news/privacy/0,1848,66686,00.html?tw=rss.TOP&quot;&gt;a Wired article&lt;/a&gt;,
the U.S. Department of State plans to issue U.S. passports that can be
read wirelessly (remotely), and it won&amp;#8217;t even encrypt this
extremely personal data.  This plan is absurd; it appears to give
terrorists and organized crime a way to remotely identify U.S. citizens
(for murder or kidnapping) and to provide enough detailed personal
information to significantly aid identity theft.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The Department of State
claims that the new passports can only be read from 10 centimeters and
that fibers will prevent any reading while closed.  However, most security
experts scoff at these claims,
noting that people have to open their passports eventually,
and doubting that the fiber&amp;#8217;s protection will be perfect anyway
in real life. Lee Tien,
an attorney at the Electronic Frontier Foundation, reports the reading
distance as more like 10-30 feet. Bruce Schneier, who just renewed
his passport to make sure he will not have an unencrypted passport for
another 10 years, says he has yet to hear a good argument as to why the
government is requiring remotely readable chips instead of a contact
chip &amp;#8212; which could hold the same information but would not be skimmable.
&amp;#8220;A contact chip would be so much safer.&amp;#8221;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I think this Department of State plan is going to kill people.
There are people in this world who want to hurt or kill Americans,
or citizens of some other countries &amp;#8212;
now we&amp;#8217;re giving them an easy tool to help them find Americans (or
citizens of some other countries) in
foreign countries so that they can be murdered, tortured, raped,
or kidnapped for ransom.
The ransom stuff alone would fund &lt;i&gt;huge&lt;/i&gt; efforts to use this
technology in foreign countries to target victims, because it&amp;#8217;d
be insanely profitable for the immoral.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In my mind, the real problem is the use of wireless technology.
This is an area where the convenience of wireless is far outweighed
by the disadvantages of getting murdered.
Frankly, for data storage, a 2D barcode (which is MUCH cheaper) would
have all the advantages of permitting quick storage of a lot of data.
If the purpose of the chip is to make forgery harder, then requiring
contact would be sufficient.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Is the lack of encryption a problem? Not necessarily, as long as
contact is required.
After all, if there&amp;#8217;s no encryption, then it&amp;#8217;s easier to see exactly
what data is on the passport (e.g., to verify that it&amp;#8217;s correct for you),
and the data is supposed to be the same as what&amp;#8217;s already on the
passport.
But it&amp;#8217;s a disaster if it&amp;#8217;s wireless, because then people who have no
business getting the data will be able to retrieve it.
Indeed, it&amp;#8217;s a disaster that this is wireless at all.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Those who wish to protest this plan have until April 4, 2005,
to send their comments to
&lt;a href=&quot;mailto:PassportRules@state.gov&quot;&gt;PassportRules@state.gov&lt;/a&gt;.
I urge you to send in emails asking State to abandon this wireless
approach, and that they instead use a system that requires contact.
Do it, before someone dies.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
   </item>
  </channel>
</rss>