<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- name="generator" content="blosxom/2.0" -->

<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>David A. Wheeler's Blog   </title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog</link>
    <description>David A. Wheeler's weblog.</description>
    <language>en</language>

  <item>
    <title>Flawfinder version 1.27 released!</title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2007/01/16#flawfinder-1.27</link>
    <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jan 2007 23:41 GMT</pubDate>
    <!-- date: 2007-01-16 -->
    <description>
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#8217;ve released yet another new version of
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/flawfinder&quot;&gt;flawfinder&lt;/a&gt; - now
it&amp;#8217;s version 1.27.
Flawfinder is a simple program that examines C/C++ source code and
reports on likely security flaws in the program, ranked by risk level.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The big functional addition is that flawfinder can now
examine &lt;i&gt;just the changes&lt;/i&gt; in a program.
If you&amp;#8217;re modifying a big program, it can be overwhelming to view all
of the warnings flawfinder can produce&amp;#8230; but if you can look at only the
ones relevant to the change &lt;i&gt;you&lt;/i&gt; are making, it can be easier to handle.
My thanks to Sebastien Tandel - he suggested the feature, I replied
in a brief email describing how I thought it could be done, and
&lt;i&gt;in the same day&lt;/i&gt; he replied with code to implement it.
Wow, that&amp;#8217;s truly amazing.  His original patch only worked with Subversion;
I modified it so that it also works with GNU diff.
For this to work, you use the new &amp;#8220;&amp;#8212;patch&amp;#8221; option and give flawfinder
a patch file (in unified diff format) that describes the changes&amp;#8230; and
flawfinder will only report on the potential vulnerabilities on the
changed lines (or the lines immediately above and below them).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
An administrative change is that
&lt;a href=&quot;https://sourceforge.net/projects/flawfinder/&quot;&gt;
flawfinder is now hosted on SourceForge.net&lt;/a&gt;, with a mailing list
and a Subversion repository for code changes.
This should make it easier for people to discuss the program,
submit changes, and generally keep track of things.
And it also deals nicely with the &amp;#8220;what happens if he&amp;#8217;s hit by a bus&amp;#8221;
problem.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
You can view the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/flawfinder/ChangeLog&quot;&gt;Flawfinder
ChangeLog&lt;/a&gt; for the details on the other changes.
It deals more gracefully with unreadable files and when there are zero
lines of code.
Also, it now skips by default any directories beginning with &amp;#8220;.&amp;#8221;;
this makes it work nicely with many SCM systems
(use &amp;#8220;&amp;#8212;followdotdir&amp;#8221; if you WANT it to enter such directories).
My thanks to Steve Kemp, cmorgan, and others.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For more info, or a copy,
just go to my
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/flawfinder&quot;&gt;original flawfinder home page&lt;/a&gt;
or the new
&lt;a href=&quot;https://sourceforge.net/projects/flawfinder/&quot;&gt;
flawfinder page on SourceForge.net&lt;/a&gt;.
Enjoy!
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
   </item>
  </channel>
</rss>