<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- name="generator" content="blosxom/2.0" -->

<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>David A. Wheeler's Blog   </title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog</link>
    <description>David A. Wheeler's weblog.</description>
    <language>en</language>

  <item>
    <title>Twisted Mind of the Security Pro</title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2008/03/21#twisted-mind</link>
    <pubDate>Fri, 21 Mar 2008 10:08 GMT</pubDate>
    <!-- date: 2008-03-21 -->
    <description>
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wired.com/politics/security/commentary/securitymatters/2008/03/securitymatters_0320&quot;&gt;Bruce Schneier&amp;#8217;s
&amp;#8220;Inside the Twisted Mind of the Security Professional&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt;
is highly-recommended reading - he explains the different kind of thinking
required to be good at making things secure.
Security pros are able to see the bigger picture, and in particular, they are
able to see things from from an attacker&amp;#8217;s perspective.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For example,
&amp;#8220;SmartWater is a liquid with a unique identifier linked to a particular
owner. &amp;#8216;The idea is for me to paint this stuff on my valuables as proof
of ownership,&amp;#8217; I wrote when I first learned about the idea. &amp;#8216;I think
a better idea would be for me to paint it on your valuables, and then
call the police.&amp;#8217;&amp;#8221;
Similarly, on opening up an ant farm, his friend was surprised that the
manufacturer would send you ants by mail; Bruce thought it was interesting that
&amp;#8220;these people will send a tube of live ants to anyone you tell them to.&amp;#8221;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Being able to think like an attacker is so important that in my
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/secure-programs/&quot;&gt;
book on writing secure programs&lt;/a&gt;,
I gave it its own heading:
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/secure-programs/Secure-Programs-HOWTO/paranoia.html&quot;&gt;paranoia is a virtue&lt;/a&gt;.
It&amp;#8217;s still true.
My thanks to Bruce Schneier for expressing this need so eloquently.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We would live in a better world if &lt;i&gt;all&lt;/i&gt; of us could see the world
as attackers do - or at least make the effort to try.
In particular, we&amp;#8217;d stop doing many foolish things in the name of
&amp;#8220;security&amp;#8221;, and instead do things that actually secured our world.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
   </item>
  </channel>
</rss>