<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- name="generator" content="blosxom/2.0" -->

<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>David A. Wheeler's Blog   </title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog</link>
    <description>David A. Wheeler's weblog.</description>
    <language>en</language>

  <item>
    <title>I&amp;#8217;ll be speaking at some Linux User Groups (LUGs)</title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2006/05/17#lugs2005</link>
    <pubDate>Wed, 17 May 2006 00:40 GMT</pubDate>
    <!-- date: 2006-05-17 -->
    <description>
&lt;p&gt;
A while ago I was asked to speak at some of the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tux.org/&quot;&gt;Linux User Groups (LUGs)&lt;/a&gt;
in the Washington, DC area, and I agreed to do so.
Here are the current plans, if you are interested in hearing me speak:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;May 17, 2006, 7pm: &lt;a href=&quot;http://dclug.tux.org/&quot;&gt;DCLUG&lt;/a&gt;,
Washington, DC. &amp;#8220;FLOSS and security.&amp;#8221;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://dclug.tux.org/dclug_meetings.html&quot;&gt;Get directions&lt;/a&gt; to
their meeting location: 2025 M Street NW, Washington DC.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;July 1, 2006, 10am:
&lt;a href=&quot;http://novalug.tux.org/&quot;&gt;NovaLUG&lt;/a&gt;.
Meeting is at
Washington Technology Park/CSC (formerly Dyncorp),
15000 Conference Center Drive, Chantilly, VA.
(I&amp;#8217;ve just sent an email to confirm, but that&amp;#8217;s the date I have.)
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;July 12, 2006, 7pm: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.calug.com/&quot;&gt;Columbia LUG&lt;/a&gt;.
&amp;#8220;Open Standards and Security (and OpenDocument too)&amp;#8221;
Meeting is at HP, 8890 McGaw Rd Ste 100, Columbia, MD.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Plans may change, but this is the information I have for now.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
   </item>
  <item>
    <title>High Assurance (for Security or Safety) and Free-Libre / Open Source Software (FLOSS)</title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2006/05/06#high-assurance-floss</link>
    <pubDate>Sat, 06 May 2006 10:52 GMT</pubDate>
    <!-- date: 2006-05-06 -->
    <description>
&lt;p&gt;
Recently I spoke at an
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.opengroup.org/&quot;&gt;Open Group&lt;/a&gt;
conference and gave my presentation on
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/essays/oss_software_assurance.pdf&quot;&gt;
Open Source Software and Software Assurance (Security)&lt;/a&gt;.
While there, someone asked a very interesting question:
&amp;#8220;What is the relationship between high assurance and
open source software?&amp;#8221;
That&amp;#8217;s a fair question, and although I gave a quick answer,
I realized that a longer and more thoughtful answer was really needed.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So I&amp;#8217;ve just posted a paper to answer the question:
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/essays/high-assurance-floss.html&quot;&gt;High Assurance (for Security or Safety) and Free-Libre / Open Source Software (FLOSS)&lt;/a&gt;.
For purposes of the paper,
I define &amp;#8220;high assurance software&amp;#8221;
as software where there&amp;#8217;s an &lt;i&gt;argument
that could convince skeptical parties&lt;/i&gt;
that the software &lt;i&gt;will always perform or never perform&lt;/i&gt;
certain key functions &lt;i&gt;without fail&lt;/i&gt;.
That means you have to show convincing evidence that there are
&lt;i&gt;absolutely no software defects&lt;/i&gt;
that would interfere with the software&amp;#8217;s key functions.
Almost all software built today is &lt;i&gt;not&lt;/i&gt; high assurance;
developing high assurance software is currently a specialist&amp;#8217;s field.
But I think all software developers &lt;i&gt;should&lt;/i&gt; know a little about
high assurance.
And it turns out there are lots of connections between
high assurance and FLOSS.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The relationships between high assurance and FLOSS are interesting.
Many tools for developing high assurance
software are FLOSS, which I can show by examining the areas of
software configuration management, testing,
formal methods, analysis implementation, and code generation.
However, while high assurance components are rare, FLOSS high assurance
components are even rarer.
This is in contrast to medium assurance, where there are a vast number
of FLOSS tools and FLOSS components, and the security record of FLOSS
components is quite impressive.
The paper then examines why this is the circumstance.
The most likely reason for this appears to
be that decision-makers for high assurance components
are not even considering the possibility of FLOSS-based approaches.
The paper concludes that in the future,
those who need high assurance components should
consider FLOSS-based approaches as a possible strategy.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Anyway, it&amp;#8217;s a thought piece; if you&amp;#8217;re interested in making software
that is REALLY reliable, I hope you&amp;#8217;ll find it interesting.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Again, the paper is here: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/essays/high-assurance-floss.html&quot;&gt;High Assurance (for Security or Safety) and Free-Libre / Open Source Software (FLOSS)&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
   </item>
  </channel>
</rss>