<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- name="generator" content="blosxom/2.0" -->

<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>David A. Wheeler's Blog   </title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog</link>
    <description>David A. Wheeler's weblog.</description>
    <language>en</language>

  <item>
    <title>Planet definition problems, and Pluto too</title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2006/09/01#planet-problems</link>
    <pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2006 20:01 GMT</pubDate>
    <!-- date: 2006-09-01 -->
    <description>
&lt;p&gt;
Well, at the last minute
International Astronomical Union (IAU) changed their
proposed definition of the term &amp;#8220;planet&amp;#8221;, and voted on it.
Pluto is no longer a planet!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Well, maybe.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Usually definitions like this go through a lot of analysis;
I think this one was rushed through at the last minute.
I see three problems: It was an irregular vote, it&amp;#8217;s vague as written,
and it doesn&amp;#8217;t handle faraway planets well.
Let&amp;#8217;s look at each issue in turn.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This was a pretty irregular vote, I think.
As I noted, at the last minute the proposal changed, with no time
for deeply examining it.
There were
&lt;a href=&quot;http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/science/nature/5283956.stm&quot;&gt;2,700
attendees, but only 424 astronomers (about 10%)
voted on the proposal that &amp;#8220;demoted&amp;#8221; Pluto&lt;/a&gt;.
And only a few days after the vote,
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.livescience.com/blogs/2006/08/31/300-astronomers-wont-use-new-planet-definition/&quot;&gt;300 astronomers have signed a petition saying
they do not accept this IAU definition&lt;/a&gt; - almost as many as
voted in the first place.
That doesn&amp;#8217;t sound like consensus to me.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
More importantly, it&amp;#8217;s too vague.
That&amp;#8217;s not just my opinion;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.space.com/scienceastronomy/060831_planet_definition.html&quot;&gt;
Space.com notes that there&amp;#8217;s a lot of uncertainty about it&lt;/a&gt;.
Now a planet has to control its zone&amp;#8230; but Earth doesn&amp;#8217;t, there
are &lt;i&gt;lots&lt;/i&gt; of objects that cross Earth&amp;#8217;s orbit.
Does this mean that Earth is not a planet?
I haven&amp;#8217;t seen any published commentary on it, but I think there&amp;#8217;s even
a more obvious problem - Neptune is clearly &lt;i&gt;not&lt;/i&gt; a planet, because
it hasn&amp;#8217;t cleared out Pluto and Charon.
A definition which is that vague is not an improvement.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
But in my mind, the worst problem with this definition is a practical one:
it doesn&amp;#8217;t handle other planets around other stars well.
We are too far away to observe small objects around other stars, and I think
we will always be able to detect larger objects but not smaller ones
in many faraway orbits.
So when we detect an object in another galaxy with the mass of Jupiter,
and it&amp;#8217;s orbiting a star, is it a planet?
Well, under this current definition we don&amp;#8217;t know if it&amp;#8217;s a planet
or not.
Why? Because we may not be able to know what else is there in orbit.
And &lt;i&gt;that&lt;/i&gt; is a real problem.
I think it&amp;#8217;s clear that we will always be able to observe some larger objects
without being able to detect the presence of smaller ones.
If we can&amp;#8217;t use the obvious word, then the definition is useless - so
we need a better definition instead.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I thought the previous proposal (orbits a star, enough mass to become round)
was a good one, as I noted earlier in
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2006/08/21/#planet&quot;&gt;
What&amp;#8217;s a planet? Why I&amp;#8217;m glad there&amp;#8217;s an argument&lt;/a&gt;.
I think they should return to that previous definition,
&lt;i&gt;or&lt;/i&gt; find some other definition
that is (1) much more precise and (2) lets us use the term &amp;#8220;planet&amp;#8221;
in a sensible way to discuss large non-stars that are
orbiting faraway stars.
Whether Pluto is in, or not.
Of course, none of this affects reality; this is merely a definition war.
But clear terminology is important in any science.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I still think that what&amp;#8217;s great
about this debate is that it has caused many people to discuss and think about
what&amp;#8217;s happening in the larger universe, instead of focusing on the transient.
That is probably the most positive result of all.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
   </item>
  </channel>
</rss>