<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- name="generator" content="blosxom/2.0" -->

<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>David A. Wheeler's Blog   </title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog</link>
    <description>David A. Wheeler's weblog.</description>
    <language>en</language>

  <item>
    <title>Using Wikipedia for research</title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2010/03/21#wikipedia-research</link>
    <pubDate>Sun, 21 Mar 2010 21:58 GMT</pubDate>
    <!-- date: 2010-03-21 -->
    <description>
&lt;p&gt;
Some teachers seem to lose their minds when asked about
&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org&quot;&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;,
and make absurd rules like
&lt;a href=&quot;http://modeltrains.about.com/od/railroads/tp/Wikipedia.htm&quot;&gt;
&amp;#8220;I forbid students from using Wikipedia&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.kioskea.net/news/10362-once-shunned-by-academics-wikipedia-now-a-teaching-tool&quot;&gt;A 2008 article&lt;/a&gt;
states that Wikipedia is the encyclopedia
&amp;#8220;that most universities forbid students to use&amp;#8221;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
But the professors don&amp;#8217;t need to be such Luddites; it turns out
that college students tend to use Wikipedia quite appropriately.
A research paper titled
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.uic.edu/htbin/cgiwrap/bin/ojs/index.php/fm/article/view/2830/2476&quot;&gt;
&lt;i&gt;How today&amp;#8217;s college students use Wikipedia for
course-related research&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
examines Wikipedia use among college students; it found that
Wikipedia use was widespread, and that
the primary reason they used Wikipedia was to
obtain background information or a summary about a topic.
Most respondents reported using Wikipedia at the beginning
of the research process; very few used Wikipedia near or at the end.
In focus group sessions, students described Wikipedia as
&amp;#8220;the very beginning of the very beginning for me&amp;#8221; or
&amp;#8220;a .5 step in my research process&amp;#8221;, and that it helps primarily in the
beginning because it provided a
&amp;#8220;simple narrative that gives you a grasp&amp;#8221;.
Another focus group participant called Wikipedia &amp;#8220;my presearch tool&amp;#8221;.
Presearch, as the participant defined it, was &amp;#8220;the stage of research
where students initially figure out a topic, find out about it, and
delineate it&amp;#8221;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Now, it&amp;#8217;s perfectly reasonable to say that Wikipedia should not
be cited as an original source;
I have no trouble with professors making &lt;i&gt;that&lt;/i&gt; rule.
Wikipedia itself has a rule that
&lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wikipedia:No_original_research&quot;&gt;
Wikipedia does not publish original research or original thought&lt;/a&gt;.
Indeed, the same is true for &lt;i&gt;Encyclopedia Britannica&lt;/i&gt;
or any other encyclopedia;
encyclopedias are supposed to be &lt;i&gt;summaries&lt;/i&gt; of knowledge gained
elsewhere.
You would expect that college work would normally &lt;i&gt;not&lt;/i&gt; have
many citations of any encyclopedia, be it Wikipedia or
Encyclopedia Britannica, simply because encyclopedias
are &lt;i&gt;not&lt;/i&gt; original sources.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Rather than running in fear from new materials and techologies,
teachers should be helping students understand how to use them appropriately,
helping them consider the strengths and weaknesses of their
information sources.
Wikipedia should not be the end of any serious research,
but it&amp;#8217;s a reasonable place to start.
You should supplement it with other material, for the simple reason that
you should &lt;i&gt;always&lt;/i&gt; examine multiple sources no matter where you start,
but that doesn&amp;#8217;t make Wikipedia less valuable.
For younger students, there are reasonable concerns about inappropriate
material (e.g., due to Wikipedia vandalism and because Wikipedia covers topics
not appropriate for much younger readers), but the derivative
&lt;a href=&quot;http://schools-wikipedia.org/&quot;&gt;
&amp;#8220;Wikipedia Selection for Schools&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt; 
is a good solution for that problem.
I&amp;#8217;m delighted that so much information is available to people everywhere;
we need to help people &lt;i&gt;use&lt;/i&gt;
these resources instead of &lt;i&gt;ignoring&lt;/i&gt; them.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
And speaking of which, if you like Wikipedia, please help!
With a little effort, you can make it better for everyone.
In particular, Wikipedia needs more video;
please help the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://videoonwikipedia.org/index.html&quot;&gt;Video on Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;
folks get more videos on Wikipedia.
This also helps the cause of open video, ensuring that the
Internet continues to be open to innovation.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
   </item>
  </channel>
</rss>