<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- name="generator" content="blosxom/2.0" -->

<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>David A. Wheeler's Blog   </title>
    <meta name="viewport" content="width=device-width, initial-scale=1.0"></meta>
    <link>https://www.dwheeler.com/blog</link>
    <description>David A. Wheeler's weblog.</description>
    <language>en</language>

  <item>
    <title>Removing www prefix on this website due to Chrome nonsense</title>
    <meta name="viewport" content="width=device-width, initial-scale=1.0"></meta>
    <link>https://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2018/09/26#removing-www</link>
    <pubDate>Wed, 26 Sep 2018 21:10 GMT</pubDate>
    <!-- date: 2018-09-26 -->
    <description>
&lt;p&gt;
The Chrome web browser is starting to lie to users about the URL you
are viewing, for example, by removing &amp;#8220;www.&amp;#8221; if it is a prefix.
I do not like this, because I think it is dangerous to tell people
incorrect information.
I&amp;#8217;ve had a website for a very long time, and when I started it,
the recommended practice was to use &amp;#8220;www.&amp;#8221; prefixes for websites&amp;#8230;
so that is what I have been doing.
Since I cannot prevent Chrome from lying, and I want people to accurately see
name of the website they are looking at, I&amp;#8217;m going to switch this
site&amp;#8217;s standard name to be &amp;#8220;dwheeler.com&amp;#8221;
instead of &amp;#8220;www.dwheeler.com&amp;#8221;.
That will not fix the problem for other sites, but it will fix it for this one.
I will set up a redirection and slowly switch some links to the new name.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
   </item>
  <item>
    <title>Plans for HTTPS (SSL/TLS) on this site</title>
    <meta name="viewport" content="width=device-width, initial-scale=1.0"></meta>
    <link>https://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2015/03/11#https</link>
    <pubDate>Wed, 11 Mar 2015 19:50 GMT</pubDate>
    <!-- date: 2015-03-11 -->
    <description>
&lt;p&gt;
Currently this website uses only HTTP, and does not support HTTPS.
That means that users cannot trivially authenticate what they receive, and
that in some cases users reveal to others what they are viewing on the site.
(Technical note:
HTTPS is implemented by a lower-level protocol; the current protocol
versions of this protocol are named TLS, and the older ones
are named SSL, but a lot of people use the term SSL to include TLS.)
I would &lt;i&gt;like&lt;/i&gt; to use HTTPS, but this website is entirely self-funded.
I do have a plan, though.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
My current plan is that I am waiting for
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2014/11/certificate-authority-encrypt-entire-web&quot;&gt;Let&amp;#8217;s encrypt&lt;/a&gt; to stand up and be ready.
Once that gets going, I intend to use it to add support for HTTPS.
I&amp;#8217;d like to eventually &lt;i&gt;only&lt;/i&gt; support HTTPS, since that prevents
downgrade attacks, but I need to make sure that the TLS certificates
and configuration works well.
Also, I pay others to maintain the server;
since I am not made of money, I necessarily use low-end cheap services.
That will limit what I can do in terms of HTTPS configuration hardening.
On the other hand, it should be better than the current situation.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The &lt;i&gt;software&lt;/i&gt; I develop is generally
available on SourceForge or GitHub, and they already provide HTTPS,
so you don&amp;#8217;t need to wait for that.
Currently
&lt;a href=&quot;https://sourceforge.net/p/forge/site-support/9807&quot;&gt;you
have to log into SourceForge to get HTTPS&lt;/a&gt;, but that is expected to change,
and for now just log in.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Anyway, I thought some of you might like to know that there &lt;i&gt;is&lt;/i&gt; a plan.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
   </item>
  <item>
    <title>Twitter</title>
    <meta name="viewport" content="width=device-width, initial-scale=1.0"></meta>
    <link>https://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2014/10/13#twitter-username</link>
    <pubDate>Mon, 13 Oct 2014 15:41 GMT</pubDate>
    <!-- date: 2014-10-13 -->
    <description>
&lt;p&gt;
My username on Twitter is
&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/drdavidawheeler&quot;&gt;drdavidawheeler&lt;/a&gt;,
for those on Twitter who want occasional comments
on computer security, open source software, software development,
and so on.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
   </item>
  <item>
    <title>Moving hosting service at end of January 2009</title>
    <meta name="viewport" content="width=device-width, initial-scale=1.0"></meta>
    <link>https://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2009/01/08#moving</link>
    <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2009 11:57 GMT</pubDate>
    <!-- date: 2009-01-08 -->
    <description>
&lt;p&gt;
I will be moving to a new hosting service at the end of January 2009.
(I haven&amp;#8217;t determined which hosting service yet.)
In theory, there should be very little downtime, but it&amp;#8217;s possible
the site will be off for a little while.
But if that happens, it will be very temporary - I&amp;#8217;ll
get the site back up as soon as I can.
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
   </item>
  <item>
    <title>My upcoming presentations - Date change and a new page</title>
    <meta name="viewport" content="width=device-width, initial-scale=1.0"></meta>
    <link>https://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2006/06/04#presentations</link>
    <pubDate>Sun, 04 Jun 2006 22:07 GMT</pubDate>
    <!-- date: 2006-06-04 -->
    <description>
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#8217;m still giving a presentation at NovaLUG, but the
date has been changed from July 1 to July 8 (2006).
This is because July 4 is a U.S. holiday (independence day),
and there was concern that some people might not be able to come.
So it will now be July 8, 10am,
&amp;#8220;Free-Libre/Open Source Software (FLOSS) and Security&amp;#8221;.
Washington Technology Park/CSC (formerly Dyncorp),
15000 Conference Center Drive, Chantilly, VA.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This has convinced me that I need a page to help people
find when and where I&amp;#8217;m speaking, so that they don&amp;#8217;t have to
march through my blogs to get the information.
So here it is&amp;#8230;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/presentations.html&quot;&gt;
Presentations by David A. Wheeler.&lt;/a&gt;
Just click on it, and you&amp;#8217;ll get the latest times, places, etc., of
where to go if you just can&amp;#8217;t find something better
to do with your life :-).
&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
   </item>
  <item>
    <title>Sorry for the website unavailability&amp;#8230;</title>
    <meta name="viewport" content="width=device-width, initial-scale=1.0"></meta>
    <link>https://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2004/09/29#sep2004-down</link>
    <pubDate>Wed, 29 Sep 2004 23:15 GMT</pubDate>
    <!-- date: 2004-09-29 -->
    <description>
For those of you who were trying to reach the website recently &amp;#8212;
sorry about that!
The website was unavailable for a little while.
The problem wasn&amp;#8217;t on the website system itself,
but on a communications link (at the ATM level) to the outside world.
In any case, it&amp;#8217;s obviously been fixed, and hopefully we won&amp;#8217;t
be having that kind of problem again&amp;#8230;. at least for a very long time.
</description>
   </item>
  <item>
    <title>Reorganizing the home page</title>
    <meta name="viewport" content="width=device-width, initial-scale=1.0"></meta>
    <link>https://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2004/02/10#homepage-reorg</link>
    <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2004 18:37 GMT</pubDate>
    <!-- date: 2004-02-10 -->
    <description>
I now have so much information on my website that I decided
a little reorganization was necessary.  Hopefully, you&amp;#8217;ll
like the new look and find it more helpful.
&lt;p&gt;
The main thing I&amp;#8217;ve done is
put the various links in multiple columns, so that more will
fit on the screen or on paper.  Also, I&amp;#8217;ve added a way to
quickly search this site for information (it uses Google).
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#8217;m not done; I intend to soon add above the search capability
a set of items like this:
&lt;pre&gt;
My Blog | About Site | About Me | Contact Me
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The home page is now automatically generated; I use
a self-created XSLT script to extract the most recent blog entries
(from /blog/index.rss), and use sed to update the front page with them.
</description>
   </item>
  </channel>
</rss>