<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- name="generator" content="blosxom/2.0" -->

<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>David A. Wheeler's Blog   </title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog</link>
    <description>David A. Wheeler's weblog.</description>
    <language>en</language>

  <item>
    <title>The Cautionary Tale of XFree86</title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2004/07/23#xfree86</link>
    <pubDate>Fri, 23 Jul 2004 13:29 GMT</pubDate>
    <!-- date: 2004-07-23 -->
    <description>
Well, it&amp;#8217;s been many months, and the sad tale of XFree86
is now clear to all.
At one time, if you used a Unix-like machine with a graphical
user interface, it was very likely that you were using
the results of the XFree86 project.
But not now.
Much of the code of the XFree86 project will live on in the
X.org project, but the
XFree86 project itself has now been abandoned by nearly all.
&lt;p&gt;
This is an important tale that needs recording, and telling.
Cautionary tales about hubris,
and ignoring both the people you lead and your customers,
can sometimes help others to avoid the same mistakes.
Hopefully, by recording such tales, there will be fewer similar tales
to tell in the future.
And in many ways this is a story of hope and triumph;
it shows how developers and customers joined and revolted together
against an extremely unpopular decision, and
eventually got their needs met instead.
In fact, customers ended up with a very simple transition path, one
which is hard to imagine for a proprietary product.
Rarely are &amp;#8220;votes of no confidence&amp;#8221; in the OSS/FS world
so obvious and so powerful.
&lt;p&gt;
I&amp;#8217;ve now documented XFree86&amp;#8217;s demise in more detail as a
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/essays/gpl-compatible.html#xfree86&quot;&gt;
new appendix on XFree86&lt;/a&gt;.
The appendix is part of my essay about
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/essays/gpl-compatible.html&quot;&gt;GPL
compatibility&lt;/a&gt;.
In short, the XFree86 leader decided that GPL compatibility
was unimportant to customers and developers, ignoring all those
who tried to explain otherwise.
Customers and developers got fed up, established a competing fork,
and switched en mass.
In the end, the customers and developers got GPL compatibility,
just as they demanded.
</description>
   </item>
  <item>
    <title>Countering Spam Using Email Passwords</title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2004/07/08#spam-email-password</link>
    <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jul 2004 12:16 GMT</pubDate>
    <!-- date: 2004-07-08 -->
    <description>
I&amp;#8217;ve been having a great deal of success countering spam
using a simple technique that I call &amp;#8220;email passwords&amp;#8221;.
It&amp;#8217;s been &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/contactme.html&quot;&gt;mentioned
on my website for a long time&lt;/a&gt;, but I thought
it might be helpful to others if I gave a more detailed description
of them and how they work.
&lt;p&gt;
As a result, I&amp;#8217;ve just released a short essay titled
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/essays/spam-email-password.html&quot;&gt;
&amp;#8220;Countering Spam Using Email Passwords&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt;
which describes email passwords, including how they work
and how to implement them.
The idea is pretty simple: if a stranger wants to contact you,
tell them to include an &amp;#8216;email password&amp;#8217; in the subject line.
Then provide the email password in a shrouded way on your website
so that legitimate senders can get it, but so
it&amp;#8217;s a pain for a spammer to get.
If a spammer gets the email password, you can simply change it.
I also use a &amp;#8220;reply indicator&amp;#8221; text phrase in my replies, so that legitimate
replies are also less likely to be labelled as spam.
But simple isn&amp;#8217;t necessarily bad!
Combined with other anti-spam tricks (like whitelists,
content filters, and blacklists), I get really useful results.
&lt;p&gt;
I suspect other people have done this too, but I haven&amp;#8217;t
seen anything written about email passwords before.
Maybe it&amp;#8217;s in many places and I just missed it; sorry if I have.
Maybe some people will point me to prior work
(I could update my essay to reference some).
But since I&amp;#8217;ve read about many anti-spam approaches without seeing
a discussion of this approach, I suspect others haven&amp;#8217;t heard of this either.
It&amp;#8217;s similar to challenge-response systems, but there&amp;#8217;s no actual challenge.
While it&amp;#8217;s not perfect, it definitely helps.
&lt;p&gt;
In the long term, I believe that governments must step in and
make spamming illegal, with serious legal teeth (including possible
prison terms and financial bankrumptcy)
for the spammer and the people who fund them, as well
as making spamming itself illegal (instead of just fraudulent headers
and spamming after a &amp;#8220;please stop&amp;#8221; message).
Spamming is a massive denial-of-service attack against people&amp;#8217;s
email accounts, and it&amp;#8217;s basically a theft of service.
After all, it doesn&amp;#8217;t matter if you own an email account
if you can&amp;#8217;t use it.
But the history of computer crime law shows that this takes time;
it took a long time for laws to be written to criminalize computer crime,
and it&amp;#8217;s really still in process.
Current laws are completely ineffective (especially the U.S. law),
but that&amp;#8217;s not surprising; lawmakers often try to make small steps in
the hopes that they will solve the problem.
Eventually laws with real teeth
will have to be written, or email will be useless.
Since legislatures like to use email, and have constituents who will
throw them out if their email is taken away, in the long term this will
be addressed.
&lt;p&gt;
But in the short term, we need to use email in spite of inadequate laws.
Approaches like email passwords will hopefully make it possible to
keep using our email until the legislatures around the world
catch up to the technology.
&lt;p&gt;
If you&amp;#8217;re curious, you can also see my
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/essays/stopspam.html&quot;&gt;essay on stopping spam&lt;/a&gt;
and my
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/guarded-email&quot;&gt;paper on guarded email&lt;/a&gt;.
I&amp;#8217;ve also written several articles on other topics you may find interesting,
including
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/secure-programs&quot;&gt;writing secure programs&lt;/a&gt;
and
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com/oss_fs_why.html&quot;&gt;quantitative
reasons why you should consider open source software / Free Software
when acquiring software&lt;/a&gt;.
And of course, you can always
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dwheeler.com&quot;&gt;visit my home page&lt;/a&gt;.
</description>
   </item>
  <item>
    <title>New release of &amp;#8220;Why OSS/FS? Look at the Numbers!&amp;#8221;</title>
    <link>http://www.dwheeler.com/blog/2004/07/07#oss-why-20040707</link>
    <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jul 2004 18:38 GMT</pubDate>
    <!-- date: 2004-07-07 -->
    <description>

I&amp;#8217;ve made a new release of my paper &amp;#8220;Why Open Source Software /
Free Software (OSS/FS)? Look at the Numbers!&amp;#8221;
It&amp;#8217;s a tome, and getting even longer, as more stuff becomes
available.
This is basically a minor release, with various small additions
and improvements here and there.
Here are some highlights:
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
I&amp;#8217;ve added references to the interesting paper
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sims.berkeley.edu/~hal/Papers/2004/linux-adoption-in-the-public-sector.pdf&quot;&gt;
Linux Adoption in the Public Sector: An Economic Analysis&lt;/a&gt;
by Hal R. Varian and Carl Shapiro (University of California, Berkeley;
1 December 2003).
&lt;li&gt;
I&amp;#8217;ve also added lots of information on the
major Microsoft Internet Explorer vulnerability that&amp;#8217;s been
undergoing a lot of press.
IE has been undergoing some really nasty exploitation as of
mid June 2004, and Microsoft only released a &amp;#8220;fix&amp;#8221; on July 2, 2004;
but Microsoft had NINE MONTHS to fix it, and didn&amp;#8217;t.
OSS customers can patch their systems, but a proprietary
customer doesn&amp;#8217;t have that option. A proprietary vendor that
ignores such a nasty vulnerability for that long is performing a
nearly criminal act; they&amp;#8217;re at least aiding criminals.
That&amp;#8217;s especially crazy because Microsoft has said they&amp;#8217;ve been
working hard on security since 2002; I think that&amp;#8217;s probably true,
but this sure is a SCARY lapse.
CERT and SANS recommend switching away from IE
as one of the options for IE users.
&lt;li&gt;
I added a reference to the
&lt;a href=&quot;http://news.com.com/Indian+president+calls+for+open+source+in+defense/2100-7344_3-5259836.html&quot;&gt;
Indian presidential announcement&lt;/a&gt; about OSS/FS.
&lt;li&gt;
Added a link to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cospa-project.org/&quot;&gt;COSPA project&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
Fixed typos, per very helpful comments from Ian McIntosh.
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
   </item>
  </channel>
</rss>